Turn 30 - 2484.5 - To the Midnight Sun, where the Eight Winds Flow

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [TOWER] Grey Battery [*] [LIBRARY] Kislev: Imperial Extensive and Esoteric, Dwarf Extensive and Antiquarian (450gc, 2 DF), Chaos Wastes: Imperial Extensive and Antiquarian, Dwarf Extensive (300gc, 2 CF) [*] [DWARF] No purchase. [*] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [*] [PURCHASE] No purchase. Once more the Council is a litany of grumblings about the Okral, but though the situation remains unchanged, it does seem like keeping the Okral on task and avoiding any actual incidents beyond verbal sniping is a win. You're glad to be well free of a situation where a great deal of effort needs to be expended just to maintain the status quo. Everyone's eyes are on the Okral's departure date in a year and a half, and it seems that every single Dwarf in the Karak would agree that it can't come soon enough. When it comes time for you to report, you get the definite impression that everyone's hoping you'll bring something more interesting to the table than the usual chorus, so with a flourish you scatter Ulgu across the table and shape it with a thought into a map of the north. You could have brought a conventional map, but doing it with magic has such flair to it, and acclimating your fellow Councillors to magic is a nice side-benefit. "The Karag Dum Expedition will travel through the Empire and Kislev to Praag, and then along the Road of Skulls until it reaches the Great Steppes, where it will turn north and chart a direct course to Karag Dum. For transport, they have five Monitor-sized 'steam-wagons', and may have more by the time they depart. Optimistic projections say it will be about two weeks from Praag to Karag Dum, while more conservative ones say about a month each way. One third of that will be spent in the deeper Wastes." "Monitor-sized is mighty large for overland travel," Gotri says thoughtfully. "What's the terrain like?" "The Road of Skulls is well travelled by carts, and the Great Steppes are mostly flat. The only concern is the weather, which is currently dictating the timetable." "Total forces?" Dreng asks. "Currently, fifty Engineers, fifty Slayers, and about a hundred and fifty Rangers, mostly of the Redbeards. Each Monitor also has a pair of cannon on swivels." "I assume Borek's nominally in charge," Belegar says. "But he's neither Engineer nor Ranger. Who's calling the shots?" "Gotrek Gurnisson on the Engineering side-" "Good Dwarf," Gotri says. "Was a rising star before he married a Clanless, and even now he's too good for Zhufbar to completely cut ties." "-and Snorri Farstrider for the Rangers." "That one's spent too long under the open sky," Dreng says. "But for an overland trek, there's none better." "The biggest problem that I can see so far is that Borek is still dreaming of reconnecting Karag Dum, rather than clearing it out." "The High King's doing," Kazrik says. "Ever since he brought news of our northern kin and was crowned for it, dreamers have been imagining holdouts in every Hold from Karak Zorn to Karak Vlag to Karaz Ghumzul, and some even gossip of Holds over the seas." "They don't have the forces to retake it or meaningfully reinforce it, but he might be thinking of regaining contact with it in the same way Karaz-a-Karak kept contact with Karak Azul," Edda says, with a smile at Kazrik. "I can't criticize him too much for wanting to retake his ancestral home," Belegar says slowly, "but Karag Dum is in a very different situation to what Karak Eight Peaks was in." "Karag Dum was once on the border of the Chaos Wastes, but the Great War Against Chaos pushed the border as south as Praag, and it's only slightly receded since then," says Gunnars, trying to tap Northern Kislev and frowning as his finger pokes a hole in the projection. "If Karag Dum still holds out, I fear they're now in the same situation as those who went east found themselves in, back at the start of the Golden Age." A grim silence falls upon the table at that. None want to admit the possibility that Dwarves could fall to Chaos, but Zharr-Naggrund is a constant reminder that not even the Dwarves are immune to that temptation. "I'll do what I can to strengthen the Expedition so we can know, one way or the other," is all you can say to that. Mandatory Actions: Pick one from each category. Journeyman Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his metalworking studies. [ ] MAX: Recruit him for the Karag Dum Expedition, and have him train in preparation for it. (NEW) [ ] MAX: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Write a paper: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which. Must be taken with a 'dictate' action. Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Have him continue to teach Adela what he knows of engineering. (NEW-ish) [ ] JOHANN: Recruit him for the Karag Dum Expedition, and have him train in preparation for it. (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks [ ] DUCK: Work with Panoramia to try to implement the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. [ ] DUCK: Panoramia's about ready to test for Magister, but she's putting it off because she doesn't have a lot of free time to prepare. Work with her to help make the most of every spare minute. [ ] DUCK: Help Johann train his rat-wolf children. [ ] DUCK: Aid Hubert in his search for a Familiar. (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Gretel and the Besiegers for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Hubert and some Winter Wolves for the Karag Dum Expedition. (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Adela and some human siege weapons and operators for the Karag Dum Expedition. (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Esbern and Seija and their compatriots of the Knights of Taal's Fury. (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Each of your three ducklings can fight in melee. Spar with them, and teach them what you can. [ ] DUCK: Study an artefact with one of the Journeymen: specify who and which. The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 175 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Expansion along the Aver EIC Handler: The Hochlander [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. Will remove this section from future turns and regain the half-turn invested in it. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander introduce a series of ciphers to the EIC to allow it to communicate internally in much greater security. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) (NEW) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Julia to find out if she's interested in being poached or passing on information. [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Start building a paramilitary river navy to ensure the coming trade explosion doesn't lead to a similar explosion in riverine banditry. [ ] EIC: Sell some of the Grand Urbaz Bank coins to collectors and museums on King Belegar's behalf. [ ] EIC: Integrate the Gong Farmers and the Niter Factory into the EIC, and expand production. [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. Personal Actions: you have four actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. Current overwork status: [+] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. Current Task: Karag Dum Expedition preparations [ ] Seek out merchants who have travelled the Skull Road to learn what they know of it. [ ] Trawl around the bars and brothels of Tilea, looking to talk to the actual mercenaries that have walked either the Skull Road, or the Great Steppes. [ ] Attempt to recruit assistance for the Karag Dum Expedition. (specify the individual, mercenary group, cult, College, or other; two choices per AP spent) (NEW-ish) [ ] With the help of a gyrocarriage, personally scout part of the route (specify: High Pass, Road of Skulls, Western Great Steppes, Karag Dum vicinity) [ ] Try to contact the Ice Witches of Kislev in the hopes they can provide clement weather for the Expedition. [ ] Attempt to learn the Greenskin tongue to communicate with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Attempt to learn Kurgan to communicate with the Kurgan of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Kurgan of the Steppes. Spoiler: Qrech Qrech [ ] Despite him considering it treasonous, push Qrech to share the Moulder dialect of Queekish. [ ] Despite him considering it blasphemous, push Qrech to share High Queekish. Qrech Gambits (can be taken for free alongside a Qrech option): [ ] Convince Qrech that you seek an arrangement with Clan Moulder, and that you will release him as an ambassador for that arrangement once you are satisfied he'll cooperate. [ ] Convince Qrech that the Under-Empire has no way of knowing he's even alive, and that he should prioritize the comfort with which he will live the rest of his life. [ ] Convince Qrech you're ambitious and loyal only to yourself, and you're willing to repay his cooperation in ways that will benefit the Under-Empire. [ ] Other (write in) Self-Improvement: [ ] Ask an acquaintance to train you in a skill: specify who and what. [ ] Attempt to learn a spell from scrolls (specify which, will be harder than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Hire a trainer to come to Eight Peaks and teach you: specify what. (costs favours for Dwarf or College trainers, money for human ones) [ ] Travel to the Grey College and attend lessons there. (1 College Favour per class; 100gc can be paid instead for non-magical classes) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Gain enough control of your unruly shadow to still it temporarily. [ ] Gain enough control of your attraction to smoke and gases to have it collect away from your face. [ ] Learn the secret behind Gehenna's Golden Hounds. (NEW) [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Try to create them. [ ] Have one of Prince Gotri's pilots teach you to fly a gyrocopter. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. (NEW) Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] Dictate papers: select which two, must be taken with Max's 'receive dictation'. [ ] Investigate the possibility of using one Wind to directly manipulate another. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. [ ] Try to establish a relationship with the Cult of Verena, with the intent of offering them access to your rarer tomes in exchange for copies of some of their own. [ ] Record all the entries of the Grand Urbaz vaults and select a good-quality example of each minting to save from the smelters. Aethyric Vitae (12 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item with a Fiendishly Complex or easier spell (specify what and which) [ ] Attempt to enchant an object to translate Windsight into a visual image. [ ] Attempt to deepen your skill with Enchantment (will be more difficult than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Turn a staff from mundane materials. [ ] Turn a staff from the horn of a Storm Dragon. [ ] Turn a staff from the bone of a Shard Dragon. (NEW) Karag Nar Penthouse: each turn, you get ONE free choice in this category. Additional selections cost actions. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have a tower built atop Karag Nar: -100gc for 1 room, bonus to room's purpose. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have additional rooms excavated underneath your Penthouse: -125gc for 5 rooms. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Your dungeon was built with a reasonable amount of paranoia. Apply an unreasonable amount of paranoia. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add security measures to your Penthouse to prevent forcible entry. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have firing platforms built around the Penthouse so that it can be defended from flyers or climbers without granting access to it. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add preservation Runes to your library: -4 Dwarf Favour, can be paid for with book budget DF for next two purchase periods. Setting up rooms for specific purposes will have to wait until new rooms are constructed or excavated. Only one construction or excavation can take place at a time, but you can do one of each. Building downwards will increase by 1 each time; second set of excavated rooms will be 3 rooms, third will be 4, and so on. Building upwards can be added upon; towers can be added on to or additional towers can be built. The distinction between the two is entirely cosmetic. Foreign Relations: [ ] Join the war between Stirland and the vampires in northern Sylvania. [ ] Involve yourself in the Marienburg affair (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Black Waters project (specify how) Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting with a fellow councillor's task: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Preserved bodies of the Rat Mothers of Clan Mors. Eshin: Throwing star, still dripping venom. Eshin Sorcerer crystal sword. Eshin Sorcerer amulet, shattered. Moulder: Electric whip, stolen from Clan Moulder. Vials, stolen from Clan Moulder. Captured Clan Moulder devices (as yet uninspected) Skryre: Firearms; jezzails, pistols, bullets, gunpowder. Warp Lightning Cannon (misfired, possibly broken) Lighting mechanism, stolen from Clan Skryre. (shared project with Adela) Breathing apparatus, stolen from Clan Skryre. (shared project with Johann) Brass orb, stolen from Clan Skryre. Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition. (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual. (FADED) The physiology and venom of the We. (FADED) The psychology and social structure of the We. (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae. (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. The We (1/2 completed) - There will be a three hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - Learning the secret of Gehenna's Golden Hounds this turn isn't quite mandatory, but delaying is very likely to miff the one who'll be teaching it to you. The Skaven artefacts remain available to be researched until after the secret is learned.

Turn 30 Results - 2484.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan Redshirt v2 -[*] MAX: Recruit him for the Karag Dum Expedition, and have him train in preparation for it. -[*] JOHANN: Recruit him for the Karag Dum Expedition, and have him train in preparation for it. -[*] DUCK: Study an artefact with one of the Journeymen: Lighting Mechanism with Adela -[*] EIC: Have the Hochlander introduce a series of ciphers to the EIC to allow it to communicate internally in much greater security. -[*] Try to contact the Ice Witches of Kislev in the hopes they can provide clement weather for the Expedition. --[*] COIN: The Gambler -[*] Attempt to recruit assistance for the Karag Dum Expedition: General Colleges of Magic, Asarnil the Dragonlord -[*] Learn the secret behind Gehenna's Golden Hounds. -[*] Turn a staff from the bone of a Shard Dragon. -[*] PENTHOUSE: Have additional rooms excavated underneath your Penthouse: -125gc for 5 rooms. -[*] SERENITY: The We Book (2/2) Johann, Adela, and yourself had been making your way through the Skaven books on engineering for background information on the lighting mechanism when the Wizard chosen to educate you in Gehenna's Golden Hounds arrived, and your first indication that they're here is Johann leaping out of his chair and hurrying towards the entrance, and then a noise like a gong being struck with a frying pan shatters the studious silence. In walks a woman no taller than you carrying Johann under one arm, wearing a golden robe that looks like it was extremely well-made before someone ripped the arms off and severed everything below the knee. Her bare and muscled limbs are as golden as Johann's, her pale skin, blue eyes, and blonde hair cut very short suggests Nordlander blood, if not Norscan. "Right!" she says, dropping the grinning Johann onto the table with a thud. "I hear there's a bloody weird Grey that wants to learn some juicy secrets." The woman who turns out to be Lady Magister Gehenna ("Gehenna the Second. I think the first was an Elf.") introduces herself, ensconces herself in your guest bedroom, and burrows into your library in the space of a single walking conversation. As Johann explains privately to you afterwards, this Gehenna - his former Master - is a Battle Wizard who 'graduated' into Lady Magister rank instead of coming up through the usual Apprentice-Journeyman-Magister ranks, so her social niceties are a bit off, even by Gold Wizard standards. But he vouches for her expertise unreservedly, and says that she was the one that stepped up and took him as an Apprentice when nobody else would. So you're even more curious than you were before when she finally gets done skimming your library and arranges the first session in the sitting room, where portions of your library have been stacked up. You're not surprised to see books on Aethyr and Chamon, but you are surprised to see ones on Aqshy. "This place secure?" "Up to Dwarven secret-keeping standards." "Right then. What apparitions you got?" Some of your shock must have shown on your face. "I meant Ulgu in general, but from that I take it you've met one." To put it mildly. "Wisdom's Asp, the Wretch, and sometimes the Whispering Darkness. I had a run-in with an Asp as an Apprentice." "Three, eh? Nasty. Chamon has the Wyrdwomen. But it's Aqshy that's the key, and Aqshy has the Fleshrender and Dark Hounds. Now, for the record..." She slides a book across the table at you, The Distinction Between Daemons and Apparitions. "We keep this up-to-date to reassure our little 'uns, as well as just in case the Witch Hunters twig and come knocking. The short version is, they're not Daemons so it's not against Article Whatever if we hunt them down and bind them into service." "Gehenna's Golden Hounds are Dark Hounds?" "Covered in Gold Magic and bound to a Wizard's soul, like a familiar except crankier. They hunger for Aqshy but they're not of Aqshy so there's no Dhar risk. We usually go for ones that are hunting Brights, but if there aren't any at any given moment, there's usually a few packs haunting the neighbourhood around the Bright College. Then we sic them on our enemies. If the spell goes wrong they can break free and either run for it or try to eat you, but that's no worse than the usual consequences for miscasting Battle Magic." "And the same method would work for any Apparition?" "In theory. Our best guess is that the Ambers use the Bleak Swarm, and the Jades use the Whispering Darkness, but we don't actually know if they use the same technique or if they've got some other secret. Needless to say, picking fights with these things isn't exactly a great idea if you don't already have a way to bind and control them. Even if they aren't hungry for your Wind, they'll still take a chunk out of you if you give them reason. But the reward could be worth it. Worked out for the first Gehenna, whoever they were." Over the coming weeks, every moment Gehenna isn't spending with Johann and his pups is spent teaching you the techniques used to bind and control the Dark Hounds, as well as the mechanisms behind those techniques. None of them are directly usable by you since they're built for Chamon, but there's enough detail to what she's telling you that you feel confident you could at least start experimentation on an Ulgu equivalent. Though you'd also need to work out a source for whatever Apparition you'd target if you did decide to go ahead with it. It's all very interesting, and close enough to forbidden that there's quite a thrill to learning it. No wonder Magister Patriarch Feldmann hesitated to share the secret - to an undiscerning eye, this would look indistinguishable from the forbidden art of Daemonology. --- Though the Skaven artefacts are bound for the College, you've time to give one a proper studying before they're all taken away by Gehenna, and you've chosen the lighting mechanism. Not because you think it's the most valuable or interesting of the lot, but because you promised to share credit of it with Adela, who wants your name and hers on a paper to give a boost to her career. With Johann and Maximillian being rewarded by the Gold College, she's the only one who would be worse off for the deal you made, so you've resolved to have this mechanism sorted out by the time Gehenna leaves with it. The lighting mechanism - or lightning mechanism as Adela's notes have it, leading to a pointless but enjoyable nomenclatural debate - seems to be the simplest possible application of the energy known as Warp Lightning, which is created by a matter-to-energy conversion of Warpstone. If done properly, this allows for an immense amount of power from a very small amount of Warpstone. If done improperly, it allows for an immense explosion from a very small amount of Warpstone. Warpstone being Warpstone, what constitutes 'properly' is a narrow and unpredictable window, so the mechanisms for extracting that power are bizarre and often counterintuitive, built as they are to try to cover as many edge cases as possible. And just to make things even trickier, they often involve traps for any would-be reverse engineers, as each Warlock Engineer seeks to keep their own techniques from being discovered by others. The rest of the mechanism is refreshingly straightforward, consisting of a series of wires to transport the energy and a glass bulb for it to be contained within. As it simply needs to illuminate, all that needs to happen is for the energy to be held there, and more energy trickled in as some of it is lost in the form of light - and in the form of heat, and a small but still uncomfortable amount of radiated Dhar. There's two potentially interesting routes to go down that you can see: using this as a means to study Warp Lightning in captivity, or trying to replicate the effect using the lightning you have trapped in your Blue Tower. [Mathilde studying Warp Lightning: Learning, 67+28+4(Library: Skaven Warp Magic)=99.] [Adela studying Warp Lightning: Learning, 41+20+10(Adaptable Mechanic)+4(Library: Skaven Warp Magic)+5(Uncanny Memory)=79.] Set up in your Room of Calamity, you and Adela carefully observe the mechanism from a safe distance, filling pages of notes with your observations on its energy output and fluctuations. None of what you and Adela record are exactly groundbreaking and it does take a number of long, dull days spent peering at it from across the room, but it is good, solid data on something normally only seen for a second as it arcs across a battlefield, often directly towards the observer. [Mathilde building a lightning-bulb: Learning, 73+28+14(Library: Engineering)=115.] [Adela building a lightning-bulb: Learning, 42+20+10(Adaptable Mechanic)+14(Library: Engineering)+5(Uncanny Memory)=91.] The constructive side of the experiment is more interesting. One of the benefits of living in a Karak is easy access to very pure metals, so it's not difficult to get your hands on copper, the metal used in the lighting mechanism. The sheathing of the copper is more of the strange bendy substance used in the gas mask, so you replicate it as best you can with layered strands of wool. Using this you bridge the storage mechanisms of the Blue Tower with a glass bell jar that Maximillian has made as solid as steel, from which the air is pumped by a miniature bellows Adela has constructed. And... nothing happens. [Mathilde understanding a lightning-bulb: Learning, 68+28+2(Library:Azyr)=98.] [Adela understanding a lightning-bulb: Learning, 27+20+2(Library: Azyr)+5(Uncanny Memory)=54.] Okay, unlike Warp Lightning, conventional lightning (if the label 'conventional' can be applied to lightning tamed by Azyr and channelled through copper) is not content to exist on its own, so it does not extrude from the wire and fill the vacuum chamber. The nature of lightning is to be travelling from point A to point B, and it is quite brilliantly bright while doing so. You set up a second wire for it to jump to and lead it back to the containment mechanism, and from a safe distance you connect the two wires. And... again, nothing. Hmm. Okay, so the Warp Lightning needed vacuum to be pulled from the wire, but perhaps the vacuum inhibits the proper travel of lightning, which after all moves through the air. You have the air returned to the bell jar and repeat the experiment, and sure enough a tiny strand of lightning connects the two wires, filling the room with an eerie blue-white light and a crackling noise. It only lasts a few moments before the smell of burning wool leads you to hurriedly disconnect the wires from the mechanism, but that's close enough to a success for you. It seems like there's no practical use to it - candles are easier to get your hands on than lightning, after all - but it was an interesting little experiment and there's a paper in it. It also gave you the opportunity to get to know Adela a little better, and though she seemed quite happy to let you take the lead, the few times she came to the fore showed she has a good grasp of engineering and an almost eerie ability to remember things she's read. It's almost a pity she seems determined to work with her hands, as she has the makings of quite a scholar if she puts her mind to it. [New paper available: Warp Lightning observations] [New paper available: Azyr Lighting mechanism] --- You go back and forth on the subject of dragon bones, weighing the definitely a dragon Storm Dragon horn against the only possibly a dragon, but possibly more Ulgu-compatible Shard Dragon bone. In the end, you went with the Shard Dragon. If it doesn't work out, you can take the lessons you learn on to a second attempt with the horn. Dragons, as demonstrated by them appearing in as many varieties as they do, are inherently mutable creatures, and the same applies to their remains. A few months stashed inside the inner workings of the Grey Tower gives the bone ample opportunity to acclimate to Ulgu exposure, and from there all that remains is business with a lathe and a chisel. If it weren't for having Runecraft to apply to break up the monotony, the next few weeks would promise to be interminable, instead of merely dull. You sit yourself down at a lathe you got Adela to scrounge up for you and get to work. [Rolling...] ...okay, you suppose it's not so bad. It's actually kind of peaceful, since you're doing it out on the balcony in the fresh mountain air with the songs of the choughs and Wolf's presence in the back of your mind for company. As the sun rises and sets over the Karak, you whittle your way gradually and carefully through the dragonbone, blunting a number of chisels in the process as you carefully reduce the bone into the shape most conducive to the flow of Ulgu. When weeks later you remove an infinitesimal sliver and can't find anything more that needs removing, you're almost disappointed. The next stage is inside, as you need the controlled conditions of magical and unvarying lighting to ensure the Runes you carve into the bone are as exact as possible. The Runes that have proven through decades of trial and error performed by College Wizards to be suitable for the flow of Shadow Magic are a varied bunch borrowing heavily from Eltharin and Thieves Cant, but also heavy with Runes affiliated with various Gods - including Ranald, but also including Renbaeth, Loec, Sokth, Qu'aph, Ptra, Halétha, Uxmac, and Anath Raema. The theory is that these aren't so much invocations to those Gods, but symbols that resonate with concepts that those Gods are affiliated with, and don't directly draw their attention. You hope that's true - the one God in your life is more than enough. When you finally finish the minute engravings weeks later, you blow off the last of the shavings and look upon your creation. It seems like a simple ivory staff adorned with a spiralling pattern of interconnected Runes. You smile, take a deep breath, and properly grasp your staff for the first time. The sensation as ambient Ulgu is drawn from the air, through the staff and into you is nothing short of exhilarating, like the first clear breath of fresh air after having lived your whole life in a smoky city. And as you gaze upon your staff, each of the etched runes begins to leak wisps of vapour, and as soon as you focus on it the effect grows hugely until billowing clouds of mist are exuding from your staff. It takes some time and concentration to figure out how to consciously stop it, but careful experimentation teaches you how to turn it on and off at will, and how to work it into your spellcasting. Pall of Darkness and Cloud of Confusion are much easier to cast and have a much wider effect, far beyond what you'd expect from simply more magic to work with. [Staff of Mists: +1 Magic, spells that create mists, fogs, vapours and miasmas are one category easier and have enhanced effects.] --- One does not simply walk into Kislev and ask to meet the Ice Witches. One instead has a word with one of the Provost's people, who has a word with one of the Chamberlain of the Seal's people, who has a word with one of the Kislevite Embassy's people, and from there you have to guess, but it probably passes through as many as half a dozen more people until it reaches an actual Ice Witch. Which you're not so sure about calling them, but it is apparently the polite way to refer to them. The founder of Kislev was one, so you suppose that Kislevarin doesn't have the same negative connotations that Reikspiel has for most words for magic-users. Truth be told, you're a little nervous. Kislev and the Empire are on generally good terms, but Ice Witches and the Colleges of Magic are not. Kislev apparently has a prophecy that a male Ice Witch will one day permanently taint Ice Magic, so any male magically-sensitive Kislevites are forbidden from using magic and are killed if they are suspected of doing so - or they were, until relatively recently when they instead crossed the border into the Empire and made their way to the Colleges of Magic, which accepted them with open arms. So they might not look kindly at a request for aid from a Wizard of the Colleges. [Rolling...] It takes a great deal of follow-ups and answered questions and the expenditure of an entirely unreasonable amount of ink, but eventually you get a letter from the Ice Witches inviting you to attend a small gathering on the autumn equinox, which according to your books is a Holy Day to Ursun, the local bear-themed equivalent to Ulric. You hope that's a good sign, rather than a sign they intend to feed you to a bear. With some trepidation, you see to organize a gyrocarriage to Karak-hop your way north and hope for the best. --- The letter advised quiet, so your gyrocarriage lands well outside the gates of the city of Kislev and approach atop your silent Shadowsteed. Today is a day of celebration, but it is a quiet one, as the first harvest is offered to Ursun for him to gorge himself and prepare for his hibernation. The walls of Kislev are tall and foreboding, encrusted with fierce-looking gargoyles and with an oddly smooth sheen to them. The guards at the gate stop you, eyeball your horse for a while, carefully check the invitation from the Sisterhood, and advise you not to break the peace. The streets within are bustling but nearly silent, and some people even wear fabric over their shoes to keep from making too much noise. Nobody wants to be the one that keeps Ursun from his sleep. Overall, Kislev seems a northern mirror to Altdorf, a bustling and wealthy metropolis that gives lie to the impression of barely-civilized barbarians some Imperials characterize the Kislevites as. The main road - the 'Goromadny Prospekt', according to your books - is lined with a mind-boggling number of stalls selling wares from across the world, with the stallholders reduced to frantically waving signs at the public since they can't hawk their goods at the top of their lungs on this day. You attract some odd looks as you weave through the crowd atop your horse, but they seem universally respectful. Kislev is a realm that honours its magic-wielders as much as it fears them, and though most don't recognize your variety of magic, you couldn't convince the average Kislevite to cross any variety of Witch if you had a gun in one hand and a sack of gold in the other. Your destination is Geroyev Square, the one public place where voices rise above a murmur - but never quite to a shout, because although the square is lined with Temples to Gods other than Ursun, nobody wants to outright oppose Him. The Temple of Ulric is made of unadorned white stone, though it is easily recognizable thanks to the wolf statues that flank the entrance. You gather that Ulric and Ursun have something of a friendly rivaly, though it does boil over into not-so-friendly territory from time to time. The Temple of Dazh is wreathed in scented smoke that is already starting to be drawn into an aura around you, celebrating the secret of fire that the Sky God had gifted Kislev's ancestors with. The Temple of Tor is bristling with metal rods inviting the Thunder God to make His will known. And towering above it all is Bokha Palace, bristling with marble towers of every size and colour. Your destination is the grassed center of the square that the crowds are carefully avoiding, despite how crowded the rest of the square is. There is a single wrought-iron bench in the square, and furrows in the grass show where it had been dragged from one side of the grass into the middle of it. And sitting on it are a mismatched trio of women: one young and dressed in a loose white sundress more suited to a Tilean summer than a Kislevite autumn, one older and larger and scowling up at the palace like it offended her while ignoring the light-brown hawk apparently grooming her hair, and a third older still, white-haired, and happily munching her way through a large fabric bag filled with candied walnuts. "Yes, it's something of a cliche," says the fourth Ice Witch, who's been trailing you since halfway up Goromadny Prospekt and has just made her way up the crowd to murmur in your ear, "but old stories have a lot of weight in Kislev." "We try to avoid the old cliches in the Colleges," you reply calmly. "But then, magic isn't respected in quite the same way down there." You turn to consider her, and how she's trying to conceal her annoyance that she didn't make you jump. She's a severe-looking woman perhaps a few years your elder, with prematurely grey hair and wearing a sky-blue dress and cloak. "Magister Weber of the Grey College." "Věnceslava of the Hromada Ledyanoy Ved'ma. Come then, Magister. Let me introduce you to my sisters." From youngest to eldest, they turn out to be Zlata, Milica, and Ljiljana, though only the first gives you a greeting in return, as the other two are occupied with their glaring and their eating respectively. "So," says Ljiljana through a mouthful of walnut, "you want us to shift the winter, I hear." "The Dwarves of Karak Kadrin want you to shift the winter," you correct. "I'm here to represent them." "You're tall for a Dwarf," says Zlata with a smile, interrupting the running translation she's giving to Milica. "I work well with Dwarves, and have a better understanding of magic than they do." Milica mutters something in Kislevarin, which gets her an elbow from Ljiljana. "That as may be, there's much good the Karzełki do for our people. That is what got you this meeting, while we play waiting games with Tzar Vladimir." She clucks her tongue thoughtfully. "Karag Dum. We have quite a spear from Karag Dum. It would be good for all if Karag Dum was not lost. Belyevobota... the Pass of White Dots, you'd call it." "They call it High Pass," Věnceslava corrects, sitting perched on one of the armrests. "Why do they do that, then?" Ljiljana asks. Milica comments something again, and evades the elbow from Ljiljana. "Imperinyi foolishness." "It's the Dwarf name for it," Věnceslava says wearily. "Oh. Well, it was their pass, they can call it what they wish," Ljiljana says with a decisive nod. "This pass, it is..." she hesitates, "it has not fallen to the Dewastacja of the Za, but it is grumpy to be surrounded by it. It will be difficult. But possible, yha. When do you need it clear?" That's the question, isn't it. And one you've spent some time wrestling with. Borek wants to leave early next year, but it definitely seems like more preparation time is warranted. Is that your decision to make, though? [ ] Spring 2485 Early next year, when Borek most wants to leave. [ ] Spring 2486 The year after next. [ ] Spring 2487 Two and a half years from now, when Borek will be leaving no matter the weather. And while you've been considering that, there's also the matter of whether you'd personally be joining the Expedition. If you commit to it now, then your own training and preparations would count towards your obligations towards Karak Eight Peaks, and you'd likely find it easier to recruit others to it. But perhaps you're not quite sure about a trip into the Chaos Wastes. [ ] You will join the Expedition [ ] You will not join the Expedition [ ] You aren't sure yet - There will be a two hour moratorium. - The part of this update with Gehenna was originally posted here. - If you pick a later year, it's possible an earlier year would happen by chance to have suitable weather for the Expedition, but not very likely. Northern Kislev is not known for naturally mild weather.

Turn 30 Results - 2484.5 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Spring 2486 [*] You will join the Expedition You've gone back and forth on the issue a number of times, balancing the maximum amount of preparation against a desire to have all this done before something else in the world requires your attention, how a shorter or longer delay might please or aggravate Borek, and whether the delay would substantially change the situation at Karag Dum when the Expedition arrives. In the end, the middle-of-the-road date of 2486 won out by a hair over a longer delay to 2487. "Between Miskaden of 961 and Shoika Day of 962," you say, having read up on the Kislevite calendar in advance. "The full time?" Ljiljana says thoughtfully. "Best case scenario, we could be back within a month. We shouldn't need more than three unless things have gone terribly wrong." "Things do that in the Dewastacja," Věnceslava says, while the other three exchange looks. [Rolling...] "We have considered this since we first heard from you," Ljiljana says. "There are a number of prices that are between we and the Karzełki, but there is one we will have from you. We have old business in the east, with our fallen cousins of the Kurgan. An item we want from one of their tribes that lives near this Karzełki tirsa of Karag Dum. We shall send someone with this Expedition who can find the tribe and the item, and you are to aid them, and you are to bring the item to us. Agree to this, and the Widow will shield the Karzełki from dying cold and hungry in the Raspotitsa." You have a number of questions, but from how the old woman emphasized item you doubt you'd get any answers. A theft from a Marauder tribe sounds straightforward enough, though you doubt it would prove that simple in the Chaos Wastes. A single odd job and clear weather for 2486, versus a high likelihood of the Expedition becoming snowbound in 2487. [ ] Agree [ ] Refuse --- Last you heard, Asarnil and Deathfang were helping Kislev see off an invasion of Ogrish invaders called 'Yhetees', but that was a number of years ago. Normally that would make it difficult to track a mercenary down, but this is one mercenary that does not travel unnoticed. You don't have to poke your nose into too many Kislev taverns to find a group of drinking Kossars, who are only too happy to tell stories of their draconic ally, including when they parted ways. That takes you to Ostland, where Asarnil picked up even more pay from the Grand Prince in exchange for stamping out the scattered Yhetee stragglers, and also a worrying Beastherd that was in the area. From there they travelled further west to Nordland, where thankfully he was not hired to get involved in the whole Laurelorn business, but instead kept travelling west... which gives you a sinking feeling in your gut. From reputation you expected Marienburg to be bustling, but it seems even more so than its reputation would suggest, as the streets have filled with mercenaries and merchants alike looking to profit from the uncertainty. Every tavern is fully occupied and entire shanty towns of tents have been erected wherever they'd fit, which in Marienburg requires a fair bit of creativity and a tolerance for dampness. It is said that the only thing you can't buy in Marienburg is open land, which makes finding somewhere comfortable to lay your head hard even for the average citizen. For an Elf who demands the finest things, and a dragon who is the size of, well, a dragon, it's a problem that you're sure would have proven difficult if they didn't have immense amounts of wealth to spend. Your questions direct you to a pair of barges tied up to Riddra Isle, one sporting a snoozing Deathfang, the other covered in silk tents, with the Elf himself reclining upon pillows and glaring moodily across the river at Elftown. "You better not be bringing another insultingly low offer from the Directorate," he says without looking up as you approach the gangplank. "Harathoi lalinoi horinar-enthlai, caladai-indrion," is your reply, and it's one you've been working on since Nordland. A simple translation would be 'I bring a better offer,' but it also has connotations of enjoyability, splendor, the inducement of jealousy, a hint at what that offer might be, and a double meaning of 'herald' that you're quite proud of. Eltharin is that kind of language. He looks up in surprise, and a smile spreads across his face as he leaps effortlessly to his feet. "The silver savage from Sylvania!" You almost take offence to that, before realizing that it's what Ma-thil would translate closest to in Eltharin. "What offer brings you to this swamp village? One from your Emperor?" "I am acting in the service of the Dwarves; they are planning an Expedition to Karag Dum, and would pay handsomely for your services." "The one way up north? Never been. Terrible place, I've heard. Full of themselves, and miserly as well. Awful combination." He frowns, and thinks for a moment. "Wait, they would have been lost in that business Teclis was here for. I suppose that explains the Expedition." He turns from you to direct a stream of half-hissed, half-gargled syllables at the other barge, and Deathfang lifts his head to look at him, and then turns to regard you, a sight that would send most people running. To many citizens of the Empire a dragon is no more than the greatest of beasts, but to those that know their history, dragons are the most ancient race of this world, dating back to before the oldest records of the Elves or the Dwarves. There's a fierce intelligence in those eyes, and to those with the Magesight to see it, raw determination fills every facet of the dragon. Deathfang was born to a world that no longer belongs to his kind, and every passing year increases the weight of that fact atop his enormous shoulders. But Deathfang remains unbent. [Rolling...] Deathfang snorts, and yawns out a response to Asarnil. "Sounds good to me," Asarnil says. "I like Marienburg's money, but this whole thing smells far too much like one of Finubar's schemes for my liking, and it's been too long since we've been able to test ourselves against the forces of Chaos. Which Dwarfhold?" "Karak Kadrin." "Oh, them. Every time I go there, Deathfang gets weird looks from a bunch of half-naked Dwarves, like they're starving dogs looking at a banquet. We'll make ourselves comfortable in Bechafen until we're needed." --- Recruiting a specific Wizard can be an extended battle of wills, but extending an open welcome to Wizards in general is a much more prosaic process. Distributing the call to arms to the Secretariat of all eight of the Colleges takes only an afternoon; what eats up weeks is setting up a means for the Expedition's payroll to pay for any interested Wizards to travel to Praag from wherever they happen to be, while also making it as impostor-proof as possible to prevent everyone with a coloured robe from being able to cadge a free trip to Kislev. It's a lot of tedious paperwork, and you won't know what the results will be until the Expedition arrives in Praag and there either is or isn't a collection of adventurous Wizards ready to join the Expedition. Bringing your Gold Wizards in on it is a lot more direct, and once you make it clear you're going, they're immediately on board. You release them from any official duties for the remainder of the year for them to see to their own training and preparations, and leave the two of them animatedly discussing which spells and skillsets might be most useful in the Chaos Wastes. [Anatomy of the We: Learning, 80+28+7(Library: Arthropods)=115.] [Society of the We: Learning, 65+28=93.] In the odd moments you're not unravelling magical secrets or gallivanting across the continent, you're putting the finishing touches to the complete book of the We. You've got your own notes, those from the various specialists you recruited to try to educate the We, and those from Johann, Maximillian, Esbern and Seija, which is a huge amount of information to boil down into a single tome. Describing their anatomy is relatively simple, as entomologists have already blazed the trail with similar specimens, giving you a model to follow and a range of comparisons to draw. Describing their society is much trickier as there's nothing else you know of that's anything like how they think, but you think you've managed to communicate the salient details. When you send off the manuscript and get a properly bound hardcover copy back a few weeks later, you don't hesitate for a moment before sliding it into the Civilized Realms section of your library. [Araneae Sapiens, 2484. Subject: Unique, +3. Insight: Revolutionary, +2. Delivery: Compelling, +1. Thorough, +1. Exotic, +1. Varied, +1. Shared Credit, -1. Total: +8.] --- Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time, this past year? The four with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) [+] EIC Reports (does not cost a choice) Romance Any victors from the below will trigger a subvote for how you'll spend time with them. For everyone but Panoramia and Johann, this is getting to know them better to see how compatible you might be. For Panoramia and Johann, it will be a first tentative expression of interest. While this would not be a soft-lock, it could be awkward to walk that back if Mathilde decides her heart lies elsewhere. [ ] [ROMANCE] Journeywoman Panoramia [ ] [ROMANCE] Magister Johann [ ] [ROMANCE] Elector Countess Roswita van Hal [ ] [ROMANCE] Baron Anton Kiesinger II [ ] [ROMANCE] The Ice Dragon of Karag Zilfin [ ] [ROMANCE] Chief Bombardier Oswald Oswaldson Fellow Wizards [ ] Gretel, who's apparently spending her newly-earned wealth to make herself at home. [ ] Hubert, as he settles in to his niche with Ulrikadrin. Karak Eight Peaks Notables [ ] Elder Hluodwica, High Priestess of Esmerelda and civilian leader of the Eight Peaks Halflings. [ ] Francesco Caravello, proud Viceroy of the Undumgi. [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart, leader of the frontier town of Ulrikadrin. Foreign Relations [ ] Barak Varr, to watch the progress of the canal. [ ] Stirland, to see for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. Friends Abroad [ ] Kasmir, to see how he's keeping himself busy in Sylvania. [ ] Julia, to see what she has gotten up to as Stirland's most experienced spy master. [ ] Eike Hochschild, to get to know your future business partner. Following Up [ ] The Amber College, to check in on the salamanders. [ ] Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - There'll be a run-down of the results of training and preparations for your recruits just before the Expedition sets off.

Turn 30 Social - 2484.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [X] Agree [X] [ROMANCE] The Ice Dragon of Karag Zilfin [X] [ROMANCE] Elector Countess Roswita van Hal [X] [ROMANCE] Baron Anton Kiesinger II [X] [ROMANCE] Chief Bombardier Oswald Oswaldson [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) [+] EIC Reports (does not cost a choice) "Behold," you say proudly, "the Staff of Mistery!" The other Wizards regard the proffered staff politely. "What's the mystery?" Hubert asks. "Whether Shard Dragons are really dragons or not, I suppose," you say, waggling it a bit. "That's some really intricate runework," Maximilian says. "May I?" "Sure," you say and hand it over. "The other big news is the upcoming Karag Dum Expedition, which after some negotiation with the Ice Witches has been firmly slated to set off in the Spring '86. You'll be getting the open invitation through your Colleges in the coming weeks, but if any of you want to bring yourselves along you'd be more than welcome." "Isn't that one of the ones lost in the Great War Against Chaos?" Gehenna asks. "Lost contact, at least. The hope is that they're still holding out." "If anyone could, the Dwarves could," Adela says firmly. "Asarnil will be joining us, so it should be quite the adventure. Anyway, think it over and let me know, I'll be gyro-hopping to meet them at High Pass so we can share a carriage. Now, I believe that I'm not the only one with big news..." you say leadingly, looking over at now-Magister Maximilian. It takes him a moment to look up from the staff when he realizes everyone's looking at him. "Oh, right," he says, as Gehenna snags the staff from him while he's distracted. "I've been promoted to Magister for my part in the-" he hesitates, and glances at Gehenna and then to you. "She was at the Battle of Ubersreik," Johann says proudly. "Yes-yes, fought-slayed the ratties," she says absently, peering at the runework. "Right, for my part in the Skaven haul," Maximilian continues. "That and a letter of good standing from the local blacksmiths. The College usually looks down on mundane crafts, but the Dwarven stamp of approval made all the difference." As the discussion veers into a comparison of local clothiers for Maximilian to acquire the fancier robes he's now entitled to, Gehenna sidles over to you. "What's this one here?" You peer at the Rune on your staff she's pointing at. "Eltharin... oh, that would be Anath Raema in Her aspect of the Stalker. Elven Goddess, like Kurnous but crankier, as I understand it." "Huh." She frowns thoughtfully. "Bunch of things just made sense. I stamped out a Cult of Styriss on Ostermark a while back that was hitting way above its weight, this was one of the symbols they had on their shrines." "Write a letter to the Taalites about it," you suggest. "I've got a contact or two that could pass it on for you. The major Cults take a dim view of the nastier Elven Gods trying to slip into the Old World." "Will do. Got a scar that aches when the weather changes that would very much like to put another spoke in their wheel." You turn your attention back to the discussion, which has mostly devolved into Gretel griping about how long the silk-weavers are taking to figure things out, and Johann acting smug about his own looted silk sheets. "Right," you say, interrupting them. "The other thing I want to touch on is the Marienburg situation. Gretel is already on retainer with Barak Varr. Hubert, can you have a word with the Winter Wolves? I don't think they'd be high up on the list of targets if Marienburg is feeling cloak-and-daggery, but they might seem isolated enough to be worth taking a swing at if Marienburg is feeling particularly stupid." "They've mostly got greenskins for neighbours so they're already very on alert, but I'll tell them to keep an eye out for human foes as well," he says. "Hopefully this will all blow over and never get beyond saber-rattling, but if it does come down to war, we're definitely not looking to have a repeat of Grootscher Marsh. I'd expect a full call to arms amongst all eight Colleges, the sort of thing not seen since Magnus' time." "'We don't want to fight but by Jingo if we do, we've got the guns, we've got the men, we've got the Wizards too. We've fought Parravon before, and while we're Reiklanders true, the Bretonni shall not have a hide east of the Grey.'" You look from Gehenna, who started the odd verse, and to Johann who joined it midway. "Parravon?" "An old song from the Third Parravon War, which was revived for the Fourth, which my Master fought in as a Journeyman," Gehenna explains. "There's always some cause that puts the realms of man at each other's throats, and for some reason people are more enthusiastic about them than fighting greenskins or beastmen or marauders or raiders." "Tell that to the Directorate," you say with a shrug. "We really don't want to fight them, we've got a dozen other problems to worry about, but if Marienburg blockades us we'll have no choice, no matter their allies." Gehenna simply nods. "So anyway, I want everyone to brush up on their combat skills, just in case. And pray to your God of choice that it doesn't come down to the Colleges against the White Tower." As the meeting breaks up, you take Hubert aside and show him your shrine. You've got no desire to steal him away from Ulric, but you did steal Wolf away from the Wolf God, so it's only fair to give Hubert a chance at the crows that call your shrine home. At this time of year there's only a handful of the choughs visiting to drink and bathe in the shallow pools, but come Spring the many nooks will be filled with nests and eggs and with a bit of luck, a hatchling will prove suitable for Hubert. The choughs live up high where Azyr dominates, and it would be nice for him to have a familiar that could fly with him. --- Prince Gotri has two personal workshops: the one high up in Karag Lhune close to the gyrocopter bays, and one built more recently in Karag Nar, close to the nascent Gunnery School. He's invited you to the latter to discuss the upcoming Expedition, and considering the opinions the relatively young Dwarf holds, you can't even begin to guess what he's going to say. "Loremaster," he says to you as you enter, not looking up from the project he's working on, and you take a moment to take in the workshop. Dwarves workshops are notoriously tidy places, and while this one has all the tools not currently in use hung on the appropriate hooks, it also has a number of half-dismantled devices taking up their own separate workbench. You wonder if this is just the way Gotri's mind operates, or if he deliberately splits his attention between different projects to rebel against the norms of his peers. "Thane," you respond politely. Prince would normally outweigh Thane, but if you're talking as one Councillor to another, that's the most relevant title. "Gotrek Gurnisson," he says. "Now there's a Dwarf who decides his own fate, and is brilliant enough to get away with it. And that wife of his must be just as determined, to refuse to join her husband's Clan and rejoin the Karaz Ankor. What a pair." He chuckles, and then swears as something inside what he's working on goes ping. "What's your actual opinion on this Expedition?" You consider your thoughts on the matter, then you consider your audience. "I think that they're trying to rescue ghosts, and I think I'm going to be hard-pressed to keep them from joining them." You manage to find a clear and relatively clean piece of workbench and take a seat atop it. "And that's the sensible ones. Borek wants Karag Dum to keep holding out even though it's halfway down the gullet of Chaos." "About what I thought. It's about context. They're refusing to give proper weight to the circumstances they find themselves in. Consider the grapecannon." He turns and gestures at a snarl of steel rods and wheels that looks nothing like a grapecannon to you. "I give it thirty years before the first fails. They'll all be scrap metal within a century. The average Engineer would sooner shave off his beard than build something like that. They'd have given it their all and made perhaps three cannon that would still be working in three thousand years. And don't get me wrong, there's a place for that, if Belegar asked me to build something for the battlements going up I'd make sure they'd last, but when there's greenskins pouring up the tunnels that's not the time to be worrying about next century." "Seems a sensible attitude to me." "That's what all the manlings say. But when I try to say something like that to my fellow Engineers, they look at me like I suggested they marry a Goblin. Sometimes I think there was a mix-up somewhere along the line and I should have been born in Nuln." He prods the not-grapecannon moodily, then peers at it and reaches for a spanner. "Still, it'd be hypocritical of me to spend time griping about how things should be, instead of focusing on how things are. So I've got two little presents for you and this Expedition. The first is this, once I get the blasted thing working." You stand up and walk over to peer over his shoulder. "It'll probably help to imagine a railing here and here." "It's a mount," you realize. "Right. We physically can't make use of all the grapecannon we've got with just one chokepoint left, and they're not going to last that long anyway, so it costs us nothing to contribute them and I'd much rather they ruin a Chaos Warrior's day up there than collect rust here. I've sent a letter to Gurnisson telling him the dimensions of the firing apertures they'll need, and once I finish the railing that'll allow them to be reloaded and run out between shots, I'll have them all sent up. Sorted it out with Barak Varr already." You imagine the effects of a grapeshot broadside lashing out from the side of the steam-wagons, and smile. "I'm sure it'll be appreciated." "The other little present is- get the door, will you?" You gesture, and a Move cantrip swings the door shut. "Handy. Right, Borek's going to encounter the reality that his Karak is inevitably doomed, and when that happens, he's probably going to go Slayer and won't care who he takes with him. So I've got a couple of levers for you to pull in case you need to alter the course of events. Gotrek's a very useful sort, I was going to make him an offer before I realized you might find it useful to keep it in reserve. If he and his family show up at the gates of Karak Eight Peaks, I've got a home and a job and a position in the Guild waiting for him, no questions asked. He can stay Clanless if he wants, or I can take him into Stoneheart. Had a word with Dreng, and the same applies for Snorri with Clan Huzkul. So if the Expedition ever needs a sudden change of leadership..." It's a problem you've had to consider yourself recently, and you're surprised to hear this kind of solution coming from a Dwarven set of lips. Gotri's always been radical, but what he seems to be implying is a step beyond that. You wonder if he's always been this way, or if he's being further radicalized by the Karak. "I do hope it never comes to that," you say, "but if it does, it will be very nice to have options. Thank you." He nods. "You're too useful to be lost on impossible revanchism." --- Judging by reports, the Hochlander has been quite busy, introducing the EIC to the concept of polyalphabetic ciphers and distributing cipher disks to each of the scattered branches. You would have gone with a book cipher, but it's his operation and micromanaging defeats the purpose of delegation, and you have to admit that memorizing a cipher disk is easier than having to consult a book for each word. The official news is a continuation of the status quo as Marienburg and the Empire continue rattling sabers without making any substantial moves towards war, but it could be things are unofficially heating up, as river piracy has started to spike along the Stir and the Aver. The EIC has avoided the worst of it as it uses its well-developed information network to travel in the wake of Riverwardens whenever possible, but other trade organizations aren't so well-prepared and a number of cargos have been stolen and the boats sunk. Though it's overall to the Empire's disadvantage, it could be that the EIC will come out with an advantage over its competitors if it continues to be better able than them to avoid the worst of the predations. The Sylvanian campaign is once more settled in for Winter, except positioned much tighter around the remaining Vampiric holdouts. A number of skirmishes ended indecisively as the Vampires refuse to commit fully to a breakout attempt, and the largest battles have been between the two towns as the Vampires apparently turn on each other. There's no better success than one's enemies bleeding each other dry, and you smile as you read through the force estimations and casualty figures. --- Mathilde has resolved to better get to know the remaining beings that she is interested in pursuing, and there's a number of possible avenues for each. Vote for the ones that you're most interested in seeing. The Ice Dragon of Karag Zilfin [ ] (DRAGON) Just show up and see if it's feeling chatty [ ] (DRAGON) Discuss linguistics [ ] (DRAGON) Offer to teach it Khazalid [ ] (DRAGON) Visit to investigate magics the Dragon seems to be casting [ ] (DRAGON) Compare notes between its recollections and Dwarven records of its activity Elector Countess Roswita van Hal [ ] (ROSWITA) Sparring sessions [ ] (ROSWITA) Invite her to peruse your library for useful information [ ] (ROSWITA) A shared investigation into the undead [ ] (ROSWITA) Attend Roswita's academic presentation [ ] (ROSWITA) Go for a Cruise on the Stir [ ] (ROSWITA) Try to convert her to a better God Baron Anton Kiesinger II [ ] (ANTON) Visit your fief together [ ] (ANTON) Tour Blutdorf's repeater factory [ ] (ANTON) Celebrate Two-Gifts Day with him and his family [ ] (ANTON) Discuss old times, and how far they've come [ ] (ANTON) Discuss his aunt, the Jade Wizard Chief Bombardier Oswald Oswaldson [ ] (OSWALD) A series of demonstrations at the artillery range [ ] (OSWALD) Swap war stories [ ] (OSWALD) Bond over pets [ ] (OSWALD) Discuss religion [ ] (OSWALD) Visit Nuln's Gunnery School together [ ] (OSWALD) Shared gyrocopter tour - There will be a two hour moratorium.

Turn 30 Social - 2484.5 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] (ROSWITA) Attend Roswita's academic presentation [*] (ANTON) Celebrate Two-Gifts Day with him and his family [*] (DRAGON) Offer to teach it Khazalid [*] (OSWALD) Bond over pets Though Belegar seems content to let the current unspoken arrangement stand, you find yourself planning a way to approach the Ice Dragon. Partially to serve your Karak, but most of it is sheer fascination for a being older than civilizations and so steeped in a Wind of Magic. What has it seen? What does it know? How does it see the world, with such depths of experience to draw on? In the end, you settle on the same approach that worked last time: flaring Ulgu in a way that would be plainly visible to anyone with Magesight, you make the long walk up Karak Zilfin with a tome under your arm. Despite the years that have passed, there is still a chemical tang to the air that doesn't fade until halfway up the mountain, at almost the exact point when the temperature drops significantly. It's a good thing you'd planned ahead and worn extra layers under your robes. Karag Zilfin is the tallest of the eight peaks, high enough that its peak would be above the snowline even if it didn't have an Ice Dragon in residence. As you cross the point where the smooth stone of the once-inhabited Karag gives way to the hewn rock of ancient mineworks, an answering pulse of Hysh blinks into existence above you, and then gradually fades. An acknowledgement from the inhabitant, and a hopeful sign. You let your Ulgu fade to the point where it would be less attention-grabbing and continue upwards, noting the crunch of frost under your feet as the temperature drops further still. Your trek ends as the passage opens up into a huge cavern lit from a huge opening on the side of the mountain, mostly closed over with ice that splits the sunlight streaming in into an even and otherworldly illumination. Several other exits to the chamber are likewise iced over, and glowing lights are visible within them. The floor is covered with snow that varies in depth from ankle deep where you are standing to several meters in depth in the center of the cavern, where the glinting silhouette of the Ice Dragon itself is lying atop it, the eye facing you slitted open and regarding you. "Shadow-being," it says in Eltharin. "Larime-Sethai," you reply, and it blinks as it considers that. Eltharin has a number of words for dragon, but most of them are for the variety that the Kingdom of Caledor is in partnership with. Inventing new names for someone out of the hellishly intricate Eltharin lexicon without accidentally insulting them is half of Eltharin diplomacy, and you hope that this invention goes over well. "The water-folk once knew me as Cython, you may speak of me as such," it eventually says. "What brings a shadow into the light?" "We are to be neighbours, but the only tongue we hold in common is an invitation to discord. I would teach you the tongue of the Daroir, if you would desire to learn it." Cython flicks its tail, sending a puff of snow into the air. "New tongues are only as useful as the answers they allow," it says slowly, "and answers in the tongue of the water-folk are often worse than no answer at all. An alternative may prove worth the expenditure. The vessel you carry, it is of the Daroir?" You nod, and lift the book up to Cython, and flinch away as Hysh blooms and grasps it. With incredible precision, the magical grip lifts the book to Cython's far eye and begins to riffle the pages. It wasn't easy to find a Classical to Khazalid lexicon, but the sheer amount of books you had purchased from your contact in Barak Varr meant that when you had a specific request, they would scour the Old World to fulfil it - though this time, they only needed to go as far as Tobaro, where Dwarves and Tileans have had a long partnership. "Not water-tongue," it says approvingly. "Ah, yes, that which is now called Classical. An adequate language of an adequate people. They trusted the wrong being, but the history of this world is made of misplaced trust." Teaching Cython is quite unlike what you expected. From you it requires only the correct sounds for the letters and a few clarifications on grammatical structure, and these questions are spaced quite apart as it scrutinizes the book with the eye not fixed on you. As you wait, you pile the snow up against one wall in the rough shape of a chair, noting that though it's certainly cold to the touch, it doesn't seem to leech the heat out of your hands, and a handful you cup experimentally in your hands stubbornly refuses to melt. "Skarrenaz skarrenazi skarrenak skarrenit," Cython says experimentally. "Orskarrenit orskarrened oranskarrenit oranskarrened oranadskarrened. A very precise language." You look up at it in some surprise. "You're done?" you ask in Khazalid. "Adequately," it responds. The book snaps closed, and floats back over to you. "I note that your tale did not conclude with the trespass of the interlopers." "The Orcs? Yes, we did manage to see off most of them." "You were one artist of their doom. Who was the other?" "The other?" You pause to consider. Kragg, you suppose, or possibly Algard. Or Gunnars. Or- oh, you think you see what it's asking. "The magic itself? The other would be Gazul, the Dwarven Ancestor-God of Death. The tower channels his Flame." "I know the taste of Death and Prophecy. This was not that." "Prophecy? You mean Morr? Or Morai-heg? The Dwarves don't have the same Gods as men or Elves." For the first time, it turns its head to behold you with both eyes. "Tell me of this Gazul, then." Not how you expected this to go, but okay. "His full title is Gazul, Lord of Underearth. He guards over the dead and helped discover the secrets of Runes. His symbols are a cave entrance and a flame-" "Flame," Cython interrupts. "Death and flame. Death and flame?" It swings its head back and forth, muttering to itself in a tongue you don't recognize. In a strange way, for the first time the aura of unknowability it seems to exude has been punctured. You know this emotion very well - the shock and confusion of someone who's just had a hole kicked in their thesis. "Their other Gods. Sun God?" You shake your head. "Earth God?" "Sort of? Grungni is the God of Mining and Stonework-" "No. Water God?" You shake your head. "Knowledge God?" "Not really. There's a God of Engineering and a God of Runesmithing-" "Engineering God," it says, like it's grasping for a lifeline. "And of crafts and metalworking?" "No, that's Smednir, God of Smelting and Smithing-" "Smelting and Smithing? But just smelting, not fire?" "Right." "Death and flame," it repeats again. "You have books on these Ancestor-Gods?" "I can get some." "It would be pleasing to have a neighbour that would share knowledge. Your lair is atop the easternmost peak?" "It is." "It would be pleasing to visit such a neighbour's lair, and to be granted temporary sovereignty of such books." "It would be pleasing to have a relationship with a neighbour where knowledge is shared," you hazard, copying the way it seems to circle around a request instead of coming right out with it. It nods firmly. "Will visit at dusk, when shadow is in primacy," it says. It then cocks its head, considering you. "A gift for a welcome neighbour," it says as it thrusts a taloned claw into the snow, then in an avalanche of snow it pulls out a massive, frosted-over figure. It takes you a moment to recognize the Orc you only ever saw at a distance: Warboss Birdmuncha. "I'd wondered where he'd gotten to," you say faintly, as Cython props the figure upright. The Warboss is forever frozen in mid-charge, his arms still gripping his looted Dwarven bolt-thrower. "He evaded the art of you and this Gazul, and then made his way to me. He believed he would feed on me. If the interlopers were not so displeasing to the stomach, it would have been quite pleasing for the opposite to become true." It exhales in a draconic chuckle that sends snowflakes whirling around the cavern. "Thank you for this gift," you say as you try to figure out how you're going to get a frozen Warboss down a mountain. Some time later as you wheel a handcart full of Warboss downwards, you reflect that you're not entirely sure what you expected from your meeting with the Ice Dragon, but it definitely wasn't that. You did succeed at getting a glimpse of it as a person instead of as a terrifying force of nature, and if nothing else, you're pretty sure Belegar would consider a few more books for your library a small price to pay for getting an Emperor Dragon invested in the Karak's continued survival. And there's not many Wizards that can boast they have a dragon in their book club. - The remaining interactions will be posted as they are written.

Turn 30 Social - 2484.5 - Part 3

When you first heard of a conference of Witch-Hunters, your initial response was that it'd behoove you to be as far away from it as possible. But though it is hosted by the Cult of Sigmar, this is no hidebound coterie of fanatic Sigmarites, nor a collection of thief-takers and hired thugs given a dubious seal of approval by some regional authority. This is a gathering of representatives of every organization dedicated to the stamping out of those that use the Forbidden Lores of the Daemonic Powers, the unholy ways of Necromancy, and other sorceries and witchcrafts that utilize the wicked powers of Dark Magic. That said, those Wizards that don't plan on attending still make a point to keep inside the Colleges or outside of Altdorf for the duration, just to be on the safe side. Today, the University of Altdorf's largest conference room is filled with notable figures in the realm of slaying the things that go bump in the night. The Morrite Knights of the Order of the Sacred Scythe, the Black Guard, and the Raven Knights are easily identified by their tabards, as are your fellow Wizards of the Magisters Vigilant by the colour of their robes. There's Priests of just about every God of the Old World present, all of whom have decided the best way to serve their God is to protect their flock from predation and corruption, and all wear the symbols of their God openly. But for everyone else the distinction is a little trickier, as a general uniform of blackened leather, cloaks, and large hats abounds, and there's enough stakes affixed to belts and bandoliers to fence a small field. The Holy Order of the Templars of Sigmar make up the bulk of these, but the Fellowship of the Shroud is almost as numerous, and there's a handful of Dwarves from the Order of Guardians. The rest of the numbers are rounded out by the Andanti, Helhunten's Redeemers, the Tsarevich Pavel Society, the Dreamwalkers, and various unaffiliated enthusiasts who have demonstrated either enough luck or enough skill to be invited to such a gathering. And, of course, there's one Elector Countess. "More Manannites than usual," Roswita says distractedly as she observes the crowd. "Stormguard and Knights Mariner. Perhaps the Vampire Coast is stirring. I'm not seeing any of the Order of the Shroud, thankfully - they always end up in a brawl with the Fellowship of the Shroud. I hear the Guild of Embalmers managed to wrangle an invite again, even though their representative almost got staked last time..." "I'm not seeing anyone from Tempelwijk," you say with a sigh. Roswita scans the crowd again and nods. "Not surprised that the Collegiates are staying away, but there's usually at least a few from the Star Chamber. Foolishness. Some things should be above politics." "Should be, but aren't. Have you got everything ready?" "I'm still not sure about the title. I really like 'The Neglected Front', but 'Economic Warfare Against Vampires' sounds stilted." "Versus Vampires? No, the alliteration sounds weird. Against the Night's Dark Masters?" "Poetic, but calling them that gives them more credit than they're due. Economic Warfare against the Vampiric Bloodlines, maybe?" "It does flow better." You frown over her shoulder as she jots it down. "Shouldn't 'against' have a capital?" She frowns down at it. "I don't think so. It's like 'at' or 'by' or 'to', it just looks weird because it's a longer word." "I suppose," you say, not quite convinced. Roswita looks around the room again as you continue scrutinizing the uncapitalized A. "I've got to make nice with about thirty different people after the Talabecland business. Want to come with, or reconvene later?" "Aren't they all Templars?" you ask warily. She nods. "Fair enough. Meet you at the punch bowls once I'm done." While she goes to circulate amongst the rather insular knot of Sigmarites, you slip into the crowd in search of people you recognize. Your hat combined with your robes gets you a lot of confused looks, but some looks of recognition, and you exchange nods with a Knight of the Black Guard and a Cleric from the Order of Guardians. The Hochlander has managed to parlay his recent contacts into an invitation and is currently deep in conversation with a Taalite and an Ulrican. From your own College, you see Lord Magister Melkoth doing severe damage to the sideboard under the eye of the poor Perpetual whose job it is to keep him away from the drinks and to remind him this isn't the right audience for his favourite party trick, and in the most shadowy corner he could find, Lord Magister Kurtis Krammovitch is talking animatedly to a cluster of dubious-looking Witch Hunters. And most prominent of all, the flow of the crowd is severely hampered by the circle of Morrites side-eyeing Magister Matriarch Elspeth von Draken as she chats with a Bretonnian Damsel. With a mental shrug, you pick the conversation that sounds most interesting and dive in. --- "There's a limit to gratitude," Roswita says as she ladles a dubious mix of fruit juice and alcohol into a stein. "Yes, yes, Talabecland was quite well done, I'll build a new church or something. But I'm not going to support a bid for a fourth Elector from the Cult of Sigmar. Does the Grand Theogonist even know he's pushing for this?" "Maybe not," you say. "My impression has been that he's focused on the tussling with the Ulricans." "Politics again," she says with a grimace, and then washes it down with a swig from her stein, and grimaces again. "Gods, did they just wave an orange at a barrel of spirits?" "They probably get students to set it all up. Some U of A students can go shot for shot with Bright Wizards." "I was one of those students," she says with a smile that quickly fades. "At least on paper. Correspondence courses. The Van Hals have earned far too many enemies to attend in person." Her smile has turned entirely into a frown as she stares at the milling crowd. "Vampires ruling damn near openly in Sylvania, and the oldest Witch Hunter family in the Empire in hiding. If nothing else, I can turn that around. Drive the damned creatures underground, and the Van Hals can live openly in Wurtbad." "You've come close," you say. "Close to starting. There's dozens of them waiting in the shadows for an opportunity to fill the voids I've opened, and far too many influential Sylvanians would welcome them back. They've grown used to paying taxes in other people's blood, and really don't like having to give up their own gold instead. It will be the work of decades to make it stick." She takes a deep breath. "But that's okay. I knew that when I accepted the inheritance." You take a moment to consider what it must be like to have your entire life's work laid out before you like that. Apart from 'being a Wizard', you've always had a lot of leeway in what you spend your life doing. Stirland was a major commitment but one that ended, as was the Expedition, and part of you is already starting to look for the next adventure after being Loremaster of Karak Eight Peaks. But Roswita's destiny - and really, the destiny of all the Van Hals - are inextricably bound to Sylvania, and perhaps always will be. "You know what might make that weight a bit lighter?" She turns to look at you. "Imagining all the future days you're about to ruin for Vampires across the Old World. All those Necrarchs without their precious books." She smiles. "Von Carsteins with faded livery." "Lahmians with tattered silks." "Blood Dragons with rusted swords." She smothers a giggle with her stein. "That does help. Thank you." --- Roswita, in your amateur estimation, is a decent public speaker once she gets going. Getting going hits something of a roadblock when one member of the audience who overindulged in the University punch asks loudly and insistently why anyone would bother interfering financially with Vampires instead of just killing them, but Roswita's recent successes have earned her enough allies that you're beaten to said heckler by several Templars who are rather insistent that the heckler has an urgent appointment elsewhere, possibly with some fists in a dark alley if he doesn't get the hint. After that things go quite smoothly with the audience erupting into mutters of shock at the sheer figures involved, but any disbelief is quickly extinguished by Roswita citing the ledgers of the now-executed Talebecland smugglers. You know that if anything she's lowballing it as Alkharad's ledgers have substantially larger figures - but, of course, those ledgers are about as classified as it's possible for something to be, since they're connected with the whole 'Black College' business. Chances are that many of those currently present will never go out of their way to wage an economic war of any kind, but if they happen to be tracking a Vampire they might be more inclined to start investigating local traders that could uncover leads that would otherwise have gone unnoticed. And for every Witch Hunter only half-listening while they wait for a presentation on a bigger gun or a sharper stake, there's a more thoughtful sort who will take this information back to their Cult or Order or College or Fellowship and there'll be a new weapon in the arsenal of mankind. And that matters a lot. Perhaps that is your life commitment - contributing to the collective knowledge of the Colleges and the Empire in ways that will tangibly increase the odds of mankind's continued survival on this hostile world. The applause at the end of Roswita's presentation is louder than you expected, and you're more than happy to contribute to it. - Writing on the remaining interactions will resume after a night's sleep.

Turn 30 Social - 2484.5 - Part 4

The Temple of Ranald is not a tavern, but that just means it offers good drinks at a fair price instead of trying to slice every copper. To those with the clout to not be subjected to the gentle but insistent reminders from the staff that this is a gambling establishment and one is expected to partake, it's one of the better places for a reasonably quiet drink. Or a rather loud drink when the fighting ring is in use. It's also a favourite hangout of the Karak's small but growing clowder of cats, ruled over with a merciless iron paw by Captain Snuggles. The cat-shaped Shrine in the centre of the Temple is her favoured perch, and one can take in the current state of the pecking order at a glance by seeing which cats sit alongside their giant obsidian fellow, and which have been banished to the ignominy of ground level. The only exception to this merciless and ironclad social structure is Wolf, who is known to doze alongside the obsidian cat while keeping a sleepy eye on the comings and goings of the worshippers. Either because of his unique relationship with Ranald or simply because he is a fully-grown wolf, none of the cats challenge his right to take up a significant portion of their chosen territory, not even the otherwise unchallenged queen-slash-officer. "It takes a special kind of bond for a cat to be a soldier's pet," Oswald says, after you ask him of his cat's rank. "A dog will stick by your side through anything, but cats? They don't like moving and they don't like schedules, and for a cat to stick with you even through that instead of running away or being left behind because they weren't with you when it was time to march means something special. That's where the ranking system comes in. Not sure if it was just my regiment or wider, but animals get promoted and demoted based on how good they are at sticking around. Which means there's a lot of highly-ranking dogs and a lot of cats that never make it past lance corporal. If a Private is missing you just look around the place a bit, but if it's a Sergeant you go ask a few pointed questions of local butchers and the regiment's cooks." You nod in understanding. "And now that you're in one place for the foreseeable future..." He nods. "They were easy promotions to make. I doubt I'm going anywhere for the rest of her lifetime." That's a sobering thought. It's been six years since the start of the Expedition, so Snuggles must be at least that old, almost certainly older. So at least half of her lifetime is already spent, probably more. You can't help but be quite glad that Familiars last longer than their ordinary counterparts. Rather than voicing that thought, you let the conversation drift into the conversation every pet owner is familiar with: the conversation about the personal quirks and foibles of one's pets, which is never interesting to anyone else, but listening to them is the price of admission for the always irresistible opportunity to talk about your own companion. And once that exchange is over, there's the question that's been in the back of your head ever since you met the man: what's with the generations of Oswaldsons? Oswald takes a long pull from his drink and stares at nothing in particular. "There was once a Norscan raiding crew lead by a man named Ásvaldr," he begins, in the tones of someone repeating a story, "who broke with the Raven and fled to Nordland, eventually settling in a small fishing village willing to take a chance on some dubious new citizens in exchange for their skills at combat and boat-building. When it came time for them to adopt a surname, they collectively chose Ásvaldsson to show loyalty to their former captain. Over the years, this family demonstrated a strong adventurous streak and grew scattered across the Empire but remained in contact, and in each generation there was an Ásvaldr, an avatar of the original ancestor to bring luck and prosperity. By this time the descendants of the original crew had intermarried enough that they truly were a family, and everyone could draw a line back to the first Ásvaldr. But the Dark Age of Three Emperors shattered this unity." He waves a hand absently. "It's a long story of heartbreak and betrayal I won't go into, and by the time of Magnus the Pious few of us were left. The Ásvaldssons that supported the Wolf Emperors had died out in battle, the Aswealdssons who backed the Ottillian Emperors had been absorbed into the noble families of Talabecland - could probably find a blood link between me and that Hubert if you spent a month researching - and only the Oswaldsons who supported the Nuln Emperors remained, and there were damn few of us after the Great War Against Chaos." "That's quite a history. I'd thought it was an unbroken line." "Gods no. Many an Oswald has died childless, but the Oswaldsons continue and name a new Oswald or Osvalda for our ancestor. Even if we're a bit diminished now, there's still part of the Reikwald that we technically own, with some of the foundations of the original manor house still visible if you know where to look. By the time I'm ready to retire I should have enough squirrelled away to begin rebuilding in the Reikwald, unless I've gotten too attached to this place. Might take a page from the Halflings' book and decide that we're more secure if there's a new branch of Oswaldsons here in the mountains." Considering your own family, it's hard to imagine having such a weight of history behind you, but Oswald seems to draw great comfort and motivation from his. And you can definitely respect the strength of will it must have taken the original Ásvaldr to turn from the Chaos Gods and lead his people to a new land. That's definitely worth celebrating, and perhaps even worth enshrining. You smile and listen with interest as Oswald turns to his current pet topic: his theorizing on the mystery of why the Dwarves have never embraced an indirect-fire blackpowder weapon. His world is very different to yours in many ways, but there's definitely parallels in how he approaches his world and how you approach yours.

Turn 30 Social - 2484.5 - Part 5

Originally from Ostermark, Two-Gifts Day is a holiday to Ranald that waxes and wanes in popularity in neighbouring provinces based on how well they're getting along. A shareholder of the EIC celebrating the day could go some way into smoothing the ruffled feathers of the League of Ostermark, or so the theory goes. So in Blutdorf, Franzen and Wolfsbach, the local rulers are welcoming this unusual holiday into their homes. You'd be quite proud of it if it had been one of your gambits, but the first you'd heard about it was when Anton invited you to his. Not quite sure whether it's Ranald playing games or just a coincidence, you shift your schedule around so you'll be able to fit it between your other travels. Blutdorf seems to be thriving, with new residences popping up outside the walls or atop the existing ones as the town draws in more and more people to work in its two factories, and then people to provide goods and services to those well-paid inviduals, and so on. It's a boom cycle the Empire is quite familiar with, and it so often ends with an untimely fire or an attack by Orcs or Beastmen or Undead, and all that hard-won progress is lost overnight. You hope that Blutdorf can set at least some of its gains in stone - literally, since permanent structures and an outer wall are the most reliable ways of doing so. You also note that at least so far, Two-Gifts Day hasn't spread from the homes of the rulers. You wonder if there's some resistance to it, or if there's no plans to implement it wider. It can, at times, lead to some strife if indulged in too freely. The Holiday itself revolves around presenting two gifts: one silly and presented in a grandiose manner, the other more precious and handed over without ceremony. Originally, both gifts were then fair game to be stolen and presented to someone else, but most families have reduced this to only the silly gifts to prevent strife. This goes against the intended message of the holiday that material objects are relatively meaningless and ownership can be fleeting, but it does make for a much more harmonious holiday. And even if the Night Prowler's message is lost, the Deceiver is still being celebrated, and was likely amused by the change besides. There are benefits to a multi-faceted God. The guards at Blutdorf Castle are wielding Gerber-Kiesinger Repeating Rifles, and very well-maintained ones if their shininess is anything to go by. They seem to recognize you, by outfit and reputation if not by face, and they simply stand to attention as you enter the castle. You're expected after all, and your invitation said to let yourself in and to join your hosts in the Lesser Hall, which roomier castles would likely have labelled a drawing room. Or possibly a wardrobe. The Imperial Palace really has a way of distorting one's sense of scale. And waiting for you inside is supposedly Anton's entire family, so it's with some sadness that you see that there's just him and his now-retired father sitting by the fire, with one chair left empty for you. "Mathilde!" Anton says delightedly, looking up from his conversation and rising to his feet. "So good to see you again!" He meets you halfway in a hug, and after you part you hand over the boxes you brought. "I'm sure you remember my father, Anton Senior." You'd only met him once and then briefly, but the resemblance to his son is hard to miss. You'd made sure to work this out in advance: Though he'd set the title aside for his son to inherit it, he was still due the respect of that rank, so that made it a Stirlandian Knight greeting a Stirlandian Baron. You give a bow of a carefully-calculated depth, deep enough to show respect but not so deep that you disrespect your own rank in turn. His returning bow is clearly automatic and visibly shallower than yours, and he settles back into his seat as soon as he's done giving it. "A pleasure, My Lord," you say. "I'm nobody's Lord now," he says gruffly, waving a hand. "Have a seat and get some fire into you. There'll be drinks along shortly if the staff haven't all snuck off while I wasn't looking." He must be into his sixties by now, but he looks closer to forties, and a lively forties at that. "Damn, what's the current lad's name?" "Wilbert!" Anton calls, and a servant appears in the doorway. "A round of ale, if you'd be so kind." The drinks are obediently fetched as you settle into the third seat, and the three of you fall into comfortable conversation of news, gossip, and a range of topics in between. --- The first flagon of ale has settled, and a second is well on its way to keep the first company. "You came from Altdorf, did you say?" Anton Senior asks. "How'd you find the roads?" "Came overhead in a gyrocopter," you reply. "Hmph. Handy folk. Charge a mint for their goods, but damned if they aren't worth it." "Speaking of," Anton says, exchanging a smile with you, "Mathilde and I decided that a noble of your calibre deserved only the best of goods, so we went to the finest artisans of the Karaz Ankor for a gift for you." "Only the best for a former Baron," he says solemnly, fighting back a smile. "And as you're rich in years, we found a suitable gift to bring comfort to you." The first box he hands over to his father was one crafted by the human craftsmen of Karak Eight Peaks, as the Dwarven ones don't have the knack for deliberately shoddy gaudiness. Cheap wood has been partially varnished, inset with gems of scratched and clouded glass, and covered in crooked 'gold' filigree that is already starting to turn green. With a suspicious glare Anton Senior slowly levers up the lid, then flips it completely open to reveal its precious cargo, gleaming white. It had taken a fair bit of cleaning to cut through the natural yellowing and then some more for the sake of hygeine, and they did need to be filed down to size to be fit for purpose, but all that effort was worth it to present Anton's father with his very own pair of genuine trolltooth dentures. "What in Taal's name..." he says, gingerly picking it up by one of the teeth. "You've mentioned a few times that your fake teeth aren't any good for dried meat, so I got you the best," Anton says happily. "Grey College guarantee that it came from an untainted troll," you say with a grin. "Considering what they normally eat, they'll outlast any of us, even if you take up rock-chewing as a hobby." While the benefits of trolltooth dentures are considerable, the size disparity between trolls and humans meant that the dentures consist of a grand total of four massive teeth. Anton Senior gives them a suspicious sniff, and then levers out his ivory set to try his best to fit the trolltooth dentures in their place. He eventually succeeds, but the teeth are so large that his mouth is held open in a horrifying grimace. "'ow 'oo 'ey 'oo'?" "Just grand," you say, fighting back a laugh. "A new fashion trend just waiting to happen, I'm sure," Anton says. With some difficulty, Anton Senior pops the trollteeth back out. "Could chew through a castle wall with that. Such a thoughtful gift." He ruffles Anton's hair, then looks about himself to try to find where he set his regular set of teeth down. "Oh, and we had a few Karak Norn carpenters make a Blutdorf-model crossbow out of Athel Loren hardwood," Anton says casually, handing over the other, much less adorned box. "Since you kept saying you don't want to relearn how to fire any other type of crossbow." Anton Senior pulls the top of the box and stares down at the crossbow inside. The wood is so dark as to be almost black, and shines with a lacquer that will outlast you all. Also in the box is a sheaf of crossbow bolts made of the same dark wood, one of which Anton Senior is already placing in the notch as he swings his aim between the ornaments and trophies hung on the wall, and eventually he decides on a boar's head and with a click the bolt is embedded just behind the ear. "Never was happy with the taxidermy job on that one," he says happily. "Daresay with this I won't have trouble replacing it." "Glad this trifle could be of some use," you say solemnly. --- You eye the sea-chest dubiously. Your instincts scream that it should have pirate treasure in it, but by the way Anton was able to haul it in by himself, you don't think it could be filled with precious metals. "This one was my father's idea," Anton says. "You're a Shadow Wizard, so you should find the contents very useful." "A princely gift, and one that not many could get their hands on," Anton Senior says gravely. "I reckon you'll put it to good use." "I'm sure it will be of immense value to my work," you say, and unable to restrain your curiousity any further, you lift the lid. "Mathilde!" Anton gasps as you stare down at an empty chest. "She let them out," Anton Senior says with a groan. If you hadn't already cheated by thoroughly scrutinizing the chest with your Magesight, that combined with 'useful for a Wizard' would have you extremely concerned. "Let what out?" "An entire chest of genuine Blutdorf shadows," Anton says sadly. "Took an entire afternoon to get them all in there." You start to laugh, then pause. "Actually..." you say thoughtfully. "Oh no." Anton hurriedly reaches under his chair and produces a second, much smaller box, and thrusts it at you. "Here, open this instead of doing Wizard things." You take the lid off, and find yourself looking at a carved wooden figure on horseback. It's not very detailed and was obviously carved by hands unused to delicacy, but the robe, the hat, and the sword on its back make it clear who it's supposed to represent. "There's a few places in Nachthafen selling them. They're used as charms in the Hunter's Hills to ward off the Undead." "They'd need all the help they can get." Anton Senior peers at the rider. "Who is that, anyway?" "Some local legend, I think," Anton says with a shrug. "The seller tried to tell me some story about someone who supposedly killed Castle Drakenhof, but it didn't sound all that plausible." You're not sure how you feel about apparently becoming a folk superstition, but you do know how you're supposed to pretend to react. "I suppose it could keep my vampire skulls company," you say with feigned disinterest, "though I'm not sure if there's room on the shelf." "Might knock them all onto the floor if it really wards them off," Anton says thoughtfully. "Might be untidy." "Bit of bouncing around would be good for them," you say decisively. --- It had been quite some time since you'd heard from those first few flagons of ale, so a rescue party of another round is formed up and sent to go looking for them. There was a time when you'd have started really feeling those drinks by now, but that was before you made your home in a Dwarfhold. Nowadays your palate is broadened and your liver is well exercised. "My gift for the man that was the first friendly face I saw in Wurtbad is as singular as the man himself," you say gravely as you hand over the unadorned wooden box. You'd debated various containers and displays, but eventually decided they'd simply detract from the granduer of the gift itself. Anton takes a deep breath to steel himself and lifts the lid, and beholds the glory of what you have gifted him for the first time. "It's... a rock?" he says, looking down at the vaguely pyramidal stone unsuredly. "It is - or rather was - the very tip of Karag Nar, the easternmost of the Eight Peaks," you say solemnly. The two Antons look down at the former peak, no bigger than a man's fist. "That's actually really neat," Anton says happily. "Great conversation starter," Anton Senior says. "'Oh, this rock? That's one of the Eight Peaks.'" You conceal a frown. You might have overshot a little with the first gift. "Oh, and I've heard your regalia is a bit lacking..." "Bloody minotaur ran off with the good sword still stuck in him back in '42," Anton Senior grumblingly confirms. "So I picked up a little something for you." With a negligent toss, you pass the sheathed blade over to Anton. "The Karak found some silversteel ingots in one of the sealed vaults, and I had a fellow in Barak Varr slap something together for you." Anton draws the blade from the sheath, and raises his eyebrows at the firelight reflecting off the silvery metal. "Ah, cast-offs," he says. "I suppose it will serve." "We've been getting along just fine with something we cadged off the Flensburg Swords," Anton Senior says, trying not to look too interested in the blade, "but I guess it'd be rude not to use it." Not long after the exchange of gifts, food arrives as you relocate to the dining room, and then to a balcony to wash it down with another flagon or two. There's a few half-hearted attempts at larceny, but the two Antons are incredibly bad at it. As are you, except in the opposite direction, as your attempts at making incredibly obvious plays for the prizes result in you easily palming them and then sheepishly returning them without either of the Antons noticing. All in all it's a very pleasant evening, and though you doubt you brought all that much honour to Ranald, it made for a good excuse to catch up and have a nice time together. --- [ ] [ROOM] Explosives Laboratory A room with enough reinforcement and baffles to withstand all but the most inadvisable of experiments. [ ] [ROOM] Training Hall A room for mastering martial combat, including a sparring area. [ ] [ROOM] Firing Range A room for training and trialling firearms and ranged offensive spells. [ ] [ROOM] Workshop A room dedicated to the more mundane crafts, with tools for woodworking, engraving, etching, scrimshawing, and sewing. [ ] [ROOM] Provision Room A room filled with provisions and water sufficient to sustain a single person (and their dog) for a year. [ ] [ROOM] Keg Cellar It's easy to cultivate a taste for beers and ales when living in a Dwarfhold. A cellar would pay for itself, as it's much cheaper to buy a freshly-barrelled ale and let it age than it is to buy it after it's ripe and ready to drink. [ ] [ROOM] Armoury A room filled with mostly-ranged weapons, suitable to equip a substantial force to defend the Penthouse from attackers from below or from the skies. [ ] [ROOM] Trophy Room Your collection of mementos is growing large and impressive enough to deserve a room to itself, complete with tasteful little plaques describing the circumstances under which you acquired each piece. [ ] [ROOM] Map Room A room dedicated to the cartographer's art, filled with large, flat surfaces to unroll maps onto and heavy objects to pin down the corners. [ ] [ROOM] Gyrocopter Hangar Includes a retractable landing pad and a reinforced outer door that cannot be easily distinguished from stone from the outside. Since you already have a landing pad on the balcony, it's somewhat redundant unless you see a personal gyrocopter in your future. [ ] [ROOM] Dragon Room An outer door large enough to admit a draconic guest, and with room enough for them to sit comfortable. [ ] [ROOM] Guest Room You already have one. Perhaps you could use another. [ ] [ROOM] Khazalid Transcription Room (2 Dwarf Favour) Runic enchantments are capable of transcribing Khazalid due to the relationship between Runesmith Runes and the Khazalid alphabet. Build a room to perform this, suitable for interviews, conferences, or declamations. Library Purchases Budget: 300gc, 2 Dwarf Favour. Anything not spent will not accumulate. [ ] [LIBRARY] No purchase. [ ] [LIBRARY] Write-in. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Feel free to suggest additional room ideas. - The rooms are not in plan format, feel free to vote for whichever rooms take your fancy. The five with the most votes will be built.

Turn 31 - 2485 - We'll Ride Steam-Wagons Through Ruined Lands

Spoiler: Voting results [X] [ROOM] Dragon Room [X] [ROOM] Workshop [X] [ROOM] Training Hall [x] [ROOM] Map Room [X] [ROOM] Trophy Room [X] [LIBRARY] Ulgu: Esoteric Imperial (50gc+2CF), The Great Steppes: Extensive Imperial+Extensive Dwarven (200gc), The Chaos Wastes: Antiquarian Dwarven (100gc+2DF) [X] [DWARF] No purchase. [x] [COLLEGE] Ulgu Power Stone (5CF) [X] [PURCHASE] No purchase. Your penthouse expands even further down, as you have local masons carve out a workshop, training hall, map room, and trophy room to have specialized areas for your ever-expanding collections of skills, interests, reference materials, and keepsakes. The last part of it was a trickier notion to communicate, and you eventually had the masons work with the blueprints for a concealed gyrocarriage bay and simply skipped the final step where it would be filled with tools and devices. So far Cython has only visited twice, and then only long enough to collect a few books on the Ancestor-Gods for its perusal before flitting off back to its frozen home. But you're hoping that it will grow comfortable enough with you or curious enough about the topics to start to engage in further conversations, and you think there is a greater possibility of that if that could happen somewhere concealed and comfortable, instead of Cython being perched precariously on your balcony for all the world to see. --- With only a year until the Okral leaves, it seemed like the uneasiness and simmering resentment could be ridden out until then, but despite the best efforts of your fellow councillors the situation is finally starting to boil over. So far the damage is limited to brawls and insults that have been smoothed over by cooler heads, but the situation is definitely uncomfortable and could easily spiral even further. "Karaz-a-Karak has reprimanded the leadership of the Okral and recalled a few of the worst troublemakers," Kazrik says, "and so far the Guild leadership and religious heads are staying out of it." "I'd very much like to expel the lot of them and be done with the matter," Belegar grumbles. "Edda, can we do without them?" "Not without setting back the timetable on getting our defences established, maybe by as much as a decade," she says. "They're some of the most skilled crafters of the Karaz Ankor, and because we've been keeping the Okral separate from our own masons, it would take quite a while for Clans Irkokri and Stoneback just to study what they've already accomplished and figure out what needs to be done to complete the job." "Due credit to the High King, he did send his best," Kazrik says, "but the flip side of that is they're some of the most proud and hidebound and prickly Longbeards of the entire Karaz Ankor." "Karak Eight Peaks was once a rival to Karaz-a-Karak," Belegar says with a sigh. "Oft-repeated, but not even I really thought through what that might mean if the Karak was re-established. I wouldn't go so far as to accuse them of sabotage, but it might be sticking in the craw of some of the Karaz-a-Karak loyalists to be working on something that might threaten to eclipse their own home. Are they at least still on schedule?" "Slightly ahead of it, at least for now," Edda says. "Dreng, any threats on the horizon?" "Da Howlaz are still skirmishing with the Red Fang after the failed Waaagh, and the rest of the mountains are as peaceful as I've ever seen the World's Edge Mountains get," he says. "Do we know if the Red Fang have a new Warboss yet?" you ask innocently. "They still seem reasonably united, so they've either got a new one or Birdmuncha made their way back to them." "About that," you say, and pulse Ulgu as you wave your hand. The doors swing open as Johann pushes a handcart through, loaded down with an oversize cargo of Warboss. "I found out what happened to Birdmuncha." Johann carefully sets the Warboss upright, still frozen in mid-charge. The rest of the council eyes him suspiciously, hands going for weapons as Johann lets himself back out discreetly. "He's definitely dead?" Dreng asks. "I've seen frozen ones get back up after being thawed." "This was the work of our neighbour atop Karag Zilfin. I've checked, the soul has definitely departed. He's not thawing out either, even though it's been weeks since I brought him down. Must be a Dragon thing instead of a Zhuf thing, I've never heard of the Light College being able to do anything like this." "That will win us some favour, both from Barak Varr and from the King-in-Exile of Karak Drazh. The Dragon is remaining peaceful, then?" Belegar asks. "Seems to be. I get the impression it likes to be left alone, so as long as we don't bother it, it won't bother us. I taught it Khazalid as well, so if I'm not around it can still be communicated with. It also will be borrowing some books from me, so put the word out to keep people from being too alarmed when it comes over for a visit." "Will do," Edda says. "Guess it's my job to explain it to the Okral," Kazrik sighs. "Anything further, Dreng?" Belegar asks. "Some signs of Skaven activity at the extreme edges of the under-Karak, but it seems like very light scouting activity and they've retreated as soon as challenged." "Might just be checking to see if anyone's left," you muse. "Either Skavenblight loyalists making sure that there's no Mors left, or leftover Mors trying to regain contact with their former leadership." "Do you think the Skaven will try to retake the Karak?" Belegar asks you. "If they sense weakness, yes, but no more so here than anywhere else. Those that came here looking to stamp out Mors either died in the attempt or would have lost a great deal of status for putting so many resources into something with so little pay-off. None of them can really claim the credit for Mors being stamped out here, though I'm sure they're all trying to. So they'd be focusing elsewhere, on grabbing former Pestilens holdings if their Civil War is still ongoing, or on consolidating and jostling for position amongst the new status quo if it's been ended. As for any potential Mors holdouts, they'd be looking for somewhere they could re-establish themselves and recover without being discovered and exterminated, so they wouldn't come back here." "Something to be thankful for. How go the Expedition preparations?" "I've made contact with the Ice Witches of Kislev, and struck a deal for clear weather through High Pass in the Spring of 7009. I'll be joining the Expedition, so I'll spend some time brushing up on my skills." "May you bring them as much fortune as you brought us," Belegar says with a nod. Afterward the meeting, Gunnars walks beside you. "Be careful with Karag Dum," he warns. "Of course I-" you pause. "With Karag Dum? Not with the Chaos Wastes?" "Karag Dum was the first place Morgrim spoke of His father's Doom," he says. "They knew that one day Chaos would come for them, and they would share in Grimnir's fate. They have known it and prepared for it for six thousand, seven hundred and twenty-two years. They survived the Coming of Chaos, they survived Morkar and Vangel and Kharduun. When we fought the Elves, Karag Dum fought Chaos. When we fought the greenskins, Karag Dum fought Chaos. When we fought the Skaven, Karag Dum fought Chaos." He hesitates, searching for the right words. "There is much that they could have seen as justified, in that time." Mandatory Actions: Pick one from each category. Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his metalworking studies. [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. (NEW) [ ] MAX: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Write a paper: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which. Must be taken with a 'dictate' action. Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Have him continue to teach Adela what he knows of engineering. [ ] JOHANN: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks [ ] DUCK: Work with Panoramia to try to implement the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. [ ] DUCK: Panoramia's about ready to test for Magister, but she's putting it off because she doesn't have a lot of free time to prepare. Work with her to help make the most of every spare minute. [ ] DUCK: Aid Hubert in his search for a Familiar. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Gretel and the Besiegers for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Hubert and some Winter Wolves for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Adela and some human siege weapons and operators for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Recruit all three of your ducklings for the Karag Dum Expedition. (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Panoramia and a team of crack Fieldwardens for the Karag Dum Expedition. (NEW) [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Esbern and Seija and their compatriots of the Knights of Taal's Fury. [ ] DUCK: Each of your three ducklings can fight in melee. Spar with them, and teach them what you can. [ ] DUCK: Study an artefact with one of the Journeymen: specify who and which. The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 175 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Expansion along the Aver EIC Handler: The Hochlander [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. Will remove this section from future turns and regain the half-turn invested in it. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Julia to find out if she's interested in being poached or passing on information. [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Start building a paramilitary river navy to ensure the coming trade explosion doesn't lead to a similar explosion in riverine banditry. [ ] EIC: Sell some of the Grand Urbaz Bank coins to collectors and museums on King Belegar's behalf. [ ] EIC: Integrate the Gong Farmers and the Niter Factory into the EIC, and expand production. [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. Personal Actions: you have four actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. Current overwork status: [-] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. Current Task: Karag Dum Expedition preparations [ ] Seek out merchants who have travelled the Skull Road to learn what they know of it. [ ] Trawl around the bars and brothels of Tilea, looking to talk to the actual mercenaries that have walked either the Skull Road, or the Great Steppes. [ ] Attempt to recruit assistance for the Karag Dum Expedition. (specify the individual, mercenary group, cult, College, or other; two choices per AP spent) [ ] With the help of a gyrocarriage, personally scout part of the route (specify: High Pass, Road of Skulls, Western Great Steppes, Karag Dum vicinity) [ ] Attempt to learn the Greenskin tongue to communicate with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Attempt to learn Kurgan to communicate with the Kurgan of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Kurgan of the Steppes. Spoiler: Qrech Qrech [ ] Despite him considering it treasonous, push Qrech to share the Moulder dialect of Queekish. [ ] Despite him considering it blasphemous, push Qrech to share High Queekish. Qrech Gambits (can be taken for free alongside a Qrech option): [ ] Convince Qrech that you seek an arrangement with Clan Moulder, and that you will release him as an ambassador for that arrangement once you are satisfied he'll cooperate. [ ] Convince Qrech that the Under-Empire has no way of knowing he's even alive, and that he should prioritize the comfort with which he will live the rest of his life. [ ] Convince Qrech you're ambitious and loyal only to yourself, and you're willing to repay his cooperation in ways that will benefit the Under-Empire. [ ] Other (write in) Self-Improvement: [ ] Ask an acquaintance to train you in a skill: specify who and what. [ ] Attempt to learn a spell from scrolls (specify which, will be harder than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Hire a trainer to come to Eight Peaks and teach you: specify what. (costs favours for Dwarf or College trainers, money for human ones) [ ] Travel to the Grey College and attend lessons there. (1 College Favour per class; 100gc can be paid instead for non-magical classes) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Gain enough control of your unruly shadow to still it temporarily. [ ] Gain enough control of your attraction to smoke and gases to have it collect away from your face. [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Try to create them. [ ] Have one of Prince Gotri's pilots teach you to fly a gyrocopter. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] Dictate papers: select which two, must be taken with Max's 'receive dictation'. [ ] Investigate the possibility of using one Wind to directly manipulate another. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. [ ] Try to establish a relationship with the Cult of Verena, with the intent of offering them access to your rarer tomes in exchange for copies of some of their own. [ ] Record all the entries of the Grand Urbaz vaults and select a good-quality example of each minting to save from the smelters. Aethyric Vitae (13 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item with a Fiendishly Complex or easier spell (specify what and which) [ ] Attempt to enchant an object to translate Windsight into a visual image. [ ] Attempt to deepen your skill with Enchantment (will be more difficult than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) (NEW) [ ] Turn a staff from mundane materials. [ ] Turn a staff from the horn of a Storm Dragon. Karag Nar Penthouse: each turn, you get ONE free choice in this category. Additional selections cost actions. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have a tower built atop Karag Nar: -100gc for 1 room, bonus to room's purpose. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have additional rooms excavated underneath your Penthouse: -150gc for 6 rooms. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Your dungeon was built with a reasonable amount of paranoia. Apply an unreasonable amount of paranoia. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add security measures to your Penthouse to prevent forcible entry. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have firing platforms built around the Penthouse so that it can be defended from flyers or climbers without granting access to it. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add preservation Runes to your library: -4 Dwarf Favour, can be paid for with book budget DF for next two purchase periods. Setting up rooms for specific purposes will have to wait until new rooms are constructed or excavated. Only one construction or excavation can take place at a time, but you can do one of each. Building downwards will increase by 1 each time; second set of excavated rooms will be 3 rooms, third will be 4, and so on. Building upwards can be added upon; towers can be added on to or additional towers can be built. The distinction between the two is entirely cosmetic. Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in the Sylvanian campaign (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Marienburg affair (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Black Waters project (specify how) Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting with a fellow councillor's task: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Warp Lightning observations - shared with Adela (FRESH) Azyr Lighting mechanism - shared with Adela (FRESH) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition. (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual. (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae. (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - For reference, here's the sustainable speeds for various possible recruits for the Expedition: Spoiler: Travel speeds Steam-Wagon: 3-6 MPH, 12-16 hours/day. Estimated 50-100 miles/day. Human: 3 MPH for 6 hours/day. 18 miles/day. Dwarf: 3 MPH for 10 hours/day. 30 miles/day. Heavy Cavalry: 4 MPH for 8 hours/day. 32 miles/day. Light Cavalry: 5 MPH for 8 hours/day. 40 miles/day. Ogres: 4 MPH for 12 hours/day. 48 miles/day. Steppe Horse: 6 MPH for 10 hours/day. 60 miles/day. Cold Ones: 10 MPH for 6 hours/day. 60 miles/day. Steppe Horse w/ remounts: 8 MPH for 10 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Bretonnian Horse: 8 MPH for 10 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Demigryphs: 10 MPH for 8 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Winter Wolves: 5 MPH for 16 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Shadowsteed: 15 MPH for 6 hours/day. 90 miles/day. Mathilde's Shadowsteed: 25 MPH for 10 hours/day. 250 miles/day. Bretonnian horses have Magical Bullshit Genes from crossbreeding with Elven horses. Demigryphs and Winter Wolves are slightly cranked up numbers from cougars and wolves. Steppe horses are based on what the Mongols achieved.

Turn 31 Results - 2485 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan: Battle Huskies, Fog Path, Record Coins, and Proper Security Measures - [*][MAX] Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. (NEW) - [*][JOHANN] Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. (NEW) - [*][DUCK] Attempt to recruit Hubert and some Winter Wolves for the Karag Dum Expedition. - [*][EIC] Start building a paramilitary river navy to ensure the coming trade explosion doesn't lead to a similar explosion in riverine banditry. -[*] Hire a trainer to come to Eight Peaks and teach you: Melkoth’s Mystifying Miasma by Lord Magister Melkoth (10 College Favor) --[*] COIN: The Gambler. -[*] Attempt to create a spell: Fog Path also with help from Melkoth and possibly Regimand -[*] Ask an acquaintance to train you in a skill: Regimand, Assassination -[*] Record all the entries of the Grand Urbaz vaults and select a good-quality example of each minting to save from the smelters. -[*][PENTHOUSE] Your dungeon was built with a reasonable amount of paranoia. Apply an unreasonable amount of paranoia. -[*][SERENITY] Azyr Lighting mechanism To your very great relief, Kislev's weather continues to be Kislev's weather and the Winter is just as harsh at High Pass as it is everywhere else that far north, and every indication is that there's no hope of the Expedition setting out this year. With Johann and Max unleashed to see to their own preparations with instructions to let you know if there's anything you can help with, you turn your attention to Hubert. There are people upon whom you'd need to unleash all of the guile that the Grey College is known for to get them to go on an ill-advised adventure into the Chaos Wastes, but Hubert isn't one of them. "I'm in," he says, almost before you've finished asking. "Great," you say, making up for in enthusiasm what you lack in surprise. "I'd also like your help bringing in some of the Winter Wolves. They'd be right at home on the Steppe, and able to keep pace with the steam-wagons." He nods. "Some of them are getting a bit restless. There's only so many times you can pick off a straggler from Iron Rock or Thunder Mountain before it gets old." "Are you speaking from experience?" you ask suspiciously. "As part of being the Karak's diplomat to Ulrikadrin," he says as innocently as he can manage, which isn't saying much. "I suppose it's better than you doing so solo." The trip to Ulrikadrin is largely uneventful, though this time you have to meet Hubert there instead of travelling with him, as he much prefers his own newfound ability to fly to subjecting himself to a Shadowsteed once more. It seems like the Ulricans are still arguing amongst themselves what form the headquarters that the Karak still owes them will take, as construction has yet to begin and they're still living amongst the people of Ulrikadrin. You're starting to wonder if it will linger that way long enough that they'll get used to it and the mountaintop monastery will never be built. Whatever the case, that's not your problem, and with Hubert at your side you once more make your way to the Temple of Ulric that serves as the current headquarters of the Winter Wolves. "Hubert!" roars a happy voice, and before you can react the youth disappears into a crowd of back-slapping and chattering off-duty Winter Wolves. It's good that he gets on with them so well, but you'd brought him with you for a reason. Which might be why he was so enthusiastically greeted and removed from the picture; despite the primitivist trappings of their God, the Ulricans are quite familiar with politics. "Loremaster Weber," comes the voice of Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart, right on cue. "Sir Wulfhart," you reply, turning to greet him. "How fares Ulrikadrin?" "It's built atop a trade thoroughfare, it would be difficult for it not to thrive," he says, though he's plainly conflicted about that. You imagine it's quite far from the hardy self-sufficient frontier town he'd imagined. "Things have grown rather peaceful in this corner of the continent," you say leadingly. "Ideal for the settlers, but I imagine the idyll chafes the Winter Wolves." He considers you for long enough that you're fairly sure he suspects where you're going with this. "Our first duty is the protection of our flock," he eventually says, "but we are lacking in challenges. Some are beginning to look outwards, wishing to seek new foes, lest our claws grow dull." "I have something in mind that could serve very well, then. I've been looking north. Very north." "Is the Great Enemy stirring?" he asks instantly. "No more so than normally, at least as far as I know. This is leftover business from last time. Have you ever heard of Karag Dum?" He frowns. "One of the Norse Dwarf Holds?" "Not quite. Karag Dum is in the Steppes, rather than Norsca, and hasn't been heard from since the Great War. Karak Kadrin is planning an expedition for Spring of '86 to learn their fate. Ideally to reopen a line of communications with them, but otherwise to evacuate survivors and relics. Myself and two of my Wizards have already joined the Expedition, and I'd like Hubert and some Winter Wolves to join us." [Recruiting the Winter Wolves: Diplomacy, 72+14+2(Library: Ulric)=88.] "The Steppes, you say," he says thoughtfully. "The Winter Wolves have had many opportunities to test themselves against the Norscans, but never in my lifetime against those who gave rise to Asavar Kul. Who will be commanding the Expedition?" "In overall command is a noble from Karag Dum, Borek Forkbeard of Clan Grimnar, who carried the last communication we had from the hold. The military commander is a Ranger by the name of Snorri Farstrider." "I've found Rangers easy to work with. The Expedition's size?" "Between three and four hundred." He frowns. "So few?" "If we need more than that, we'd probably need an army. The focus is on maximum efficacy per head, which is why I've come to you." "I thought the Grey College was supposed to be subtle," he says, but with a smile. "Anyone else of note associated with the Expedition?" "I've brought in a mercenary of some repute, by the name of Asarnil." "Never paid much mind to-" he pauses. "Wait, the Dragon?" "The Elf that rides him, but yes." "This is beginning to sound like something that songs will be sung about," he says with a grin. "And I'm of the opinion that there ought to be a verse or two in glory of Ulric in those songs. The Winter Wolves will ride with this Expedition." --- Melkoth is a formidable individual. He'd be a legend outside the Grey College if most of what he did isn't extremely secret, and he'd be a legend inside of it if he didn't hate people making a fuss over him. Most Apprentices get introduced to him by an older Apprentice telling them the year Melkoth was born and asking them how old he is. Some Apprentices who can't let the puzzle go have their sense of time compromised for weeks or even months afterwards, and though it leads to a fair number of missed classes, the Grey College considers this very good training on avoiding harmful mental influences. Through trial and error you'd managed to deduce it down to a five-year range before you'd realized it was wiser to let the matter rest. He'd declined your offer of a gyrocopter and had travelled via rivercraft all the way from Altdorf with a few detours he doesn't comment on and you know better than to ask about, though you make a mental note to check if there's any impact to piracy along the Aver. He settles himself into your guest quarters, rummages through your library, side-eyes Wolf suspiciously, and spends a fair bit of time grumbling about Khazalid before he's good and ready to start teaching, but you wait patiently, confident his advice will be worth it. [Learning Melkoth's Mystifying Miasma: Learning, 91+28+5(Library: Ulgu)+20(Coin)+20(Room of Dawn and Dusk)+???(Melkoth's tutoring)=???.] And it is, in a way. --- "You know how Ulgu gets wibbly when you're pulling on just enough of it that the shadows start to quiver?" "Wibbly?" "Sideways-upwards from reality." "Oh, that tugging?" "Yes, like a stutter. You need to grab it during that and pull. Not a yank, just a long, steady pull. And don't pull into you, pull towards you and then let the inflow do the rest." --- "No, you're twisting it. Feel the unevenness there? That fraying?" "Just here?" "No, a moment ago. While you were condensing on the other side." "That flow's been steady the entire time, why's it only now playing up?" "That flow's been waiting the entire time." --- "Okay, what am I doing wrong here? I know I've got the mental state right." "You've got it exactly correct?" "Yes!" "And what's your dog doing?" "...playing?" "Either get him to cut it out, or overshoot to compensate. Actually, just overshoot. It's good training. Need to be able to do that on the fly when you don't have time to centre yourself." --- "Stop thinking of the Miasma as a delivery mechanism." "How do you know I have been?" "Because I've watched three generations of Battle Wizards screw up the same spell in the same way for the same reason. That mental separation is just enough of an opportunity for the Miasma to be able to break free from the Mystifying. They need to be interwoven in your mind to be interwoven in the spell." --- It's a long and exhausting process that severely drains the Ulgu reservoir of your Grey Tower, and Ulgu itself seems to fight you every step of the way. But through it all Melkoth is there, nestled into the armchair he brought with him from Altdorf and with one eye on you and one eye on a book from your library. He seems to intuitively grasp every twist and turn of the Grey Wind and has a knack for communicating what would normally be incommunicable. As the weeks pass, you learn how to form and unleash the most basic Battle Magic of the Grey College: Melkoth's very own Mystifying Miasma. The secret behind it is that it doesn't actually affect the mind of those caught in it, which could be resisted by the strong-willed - it alters reality in such a way that to those inside it time runs just a little bit slower, indirectly slowing reaction speeds and disorienting even the most highly-trained of combatants. Many elite warriors train to be able to fight when in altered states, but you've never heard of any that have trained to fight effectively when the passage of time becomes a variable. [Spell learned: Melkoth's Mystifying Miasma] --- You'd built your guest room to be modular so you could subdivide it into two for your two Grey Wizard guests, but Regimand turns down your offer in favour of making himself at home in some of the Karag's nicer establishments. Though you're a little put out, you're fairly sure you know why and that it isn't official business - Regimand owns inns and taverns across the Empire, because being able to guarantee secure and discreet housing at zero notice is Of Direct And Practical Use To His Cause. It also justifies any wealth he might accumulate as being an unavoidable necessity to expand his network, and of course he has to collect the profits from them or otherwise that lack of financial outlay might give away the true motives of the owner. Completely justifiable. And now it seems he might be expanding into the newest friendly corner of the Old World, which says good things about how secure the Karak seems from an outsider's perspective. "So," he says, as he shimmers into view on the chair beside you. "What did you need?" "If I didn't know you were here, I probably would have shot at that jumping patch of Ulgu," you comment as you slip a bookmark into Beyond the Great Bastion. "Smoke and Mirrors, I take it?" "With enough Skywalks to keep downwards velocity down." He looks out at the view he'd just teleported his way up. "Your Magesight must have gotten pretty good to pick up an Ulgu chain-cast." "Speaking of, I seem to recall you lecturing me at length about why one doesn't chain-cast." "Normally I'd stick by that, but I honed this particular chain-cast rooftop-hopping across Marienburg back in the sixties. Only have to fall in the river a couple of times before you learn not to." You nod. "Fair enough. I want you to help me hone my skills at assassination." He frowns. "The entire process?" "No, just the moment of. I'm going to be venturing into the Chaos Wastes, and I don't want to have fair fights against whatever I end up facing there." "Good policy. You planning on whacking whatever you encounter with that behemoth of a sword?" "Only if I have to. It's not exactly quiet." You concentrate for a moment and summon a dagger of solid Ulgu into your hands. "Mostly I'd be using this." He squints at it thoughtfully. "Is that a Shadow Knives manifestation?" "Sort of, I think. Or halfway between that and a shadow chisel." "A what?" You dismiss the dagger and reform the energies into a chisel. "Cantrip to replace enchantment paraphernalia. Learned it from who I think was one of Algard's Hands." "I take it the chisel doesn't bypass armour like Shadow Knives?" You nod. "Pity. Let me know if you do manage to codify the dagger." He looks at it thoughtfully, drumming his fingers on his armrest. "Have you ever studied anatomy?" "Not in its own right. A little for interrogation, a little for autopsying, a little for study of some species..." "That's a good place to start, then." --- [Applied anatomy: Learning, 43+28+9(Library: Anatomy)=80.] You know the basics, of course. The organs someone needs to stay alive, the tendons they need to be a threat. When someone is unaware that you're about to introduce a blade to one of those possibilities, you're quite capable of removing them from the tactical situation with one of those options. You're even capable of scaling up appropriately when the target is an Orc. What you've not previously been introduced to is the idea that these are not necessarily constants. When the followers of the Daemonic Powers are involved, things like organ locations and how necessary they might be for their owner's continued survival aren't quite as nailed down. This changes things dramatically. It's no longer a solved question, it's a puzzle with several unknowns, and the answer can differ quite a bit based on whether you need a lack of noise, a lack of mess, or both. As well as going through his own personal experiences with the anatomy of those that serve the Ruinous Powers, both Beastmen and those that were at least originally human, he runs you through his preferred techniques for dealing with them. A stab that skewers the heart and both lungs would usually be considered overkill, but not when you can't really rely on those organs being where they're supposed to be, or be entirely sure that there wouldn't be a back-up somewhere. [Daemonic anatomy: Learning, 76+28+4(Library: Daemons)=108.] The other half of what he has to teach you is both more complicated and less known to him: the anatomy of Daemons. Yes, they're made of warpstuff rather than flesh and blood, but that warpstuff is often formed into facsimiles of flesh and blood to strengthen the ability of a Daemon to exist in the physical world. Puncturing a Daemon's heart doesn't guarantee the end of the encounter, but it's slightly more effective than stabbing whatever's closest to hand and hoping for the best. Or at least, that's the case for unaffiliated Daemons, and for at least the lesser Daemons of the Violent and the Obsessive. Daemons of the Diseased have the organs but in such a state that it's hard to make the situation worse with a mere blade, and Daemons of the Plotter have bodies made of sinuous, flickering warpstuff that in any given moment is as likely to be a liquid or a gas as it is to contain anything recognizable as an organ. Those require a completely different approach entirely, and it's here that Regimand's depth of experience starts to grow thin, as he's only had a few encounters with manifested Daemons, and most of them only taught him a single lesson: try to avoid encounters with manifested Daemons. Despite the usable information running thin at the end there, it's a depth of hard-won experience that would have taken a significant amount of time and effort and risk to accumulate yourself. You feel like you're that much better equipped to avoid fair fights with whatever it is you might encounter on the journey to Karag Dum. [Skill increased: Advanced Assassination 3/3: You know how to end a variety of forms of life with a single stab. +2 Intrigue] - To be continued. Writing will likely resume about two days from now after dealing with IRL stuff.

Turn 31 Results - 2485 - Part 2

As you stare at the blank chalkboard and fidget with a piece of chalk, it occurs to you that you've never really created a spell from scratch before. The Multidimensional Aethyric Projection doesn't really count, that's just corralling Ulgu into the required shapes, which is just an alternative manifestation of the basic techniques of spellcasting. And with Mathilde's Mystical Matrix you had a design to work off. But this time, you've only got your objective to guide you: create a spell that allows for travel over broken terrain. Apart from that single end goal, you're starting completely from scratch. Actually, that's not entirely true, is it? You flick your eyes over the books on Ulgu theory you've already stacked up in your Room of Serenity, and sigh to yourself when you realize it didn't occur to you to bring up the one you wanted. Another trip down to your library and back and you have a stack of books on the very basics of Ulgu spellcasting, and as you skim through the books and start inserting colour-coded bookmarks, you consider the problem in the back of your mind. Most spells are only recorded as a set of instructions that will create a specific effect, without any record of the logic behind those instructions. Some were never recorded out of selfish pride or paranoia on the part of the inventor, others were invented by the Elves or by civilizations lost to history so the College only has access to the spell itself, still others are so steeped in a specific Wizard's unique viewpoint that they could only be understood by themselves. Consider Shadowsteed: to your mindset, Ulgu is not a swift wind, nor one especially attuned to horses. If you'd never heard of the spell, you'd think it better suited to Hysh or perhaps Ghur. But you tend to think first in terms of Elemental Ulgu, the fog and the shadow, where the inventor of the spell was much more Mystical and drew inspiration from the inexorable march of dawn and dusk that loop the world every day. Most Grey Wizards can cast the spell, but few could recreate the underlying logic unless they dedicated themselves to the study of the moments on the cusp between day and night. But that's not the case for every spell. The Lesser Magics held in common between the Colleges are so simple and widely-known that they make ideal examples, and entire books have been dedicated to reverse-engineering them, written by Wizards of every College. The one you have your eye on is Skywalk, the spell that allows the caster to walk on empty air for a few precious seconds. It does seem like a natural starting point. [Incorporating Skywalk: Learning, 62+28+7(Library: Sevir)=97.] It's also significantly easier said than done. The Lesser Magics are universal because of the very small amount of magical energies they use. Basic Winds theory states that the more of a Wind is concentrated in one place, the more tempestuous it is, which is why Battle Magics are so powerful and so dangerous. The flip side to that is that very small amounts of Winds are much more malleable, to the extent that their identity can be completely lost. This is sometimes referred to as Earthbound Magic as small amounts of it can be drawn out of almost any mundane object, and this undifferentiated magical energy is believed to be what allows for witches, hedge wizards, the Hedgewise, and Elementalists to create magics that don't align with the Teclisean model. It's also believed to power the Runes of the Dwarves, which take in whatever Wind is available and somehow break it down into undifferentiated magic, which would be believed impossible to do in large quantities if the Dwarves weren't so clearly doing it. What all that amounts to here and now is that Skywalk cannot be simply scaled up. Increasing its effect would require more power, which would require more Winds, which would change the nature of those Winds, and you would now have to alter the spell to obey the nature of that Wind. Celestials could do it easily, and you think Lights could work something out. You think Ulgu could manage something similar, but creating a second entirely new spell would require even more time. [Using Skywalk as-is: Learning, 54+28+7(Library: Sevir)=89.] Using one Wind to manipulate another is a fairly well-established idea, albeit in the form of Necromancy. What about using a Wind to manipulate itself? Can a larger spell create localized Skywalk at enough of a distance to keep the small amount of energy from being influenced by the much larger amount that the spell as a whole would be made of? Now you're finally able to mar the perfect blankness of the chalkboard as you begin to play with thaumaturgic equations. Most spells try to remain as self-contained as possible to remain under the caster's control and so that outside forces and influences can't get involved, but this would require the creation of spells at a considerable distance. You picture a massive rolling fogbank with a core of solid Ulgu, with uncountable strands descending like puppet strings to create and maintain the same tiny spell over and over again, and you frown as you picture the complexity of it. [Minify Skywalk: Learning, 93+28+5(Library: Ulgu)=126.] Lesser Magics aren't just spells, they're training tools. They're designed to be as easy to cast as possible. But they aren't as simple as possible. If you assume a competent and skilled caster and strip the spell right down to the bone... Days pass in a haze of equations and revisions as you rebuild the spell over and over, only interrupted by other Wizards checking up on you. Regimand spends three hours decoding the thaumaturgic glyphs for one of the later revisions of the spell before he figures out what it's supposed to be. Melkoth manages to cast it, but grumbles about a knot in his brain for the rest of the day. By the end of it you've got it down to eleven concatenated symbols and you're no longer entirely sure why it works. It would never be worth the time to teach this version of the spell to someone, as it would take ten times as long and save them a minuscule amount of power. But if you're going to be using the same spell hundreds of times a second, every scrap of concentration and power you save yourself will be an immense help. With the first component of the spell completed, it's well past time to take a break before you lose the ability to communicate in anything but Praestantic equations. --- You'd been internally debating the matter of the coins of the Grand Urbaz for some time. On one hand, it's a great deal of work that can't be handed off to anyone else for reasons of secrecy, and that's time that could be spent preparing for your rapidly approaching jaunt into the Chaos Wastes. On the other, a complete numismatic history of both Tylos and Strygos wouldn't just be a notable historical artefact in its own right, it would also shed light on forgotten chapters of human history in the Old World. After all, the peoples of Tilea and Estalia are believed to be descended from those that survived the fall of Tylos. And though Strygos was ruled by the vampire Ushoran, its peoples were still a cousin tribe to those that would go on to found the Empire, and history might have been very different if they weren't there and Waaaghs were able to flow north towards the nascent Empire unimpeded. Of course, the Nehekharan portions of history are rather better known, and many of the rulers on those coins are still ruling over the deserts to the south. But they tend to be inhospitable to visitors, so there could still be value in those portions of the vaults, even if the information still technically exists somewhere amongst the sands. And if you're already going through it all for coins from Tylos and Strygos, it wouldn't be much extra effort to catalogue and collect the Nehekharan ones. The Tylosian coins are fairly straightforward. They don't have the date of minting like modern coinage, but you're able to deduce a year for all of them by the date they started being deposited. Most of the golden coins are dedicated to either Myrmidia or a man who appears to be the city's legendary father of the Tilean people, Tyleus. There's also representations of Verena, Morr, and Shallya, as well as a God you don't recognize. From the symbology you'd guess Taal, except you're fairly sure Taal is one of the Northern Gods, and wouldn't have been known to the ancestors of Tilea. There's also some of the Dwarven Ancestor Gods scattered throughout. The silver coins are largely dedicated to temporal rulers, and judging by their turnover either they were elected to a temporary position of power, or Tylosian politics were especially rambunctious. You also see several dedicated to local prestige projects, temples and aqueducts and bridges and lighthouses. In some of the chronologically last coins, the depictions of a grand tower sends a shiver down your spine when you realize what it must be depicting. The Strygosi coins are much more straightforward. The early coins from when the city was Mourkhain are largely dedicated to its ruler Kadon, bearing one of his face, his pyramid, or his crown. The only exception are ones bearing a different face entirely, its eyes closed and its features seeming more Arabyan than northern, which you spend some time puzzling over. When Ushoran claimed the city the coinage increased substantially in quality and started using a regnal calendar, which is extremely straightforward with an immortal ruler. It gets somewhat tedious to see the same fanged face on every single coin, so it's the silver coins that capture your attention, bearing the banners of various Orc tribes and Waaaghs and the year they were defeated. There's a lot of different victories commemorated. You feel a new appreciation for how incredibly difficult it must have been to build a civilization in the Badlands. The Nehekharan coins are easily the most varied. Nehekhara was a land of city-states and each of them minted their own coins in glory of their rulers and their Gods, which means that even though there's only really a representation of the Fourth, Fifth, and Sixth Dynaties, there's still a dizzying array of coins to catalogue, dating from Lahmizzar to Alcadizzar. That last one causes an itch of familiarity at the back of your mind and it takes you some time to realize why, and upon comparing the Nehekharan coins depicting Alcadizzar to the Mourkhainian ones with the unknown face, you find they're as identical as the quality of the coinage could reasonably permit. What few historical records there are agree that Mourkhain was founded by the Lodringen tribe, so why were they commemorating a Nehekharan King on their coinage? Did they take in Nehekharan refugees? Did Alcadizzar escape the fate of his homeland and spend time in Mourkhain? You put the matter aside as something to investigate in the unlikely event you ever have more time than you have things to do. Apart from the odd sense of familiarity that the Nehekharan coins depicting a hooded snake cause you, the rest of the cataloguing is uneventful, and after weeks of work you're left with enough coins to fill several coin cabinets that Belegar had a hobbyist carpenter of Clan Angrund put together. You tuck them away in your vault for now, and when you have the time you'll figure out a way to have it plausibly introduced to the historical record. --- As you and Adela start to put pen to paper on the matter of the Lighting Mechanism, Adela's rough edges start to show. As you can't see lightning-powered lighting being at all practical you're happy to have her take the lead on this one, but it quickly becomes apparent that Adela is not very suited to collaboration, having a strong tendency to disappear inside her own head as she uses her uncanny memory to consult her mental library. As the days drag on and she clearly struggles to wrap her mind and her pen around the alien logic of Azyr, you start to quietly take notes on the side in case you need to write the paper yourself. Thankfully, consultation with Hubert manages to push past Adela's writer's block, as if there's one thing about magic he knows it's lightning. From there she gamely pushes on and though she starts to flag before all is said and done, the resulting paper is close enough in quality to the one you were mentally preparing that you put the matter from your mind. It's not exactly a groundbreaking paper, but neither was your first contribution to academia, and Adela seems delighted to have her name on something, and doubly so to have it alongside yours. And even if it's not going to set the world on fire, in academia it never hurts to keep your name out there. [Adela writing the paper on the Azyr Lighting Mechanism: 15+20+10(Adaptable Mechanic)+2(Library: Azyr)+5(Uncanny Memory)+10(Fresh)=62.] [Coaching Adela through writing the paper: Diplomacy, 6+14+2(Library: Azyr)=22.] [Hubertian consultation: Learning, 83+14+2(Library: Azyr)=99.] [Writing the paper yourself: Learning, 43+28+2(Library: Azyr)+10(Fresh)=83.] [Using Azyr to Create a Bright and Even Light, 2485. Subject: Uncommon, +0. Insight: Agreement, +0. Delivery: Competent, +0. Alien, +1. Thorough, +1. Secondary Author, -2. Total: +0, raised to minimum of +1.] The rest of your time is spent seeing to the incorporation of various increased security measures into your dungeon. As unwilling guests go, Qrech has been a comparative delight to host, seemingly content with his life of model-making, the companionship of Skufit, and his near-complete Diploma of Near-Eastern Studies from the University of Altdorf. But you know his psychology well enough that you know that it is built upon a foundation of an inability to return to his Clan, and if that changed, so would his contentment with his current living situation as his loyalty to Clan and Empire took precedence. So with you about to spend months away, it's a sensible precaution to upgrade the security measures around your dungeon to ensure that he can't get out, and nobody else can get in unless you want them to. By the time you and the team of Dwarven artisans is complete, gaining entrance to the penthouse is only halfway to gaining entrance to the dungeon, and it could also serve as a makeshift panic room if need be. --- Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time, this past year? The four with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) [+] EIC Reports (does not cost a choice) Romance Any victors from the below will trigger a subvote for how you'll spend time with them. Choosing any of these will represent a first tentative expression of romantic interest. While this would not be a soft-lock, it could be awkward to walk that back if Mathilde decides her heart lies elsewhere. [ ] [ROMANCE] Journeywoman Panoramia [ ] [ROMANCE] Magister Johann [ ] [ROMANCE] Elector Countess Roswita van Hal [ ] [ROMANCE] Baron Anton Kiesinger II [ ] [ROMANCE] The Ice Dragon of Karag Zilfin [ ] [ROMANCE] Chief Bombardier Oswald Oswaldson Fellow Wizards [ ] Gretel, who's apparently spending her newly-earned wealth to make herself at home. [ ] Hubert, as he settles in to his niche with Ulrikadrin. Karak Eight Peaks Notables [ ] Belegar, to discuss the northern Karaks and the Expedition. [ ] Elder Hluodwica, High Priestess of Esmerelda and civilian leader of the Eight Peaks Halflings. [ ] Francesco Caravello, proud Viceroy of the Undumgi. [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart, leader of the frontier town of Ulrikadrin. Foreign Relations [ ] Barak Varr, to watch the progress of the canal. [ ] Stirland, to see for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. Friends Abroad [ ] Kasmir, to see how he's keeping himself busy in Sylvania. [ ] Julia, to see what she has gotten up to as Stirland's most experienced spy master. [ ] Eike Hochschild, to get to know your future business partner. Following Up [ ] The Amber College, to check in on the salamanders. [ ] The Gold College, to see what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Feel free to make suggestions for other social actions. - Melkoth didn't get involved in the spell creation process because he wasn't needed. If Mathilde had hit a roadblock or it turned out the Skywalk approach wouldn't work, then he would have been brought in. Same sort of thing as when you use the Coin on something and then you obliterate it in the first diceroll. - Melkoth and Regimand will be attending Duckling Club.

Turn 31 Social - 2485 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) [+] EIC Reports (does not cost a choice) [*] Belegar, to discuss the northern Karaks and the Expedition. [*] [ROMANCE] Journeywoman Panoramia [*] Kasmir, to see how he's keeping himself busy in Sylvania. [*] Barak Varr, to watch the progress of the canal. Belegar's personal quarters are in a state of uncertainty, as debate amongst Clan Angrund is focused on whether the Royal Clan should be housed in close proximity to the current de facto Throne Room in Karag Lhune, the original de jure Throne Room under the Citadel, or somewhere else to establish a completely new beginning for the reborn Karak. So you've invited him to your own quarters for the discussion you intend to have, and though his Hammerers are ever by his side, between your own proven trustworthiness and the security of your penthouse they relax a fraction and accept seats and drinks at a discreet distance. "Hell of a view," Belegar says, gazing out over his Karak. "Shame that Gotri's gyrocopters are taking up the peak of Karag Lhune, or I'd be tempted to set up something similar." He takes a pull from the ale you'd offered him and grunts in surprise. "Sticking with the zinti brewers?" "At least for now. Dourback's currently focused on recreating the old recipes, and while that's all well and good, I like a bit of a surprise when I broach a new barrel." "They'll re-diversify after they settle in. They were doing quite well for themselves in the Empire, brewing ales for manling tastes. Once they've scaled up production enough to satisfy the thirsts here, they'd be foolish not to go back to supplying their old contacts - especially once the canal's done. Though I daresay it wasn't ales you wished to discuss, as rich a topic as that is." "The Karag Dum Expedition. There's something that I'm missing here. Near sixty thousand Dwarves marched south with you, but less than five hundred are going north." "Ah. Yes." He mulls that over, taking a long drink from his tankard. "First of all, there's the usual matter of Old versus Young. Only had four thousand from Karak Kadrin, half of them Slayers, and Karaz-a-Karak and Barak Varr only gave materiel support. The rest were from Norn or Hirn or Izor, or were Clanless. And it was almost very different - if I had left Altdorf outright when the Elector's Meet turned out to be a waste of time, I would have returned to Karaz-a-Karak and would have eventually ventured forth with only a few thousand. But I gave the manlings a chance to rise above their leadership, and by Grimnir they did. There's two thousand manlings interred in the foundations of Karag Lhune now, and it's all the stronger for it and I'd declare a Grudge on anyone who said otherwise. "But apart from the direct assistance of the citizens of the Empire, being based in Reikland and later in Averland meant I was close enough to exchange a lot of letters with the Young Holds, and I had the legitimacy of having armed forces accumulating. Not just a Beggar-King appearing in their halls once a generation to ask for troops, but a growing and imminent Expedition that they had the opportunity to negotiate with. Princess Edda is..." he hesitates. "...talented in her niche, but less flexible than perhaps she could be. But as the price for Karak Izor's assistance, it's a deal I don't regret. Similarly, Karak Hirn wanted... hmm..." "To remove the least favoured son from the picture." "Ah, you know about that." You nod. "Got it straight from Ulthar." "Least favoured, hah. And then what happens once there were only two Princes left... there's something rotten in the foundations of that Clan, and I pray the Ancestors give Ulthar strength enough to root it out, and that Alrik manages to rediscover his honour long enough to shave his head and let the Throne pass to Ulthar. But anyway, point is, this was all Young Holds. To them, Karak Eight Peaks wasn't an aching scar, it was a beautiful legend. They were bold where Karaz-a-Karak was weary. But when we're speaking of Old Holds, Karag Dum was definitely an Old Hold, and even Karaz-a-Karak considers them arrogant. Even in desperation, this envoy of theirs only treats with Karak Kadrin and Zhufbar and Karaz-a-Karak - he even snubbed Barak Varr, as Karag Dum considers them weakened by their dependence on trade." "So it's not that this Expedition isn't being supported, it's that those that are supporting it are doing so with goods rather than lives." "Aye. Part of that is regular Old Hold reticence - they're astonishingly rich, but their population is shrinking and they've no desire to accelerate that, so given the choice they'll supply steel instead of blood every time. But the other half of the story goes back to before my time. I was born shortly before Thorgrim's hundredth year on the Throne of Power, so I only know what my grandfather told me of the Great War Against Chaos, and the Council of Kings that followed it. It was..." Belegar sighs, and takes a moment to refill his flagon from the barrel. "It was a time that some call the Skedanbryn, the Stolen Hope. The forces of ruin were battering at our doors, but not one Hold succumbed to the temptation to seal itself away and diminish, and every Hold's banners flew on the walls of Kislev. Our ancient allies of the Empire had pulled themselves back together after centuries of division and civil war. And the greatest of all miracles, as we chased the shattered enemy from the borders of Kislev, we met our long-lost cousins in the Battle of Grovod Wood, who we had thought lost in the Coming of Chaos. It seemed like a turning point in our history, a time of resurgence. Even the news that High King Alriksson was dying could not damper our hope, and at the Council of Kings Thorgrim rode that hope onto the Throne with his promise of an Age of Vengeance. "My grandfather was almost elected," King Belegar says, his voice strained. "That thought consumed him until his dying day, that he had come so close to getting his hands on the means to recover our ancestral home, but had been defeated when Thorgrim made his late entrance to the Council. But Thorgrim was High King, and then it came time to tally the costs. Every Dwarf Hold had contributed, and each had been so thoroughly weakened that all we could do was maintain our defences against the constant probing from the rats and the greenskins. But though the War was over, the aftershocks went on. Asavar Kul had drawn on Marauders and mutants and daemons from across the northern hemisphere, but when the Chaos Hordes broke against the walls of Kislev, every survivor went north into Norsca, and were rallied under some new champion to attack our northern kin. Last we heard from Kraka Drakk, they had collapsed the mountain itself to take as many of the hordes with them as possible. And Karag Dum had been founded right at the line between the steppes and the Chaos Wastes, but the Great War had pushed that line as far south as Praag and it still shows no sign of receding. As for Karak Vlag... we still don't know. It's as if it was never founded. Not even the watchtowers that used to line the pass remain, nor any sign they were ever built. So not only did we lose our newly rediscovered kin, but we lost major Holds for the first time since the fall of Karak Azgal, and we didn't have enough influence in the world to even know their final moments, or who to level the Grudge against. Thorgrim's Age of Vengeance stopped being about hope and started to be about..." He sighs. "Settling our affairs as best we can before we disappear forever, and have to answer to the Ancestors for what has become of the Empire that They left us." You nod solemnly, having seen that attitude yourself, from Thorgrim himself and from Kragg and from so many others. A sense of doomed fatalism, that doing all in their power isn't enough to turn back the tide, and all it will accomplish is being able to meet their Ancestors without too much shame. "So the assumption is that Karag Dum is doomed," you say. "Zhufbar and Karak Kadrin will do their duty and invest expertise and resources, but not many Dwarves, because that is the one loss they can least afford." "If all I had at my disposal were Dwarves, I'd do the same," Belegar says frankly. "But for all the bravery and artifice of the Dwarves, it was men that held the line at the Battle of Karag Nar and the Battle of the Citadel, it is men that hold Death Pass and keep us connected to the Karaz Ankor, and it was a joint project between the Runesmiths and the Colleges that shattered Waaagh Birdmuncha. If the Karaz Ankor has a future, it is alongside the men of the Empire, as High King Kurgan Ironbeard decreed so long ago. So I sent you." --- One of the benefits of being the Loremaster of a major Karak is that showing up and saying 'I'm nosy, tell me what's going on here' is considered by Dwarves to be entirely within your job description. Over a series of days, you're handed from supervisor to supervisor as each describes their own part of the massive project to link the Empire's rivers with the Black Water. One such supervisor sheepishly admits they're technically already linked, but neither the Aver Falls nor the Zhuf that gives Zhufbar its name are what you'd call navigable. The Project is a much larger scale than you envisioned. The Dwarves are not content to dig another River of Echoes, where boats designed specifically for its narrow and shallow watercourse carry barely a wagonload of cargo each and every year a new diplomatic incident is caused because boaters meet in a particularly narrow area and neither wants to be the one that backs up so the other can pass. This is being dug to what the Dwarves call Monitor Standard, wide enough and deep enough that a fully-loaded River Monitor, or a freight vessel built to the same dimensions, can pass without trouble, and even that is causing grumbling because some say the job won't be properly done until Barak Varr's riverine Ironclad design can pass through. Work is being done on from both sides at once, though weekly map exchanges ensure that both are still on course to meet each other halfway. Starting from the Black Water is a tunnel being dug through the mountains in the same way it has always been, as for all their insight and technology, to Dwarves there is exactly one correct way to dig a tunnel, and that is the way that Grungni did it. Sure, there are vast ventilation pumps bringing fresh air in, and steam vehicles on rails taking away dirt and rubble, but at the very front of the tunnel is a series of wooden scaffolds to allow what looks like an entire Mining Clan at once to bring their picks to bear on the solid rock of the mountain. Occassional side-branches are being dug to pursue interesting veins and deposits that were uncovered by chance, carefully watched over by Lodewardens in case they break through into unexpected tunnels. Far below, the work is far different. Ever since the Purge of the Haunted Hills, migrant workers have swarmed into Southern Stirland in huge numbers to be a part of the logging of the Ghoul Woods, funded by the Counties of Hornau, Sigmaringen and Leicheberg. Even as timber prices crashed the logging continued to free Southern Stirland of their worst neighbour and unlock some prime farmland and pastures, with Schramleben being piled high with logs yet to find a buyer. But even though prices are recovering as shipyards and boatyards throughout the Empire begin to ramp up production, the amount of work available to these migrant workers fell as the Woods shrank, and when the Dwarves arrived to start surveying for their canals and locks, they found a veritable bounty of cheap labour and cheaper timber. Mining through rock is one thing, but digging through soil is quite another, and few grumble about letting manlings do the shovelwork. The manlings are equally happy with the arrangement, as being paid in good Dwarven silver is worth a third again as much in shillings if you find the right moneychanger. There's still a lot of distance to cover vertically and horizontally, especially since the route carefully skirts the ruins of Karak Varn. But so far everything is going exactly as planned. The tricky part will come when it comes time to design the mechanisms to allow boats to make the trip between the Aver Reach below and the Black Water high above, especially since every supervisor seems to have his own answer for how to accomplish that. Lock flights or staircase locks are the most obvious solutions, but others are championing inclined plane canals, boat lifts, caisson locks, and shaft locks, and each champion is able to come up with a long list of drawbacks to every solution but theirs. The ultimate problem seems to be that this is a joint project between Barak Varr and Zhufbar, and both consider themselves to be the ones best suited to overcoming the technical problems: Barak Varr as champion of the rivers, and Zhufbar as the foremost technologists of the Karaz Ankor. You hope that something is able to be worked out soon. If there's one problem that you don't think you have to worry about, it's Marienburg. The upper excavation is prepared for all-out assault from greenskins or Skaven or even fouler things from the depths of the Black Water, so any mere bandits that Marienburg pays off to interfere with them will have a very rude awakening indeed. And of the itinerant workers in Southern Stirland you feel equally confident. An outsider might peg them as an easy target for bribery to sabotage the project, but these are Stirlanders and they, at least for now, are full of patriotic fervour for their province and gratitude for their Dwarven neighbours. Thanks in no small part to Dwarven firepower, the Hunter Count and his successor have been avenging four hundred years of terror and violence that have poured out of Sylvania, and everyone present knows that even if their morals could stretch far enough to accept Marienburg gold, they'd be far more likely to be beaten to death under the shovels of their fellow workers than to manage any substantial damage to the project. When you finish your tour of the dig sites, you feel confident that Marienburg is far more likely to land themselves in trouble than to cause any for this project. --- On paper, Stirland is right on the brink of finally pacifying Sylvania. In reality, things are very far from that simple. Like the Jutone ancestors of the modern Marienburgers, the Fennone ancestors of the Sylvanians were not part of the original tribal unification under Sigmar, instead being conquered by Emperor Sigismund centuries later. This original rift was only widened by the events of 1111, where warpstone meteors, the Black Death, and the invasion of the Skaven and the rise of Frederick Van Hal made Sylvania a cursed land. Mutation, disease, starvation, and predation are common to all who live there. The poor know damn well that their best defence against the horrors of the night is fealty to a Vampire that can command those horrors, rather than relying on the distant armies of an Elector Count. The rich know equally well that they would rather pay taxes in someone else's blood than their own gold. The Sylvanians might be cowed for now after the destruction of Castle Drakenhof, the deployment of the Battle Wizards, and the slaying of most of the more prominent Vampires, but it will take much more than that to win them over to the benefits of Empire and civilization. This is the purpose that Kasmir has apparently dedicated himself to, and it's to some surprise that you finally track him to his current headquarters: a very small town on the northern edge of the marshes between the Hunter's Hills and the Aver Reach. There's a great deal of recent construction as the town takes advantage of cheap timber and the influx of settlers, and the town seems very different to the other Sylvanian towns you've visited. "The town of Bylorhof," Kasmir says with a wave of his hand, walking the streets and nodding to those he passes. "Technically, it's part of County of Leicheberg. If you look at the roads, it's closer to being part of the County of Hornau. But realistically, it's Sylvanian - the people are Sylvanian and the Stirlandian Counts haven't drawn taxes or levies from here in centuries. But it's never been ruled by Vampires, either. Vlad von Carstein never tried, and though Mannfred von Carstein did, the Vampire he sent - Count Ranelf von Feuerfliege - was staked and thrown into Bylorhof Marsh." "What makes this place so different?" you ask, consulting a mental map. "It's on the wrong side of the Ghoul Wood for them to escape the attention of the Von Carsteins that much, surely." "Have you ever heard of Manhavok?" Without thinking you make a gesture to placate the God of Floods, and you frown as you try to remember where you learned it. "Yes, that's the one. God of Floods, only worshipped in Stirland, which always struck me as odd. Everyone knows the gesture and most people know the prayer, even if they grew up in the hills far from the gentlest tributary. But I think I know why. The ancient Fennones would worship the bogs, which isn't as strange as it first sounds. Bogs gave them bog-iron and peat and bog-wood and all sorts of berries, and in return the Fennone would give them their worship and the bodies of their dead, which the Vampires later took advantage of. Bylorhof never forgot the old ways, and they still worshipped the God of Bylorhof Marsh, Bylorak, even after the Vampires came. In secret at first, and openly after they struck down Count Ranelf. I think there was once a 'family' of Gods that were worshipped, one for each bog and marsh and swamp, and one for Manhavok for when waters encroached on dry land unexpectedly." You frown to yourself as you remember the shrine to Stromfels under Wurtbad. It seemed strange to you at the time that there'd be a God of Shipwrecking so far inland, but for an ambitious acolyte, Manhavok might have represented some substantial Godly real estate that Stromfels might have been able to subsume, and considering the entire household got buried under flood-silt, perhaps Manhavok objected. "It makes sense," is all you say. "The first clincher for me is Mannfred," Kasmir says. "After the Battle of Hel Fenn, the Imperial forces searched for Mannfred von Carstein's body. Martin of Stirland sent search parties on a regular basis for the rest of his life. Even today our forces keep finding necromancers dredging Hel Fenn. Some people take this as a sign that Mannfred escaped and is licking his wounds somewhere, but everything about him in the history books tells me he's not the type to lay low. If he was out there, we'd know about it. So I think that nobody can find him because Hel Fenn is holding him, just as Bylorak is holding Count Ranelf." You nod to yourself. It doesn't take much to bring a Vampire back. If it hasn't happened yet despite all the foolish Necromancer acolytes doing their best to make it happen, it's reasonable to assume it's because something is stopping them. "You said the first clincher. What's the second?" "Ever been to Hel Fenn?" You think for a moment. "Visited Mikalsdorf once, but didn't pay much attention to the surrounds. Why?" "It's not a fen, it's a swamp." You shrug. "Cartographers mistake? Can't imagine many would be willing to double-check." "That's the thing, I went digging through all the archives I could. Even the earliest maps record it as Hel Fenn, and so does every one since. Always one L, always two Ns. Something's making that name stick. Nobody's ever tried to 'correct' it to two-L one-N Hell Fen. Nobody's ever relabelled it to a swamp. Which makes me wonder where the Fennones got their name. Their foremost God, perhaps?" You think through the rest of your knowledge of the Vampire Wars. "And Grim Moor?" "Is a bog," he says with a smile. "Is it too holding tight onto Konrad?" "Another God hidden in a name?" "Morr, perhaps? Or something like 'Gremmer' that was transliterated into words by outsiders." "All very interesting, but what's it in service of?" He waves a hand. "Sylvanians have no patience for outsiders coming in with outsider Gods. They'll accept our help, and they'll definitely accept our gold, but at the first sign of trouble the priests flee and the Sylvanians will have no choice but to go back to their old habits. What do they care for Sigmar, who overlooked their tribe? What do they care for Taal when their forests are so hostile, or Rhya when their crops so often rot, or Shallya when there's no mercy to be found? But Bylorak succeeded where all others failed. Bylorhof never paid a drop of blood to the Vampire Counts. So if we can re-establish their Old Gods, perhaps they can succeed where ours have failed." --- What setting shall Mathilde choose to ask Panoramia on a date to? [ ] A Shared Meal It worked out well last time. If it's not broke, don't fix it. [ ] A Picnic in the Fields Some are laying fallow with just a thin layer of clover. A perfect setting for a Jade Wizard. [ ] A Scenic Hike You're both active people, and the Silver Tarn is supposed to be beautiful. Go for a hike up Karagril and take in the view. [ ] Drinks and Dice She seemed shocked to learn you worshipped Ranald. Play a few low-stakes games of chance with her at the Karak's own shrine to Him to introduce her to Him properly. - There will be a two hour moratorium. Please do not relitigate the romance vote at this time. - Other date ideas are welcome.

Turn 31 Social - 2485 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] A Scenic Hike You're both active people, and the Silver Tarn is supposed to be beautiful. Go for a hike up Karagril and take in the view. Earlier, you wrestled with the question of how one best asks someone on a sort-of date, until Wolf rendered your careful preparations moot. Now, the question is how one asks someone on an actual definite date. After some thought you stumble upon a possible solution that would be substantially easier: you just pretend that the sort-of date was a definite date and act like this is date number two. Panoramia has shown herself to be very insightful, so you're hoping that she'd pick up on all the unspoken parts and know where everyone stands. Is that unfair to her? You're feeling like that might be unfair to her. It's also not really putting your best foot forward. Okay, back to the drawing board. What little you remember of how such matters are gone about in rural Stirland is of little use, as you doubt Panoramia would recognize the significance of a carved wooden spoon. Your memory of how things are done in the Colleges are equally useless, as romantic fads amongst Apprentices would come and go on a regular basis and would rarely go beyond an individual College. Eventually you settle on following Wolf's lead and track her down in the fields, which is fairly straightforward since she's flaring Ghyran like a signal fire as she draws power from the mountain Waystones. You wait until she's finished the intricate magical ritual she's performing on the freshly-sown field and ask her outright, thankfully managing to do so without stumbling too much over your words, if she would like to share some private unchaperoned time with romantic intent with you. The look she gives you is long and thoughtful, and by the quiver of her lips it's clear she's fighting back a smile or even a laugh, but she eventually says yes so you're able to tell her your idea for the details and flee as soon as she accepts that too. Her acceptance means you only spend most of the rest of the day hiding in the privacy of your dragon chair as you wait for your nervousness and embarrassment to abate. It's so much easier in the books. --- Though it has its downsides, living just a few mountains from the Badlands means that you can usually count on sunny days. On the day of the hike, you set out just as the sun is starting to peek above Karag Zilfin and mist is still hovering over the fields to meet Panoramia early, outside the cottage that the Halflings built for her. One advantage of being a Wizard is never being unsure of what to wear, and she's dressed just as she always is, except with stout Dwarven boots instead of her usual sandals, and she's done her hair up in a plait instead of letting it hang loose like it usually does. For your part, with some reluctance you've left your revolvers at home, but Branulhune is always with you and your staff makes for a good walking stick so you're far from unarmed. "No hat?" you ask as the two of you head out. She shakes her head. "It's almost Summer. I only ever get sunburns in Winter." "Ah. An Arcane Mark?" "Something like that. It runs in the family, being hardy in the summer and very not in the winter. Handy for working the fields, not so much the rest of the time. I'm just glad the Expedition succeeded before it got too far into autumn." You nod. "That's why you holiday through winter." "If you're not going to be productive anyway, might as well enjoy it. The College just about shuts down during winter. Drives some of the new blood spare, at least until they delve deep enough that they start feeling the rhythm too." She prods at your shadow with her staff, which sways to the side to avoid it. "I suppose you wouldn't have anything like that, with Ulgu." "Not so much. It does peak twice a day at dawn and dusk," you say with a wave at the rising sun, "but there's no real low points because there's almost always plenty of shadows and boundaries to be found. I've read theories that the moment between years should be powerful for Ulgu, but there's six different dates for that in the Old World alone." "Prescriptivists," Panoramia says with a snort. "Assume a spherical calendar in a magical vacuum..." Panoramia laughs. It's a nice sound. --- Climbing Karagril would have once been a formidable feat, but to construct the aqueducts to water the fields the Dwarves scouted the best route and carved stairs into the steepest parts of it, turning it into a challenging but enjoyable hike. You're able to keep a decent pace as you've kept yourself in good shape ever since you first picked up a greatsword. Panoramia proves able to match you, which you partially ascribe to being on her feet all day and partially to the benefits of Ghyran, since she only ever seems to need a few moments with her staff buried in soil to find renewed energy. When the slope is gentle enough to allow the two of you to walk abreast you chatter about Karak events and College gossip. The sun has climbed high in the sky by the time you reach the tarn, and the beauty of its silver waters is matched only by how refreshing it is to drink from them after a long walk. The two of you circle the water to find a suitable place to rest, and end up sitting with your backs against a boulder, watching the shimmering water and resting your legs. "So," Panoramia eventually says. "What is it about me that got your attention?" It's a question you'd considered yourself. "You're fun," you say. "You're fun, you keep up, you're not intimidated, and you're a good person. And it's easy and pleasant to spend time with you." You hazard a look sideways at her, and there's a hint of blush to her cheeks. "Well, I'm glad you think so," she says. "I thought you were put out that I managed to see through your Grey Wizard-ness." "I..." You sigh. "It can be useful when I'm working, the reputation and the general aura can save a lot of time. But when I'm not, it can really get in the way of getting to know people. Even some people who are alright with Wizards in general are unnerved by my Order. This," you pause to flick a stone at your shadow, "certainly doesn't help." "Ah," she says, nodding. "I suppose I see what you mean. Though it could always be worse," she leans forward and starts to undo the laces on her boots, "one common one for us is being really uncomfortable with shoes. I can't imagine working around that. I mean, soil is all well and good, but there's all sorts of things that are unpleasant to step on, or in." You consider telling her of some of the worst of the Marks Ulgu has to offer, and decide against it. "My Master lost his beard to one," you say instead. "Now there's just smoke coming out of his chin." She pauses and looks over at you. "That must look so strange." "You'll have a chance to meet him, he'll be at the Duckling Club meeting." "The August Order of the Ducklings," she corrects with a smile. "Was he a good Master?" "Yes," you say automatically, then consider it. "Yes. Often busy, but... well, when my magic first manifested, he was working nearby. When he collected me, I kind of clung onto him. By the time he had wrapped things up and brought me to Altdorf, I'd decided I was going to go into the Grey College and he'd teach me and I'd be able to do all the wonderful things he could do. And once I'd finished my Junior Apprenticeship, he took me on." You smile. "I suppose life would have went very differently for me if a Wizard from a different College had been closer." "Sounds like it must have been nice," Panoramia says, kicking off her now-unlaced shoes and stretching her legs, which you take the opportunity to admire. "I had a Master - still do, I suppose - but it was always Ma that taught me. She didn't want to be the one that broke the link, mother teaching daughter since the dawn of time. I think Teclis broke that link when he revealed we'd been worshipping the Jade Wind instead of an actual deity, but I quickly learned not to get involved in that mess." She sighs, and then starts to unbutton her robes. "Anyway..." You can feel your face heating up as a thousand risque scenarios rush through your head. "Uh, Panoramia, what- what?" She looks at you oddly. "We're up here to swim, aren't we?" Oh. Oh."I only had the hike and the view in mind," you say faintly, only mostly relieved. You should be looking away, but find yourself unable to as she shrugs off her robes. Even though the shift underneath doesn't reveal much more than her robes did, they were still her underthings. "I don't even know how to swim." She smiles at you. "Didn't you learn to swim as a child? In a dam or a dew pond or something?" You shake your head. "Of course not. That's tempting Manhavok." Though you put up a resistance that's half-hearted at most, you can't deny that the water and the company are both tempting, and in the end Panoramia does manage to cajole you out of a few of your outermost layers. The waters of the tarn are quite bracing, fed as it is by meltwater from above and a spring from below, providing a nice counterpoint to the sun now high in the sky. You have to admit that once you start splashing about in the water you quickly forget how exposed you are, though that forgetfulness did not carry over to how relatively exposed Panoramia is. By the time the sun passes its zenith and begins to dip, you've discovered an ability to remain afloat in water and built up quite an appetite for the meal the two of you had carried up - Panoramia had selected the food and you the ale. Though it doesn't have your full attention, the meal is quite excellent, and by the time you've packed away the remains the sun has dried you out enough to redress for the trip back down. All in all, it wasn't quite what you expected, but it was everything you could have hoped for. --- To your surprise, Cython becomes a regular visitor, justifying your decision to build a dragon-sized room with a dragon-sized entrance to accommodate it. In a series of evening meetings it devours your books on the Ancestor Gods, appearing to focus on their mortal lives rather than their worship after they left the material world. "They came from the south," Cython says thoughtfully. "A different origin makes for different archetypes, perhaps." It stretches its wings and yawns, light glinting off the vertices of its teeth. "Perhaps one day I will journey there." "So you theorize a common set of deific archetypes?" you ask curiously. "There are only so many phenomena deserving of cultural primacy," it says. "It stands to reason that there are only so many possible Gods. Perhaps origin is immaterial, and living chiefly underground means that their lives are different enough in substance that they reach different answers to the same questions. The only other subterranean societies are already dominated, so the Dwarves may be unique on this world." "Why does it matter to you? Do dragons have Gods?" "Only if they are very unfortunate," it says with a hissing chuckle. "But those of us that have attuned ourselves to the World-That-Is have the Winds, and mine makes the seeking of truths very satisfying, just as yours leads you to find enjoyment in trickery and deception. A new appetite is a small price to pay for the abilities and insights and joys a Wind affords." "Did you choose your Wind?" "Did you?" Cython replies, and as far as you can tell its tone, it seems genuinely curious. You frown, thinking. "Sort of? I had the opportunity to choose differently, but I didn't." "So it is with us. We could prevent our attunement, but those of us with sense see little point. Our natural state, while grand, is suited for the World-That-Was. As those that have made pets of the water-folk are learning, the World-That-Is punishes those that will not adapt." It turns an eye back to the book it is holding aloft in a grip of magical energy. "A lesson that the Dwarves seem to have learned well, to elevate those who met the new world head-on." "Ah," you say. "Actually, many of them consider it wrong to deviate from the example set by the Ancestor Gods." It turns its eye back to you. "They walked the World-That-Is thousands of years ago, did they not?" "Almost seven thousand." "And their greatness and suitability for worship derives from the ways they taught the Dwarves to adapt to the World-That-Is." "That's one way to put it." "And the lesson the Dwarves take from this is that they should not adapt any further?" "A lot of them, yes," you confirm with a shrug. "Though not those that have resettled here." It snorts, sending a chill wind blowing through the chamber. "Good," it says simply. --- "The Dwarves say you used to live off the coast of Araby," you say conversationally another evening. "A pleasant archipelago," Cython says, scratching at its neck with a massive claw. "Mountains rising from the sea atop a confluence of magical energies. It served admirably for raising eight children over three centuries." "You're a parent?" It nods. "Many times over." "What happened to your mate? If you don't mind me asking." "Singular?" It hisses a laugh. "I had many. Some stayed long enough to teach their child, others left as soon as their part in producing the eggs was complete. Some I tired of and chased off before an egg was created, others were incompatible matches for offspring but proved pleasant companions nevertheless. My islands were very attractive to those attuned to the Winds, and as the rebel water-folk would pass by regularly, tearing apart the fallen beasts that pulled their ships served well as a display of strength and skill. I had my pick of mates for as long as it entertained me." You're probably not going to get a better in than this to satisfy your curiosity. "So these eggs, were you laying them or siring them?" Cython turns to look at you with both eyes, and from what you've been learning of draconic expressions, it looks amused. "Does it matter? I have delved far deeper into Hysh since then. Such distinctions now only exist when I have reason to will it so. I am a being of light and magic, not of flesh and blood." It points at you with a single massive claw. "If you survive long enough, your path will allow you to become something similar. And the blessing of your species is that it will take you much less time than it did me." --- "It's my privilege to introduce Lord Magister Melkoth, Rector of the Grey College, and Magister Regimand Speiseschrank, my former Master." The resident Wizards introduce themselves one by one, automatically falling into the standard practice of going by rank and seniority. If anyone is intimidated by having the Commander of the Grey College's Battle Wizards present, they don't show it. Few last long as Wizards that can't put on a brave front. "First matter is the only piece of unfinished business I was nervous about leaving behind - the Ice Dragon question." "Ice Dragon?" Regimand asks. "It's going by the name of Cython, and it's happy to leave us alone as long as we leave it alone. I'm hoping that in the long run we can talk it into something more mutually defensive, but for the short term, I'm happy with nonaggression and loaning it the occasional book." "As in, a Hysh Emperor Dragon?" Regimand asks. "Handy sort," Johann says, with deliberate casualness. "Wiped out its share of the local foes and then some." "Far from the worst neighbour we've had," Panoramia agrees. "As for other potential problems, the Okral matter seems to be getting no worse than simmering, but the Marienburg situation looks like it'll drag on for the foreseeable if it doesn't come to a head. Seems like they've been funding bandits in the Empire, and Gods help them if they get it into their head to start the same thing around here. The Dwarves don't approve of that sort of thing, and I've got a feeling Ulrikadrin won't either." "The Winter Wolves have started lending their initiates to the riverboats, just for the trip to Barak Varr and back," Hubert reports. "That way the Barak Varr marines can focus elsewhere. They've already had a few clashes, though it could just be the usual lawlessness of the Border Princes." "Only time it's ever peaceful is just after a Waaagh goes through," Melkoth says. "And even then, not for long. Nobody wants to be the last one to emerge from the Vaults and find that all the relatively good land has already been reclaimed." "I'm glad they're working with Barak Varr. The more of a unified front we can present against Marienburg, the more likely it is they'll back down." "Not necessarily," Regimand says. "Marienburg isn't a united front, the Directorate is ten heads of the wealthiest Merchant Houses, four High Priests, and the head of their College. The ten families want to show off to make sure the lesser families don't get any ideas about supplanting them, and the High Priests tend to egg them on so that their own influence grows as the Merchant Houses expend theirs. Even if they don't get anything out of it, they might keep up with their games as part of internal peacocking." "Bloody Marienburg," Max sighs, to general agreement. "Apart from all that, the big thing on the horizon remains Karag Dum. I've been getting a lot of vague yet dire hints but no solid information so I'm going to do my best to be prepared for anything. Might be a good time to brush up on the fundamentals if you're going to be joining me - I understand the Wastes are rather unfriendly to spellcasting." --- With Marienburg's games leading to an explosion of banditry, it's about time the EIC started to develop the ability to defend itself. Bandits are in it for the profit after all, and if ships flying the EIC flag develop a reputation for answering with steel and gunpowder instead of surrender when challenged, their ships should be much more able to deliver their cargo to its destination. While it would be quite nice to lay down keels of Dwarven River Monitors to start utterly dominating the Aver, the expense would be ruinous and every Dwarven shipwright is already spoken for due to Barak Varr's riverine expansion. So instead the Hochlander is sent to work with the existing Boatmen Guild to expand their training practices. There's trouble early on as the boatmen don't want to disrupt the unspoken agreement with river pirates of 'surrender peacefully and everyone goes back to their families', but the Hochlander manages to play on their patriotism by pointing out that the pirates are taking the money of a foreign power to disrupt the Empire's inner workings, of which the boatmen are a fundamental and irreplaceable part. The boatmen are fairly capable of self-defence already, as beastmen, forest goblins, and wild animals don't give an option of surrender, and the normal operation of a vessel requires a number of heavy and sharp implements. So it doesn't take much to hone that natural edge into something fierce with the help of a few ex-River Warden trainers. Supplementing that is a crate of Stirland Repeaters distributed throughout the EIC fleet, as a single Repeater used properly should be enough to give the impression of a staggered volley of fire - enough to dissuade even the most desperate of pirates. The Hochlander also sees to the construction of a pair of scaled-down Wargalleys to act as escorts to the most vulnerable cargos, as the river barges will never not be a sitting target, no matter how well-trained their crew. Even at cost arming the entire crews with Repeaters would be hugely expensive, so they're instead armed with Blutdorf crossbows. They're not exactly Wolfships, but they should serve as an answer to riverine banditry. As you skim through the rest of the paperwork from the EIC, the results are plain to see: even though banditry has expanded significantly over the past few months, the EIC's losses have remained steady where everyone else's have increased significantly. It's not just the Aver that's been targetted, as word from elsewhere in the Empire is that the Stir and the Upper Reik are also seeing upticks in hostile activity. It seems Marienburg has found a way of expressing their displeasure that suits them. There's no corresponding increase in Barak Varr's rivers; you're not sure whether that's a good thing or not. Dwarven displeasure would certainly escalate matters, but might swiftly convince Marienburg to back off. You do, however, have the pleasure of reading that attempts at banditry on the Moot's portion of the Aver had a swift and brutal response, including a written apology to the town of Scheibbs for the Halflings not being able to fish all the corpses out of the river before they bobbed downstream. The Sylvanian campaign remains calm; the two remaining Vampiric holdouts are no longer tearing chunks out of each other, and Roswita seems content to maintain the greatly tightened stranglehold over the towns. Refugees are streaming out of the cordon, all claiming to be opposed to Vampiric rule but more likely unhappy with being on the losing side, and they're currently being resettled in Drakenhof. It shouldn't be long now; either the holdouts will be weakened enough that Roswita can roll right over them, or they'll be desperate enough to give one final battle and be crushed. --- Library Purchases Budget: 300gc, 2 Dwarf Favour. Anything not spent will not accumulate. [ ] [LIBRARY] No purchase. [ ] [LIBRARY] Write-in. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Though only a single date is shown in the text, there would also have had several offscreen dates over the months. - The Cython portion of the update was originally posted here.

Turn 32 - 2485.5 - We'll Fight the Hordes, and Sing and Cry

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [LIBRARY] Dark Lands: Extensive + Esoteric Imperial (200gc), Marauder Tribes: Extensive Imperial + Extensive Dwarven (200gc), Karaz Ankor: Esoteric Dwarven (150gc, 4DF), Enchanting: Esoteric Imperial (50gc, 2CF) [*] [DWARF] Runesmith briefing on Karag Dum (2 gallons AV) [*] [COLLEGE] Aqshy item emulating Dragon Breath (20 Favor). [*] [PURCHASE] Commission a painting of the duckling club together from an artist. "You understand that every word of this is to go no further than yourself," Thorek says gravely. "These are not Guild secrets exactly, so you would not be Grudged, but you would still earn the enmity of the Guild if you spread what I am about to tell you." You nod. "I understand." "Very well." Thorek sighs. "The leaders of the Runesmiths Guild of Karag Dum call themselves 'Runemasters'." You contemplate that as you look at Thorek's grave expression. "That's it?" "'Runelord' is the title Thungni bestowed upon the son that succeeded Him when He departed," he explains patiently. "Those that oppose Karag Dum's Runesmiths say that to declare that insufficient is to say that they have reached heights that one taught by Thungni Himself could not reach." "So it's something of a religious schism." "And a Clan feud, and a Guild dispute. That is the foundation of the conflict, but not the climax of it. In the Runesmith Conclave of 6769, the last that Karag Dum attended, they announced that Chaos was waxing and that all efforts needed to be spent preparing to withstand it. This was taken poorly, seen as an attempt for Karag Dum to increase their status. Karag Dum has always been focused entirely on the threat of Chaos and has always called for more efforts spent to oppose it, so this was seen as their usual rhetoric, only more so." You make the mental conversion to the Imperial Calendar - 2246 - and you're pretty sure you know where this is going. "But it wasn't. They were right." Thorek sighs. "It is easy to see that now. But from what I've been told - and it seems to be true - that century was a tumultuous time in the Old World. High King Alrik had died in battle at the Battle of Black Falls, Bretonnia was tearing itself apart over succession, humans marched on Nehekhara time and time again and agitated the Tomb Kings into a great deal of activity beyond their borders. Worst of all, at the time of the Conclave, Ulthuan's forces were on the march in the Old World. In the face of all that, it seemed very self-serving for Karag Dum to announce that it was Chaos that was the real threat. A great deal was said in hot blood, every word of it recorded for posterity." "What were the Elves doing?" "Pursuing the Beastman demigod Cor-Dum, but that was not known at the time. The Phoenix King Finubar was still new to the throne, and many Dwarves suspected the worst when his forces made landfall in the Old World." "So when the Great War Against Chaos proved Karag Dum right..." "Influential and ambitious Runelords had their words against Karag Dum indelibly recorded. If they had taken the warnings seriously, and fifty years had been spent exerting all effort of the Karaz Ankor to prepare against the coming storm..." Thorek shrugs. "Perhaps the High King would not have fallen. Perhaps Karak Vlag and Karag Dum would not have been lost. Perhaps the Norse Dwarves would not have fallen. Perhaps the Silver Age would not have ended. Anyone that accepted that burden upon their shoulders would have no choice but to shave their head and seek their Doom. But they have not. I did not ask why not, but they answered the unasked question anyway, and what they gave me was not justification, but accusation." You think back to all the dark warnings you've heard about Karag Dum. "Argumentum ad, er, Dawinem. You can't be blamed for ignoring a warning if the messenger could not be trusted." Thorek nods. "In my recent travels, I've heard a lot of accusations levelled at Karag Dum. Unstable. Unreliable. Undwarflike. Spent too long too close to Chaos, closer even than the Fire Dwarves were when they fell. Karak Kadrin was once brother to Karag Dum - the former dedicated to Grimnir the Slayer, the latter to Grimnir the Foe of Chaos - but all but the eldest there now half-believe this new truth." He sighs and scratches at his beard, and for a moment he seems very tired. "I don't know any of this for sure, or I'd already be levelling accusations and tearing the Guild asunder. But what I do know indicates that that's how it stands." --- After a great deal of internal back-and-forth, you've decided to burn most of your accumulated favour with the Colleges by commissioning as mighty an enchantment as you possibly can from the Bright College: an item emulating the spell Breathe Fire, only much more so. Enchantments aren't usually scalable like that, but one notable exception is when asking Aqshy to make fire. Months later you travel to collect it from the Enchanter, Magister Wolfgang Scheunacht, a neatly-dressed and well-groomed young Magister with black hair and a fresh-looking burn stretching from his eyepatch to his neck. "Magister Weber," he says with an easy smile. "Allow me to introduce you to what might be my finest work yet." With hands covered in neat leather gloves, he presents you with a flask covered in red scales with a brass topper. "The flask is imitation dragonskin, from a local curio shop - it's the inner workings that do the magic. Fill it with something flammable, spirits for preference but in a pinch lamp oil or animal fat will do, and leave it over a fire hot enough to melt lead for a day. The scales will turn red when it's ready - they're normally black. To activate, drink the contents in a gulp - it's less than it looks, the inner workings take up much of the volume - and point your face in the direction of whatever it is that you so strongly disapprove of." "Any residual Aqshy?" you ask, turning it over in your hands. "As long as you give it a few minutes before doing any verbal spellcasting, none to speak of. Oh, but do refrain from drinking anything magically-active for at least twelve hours after using it." You look up at him, and the angry red scar marring what would otherwise be a handsome face. "Is that burn from the enchantment?" you ask. "The process of creating it, yes," he says breezily. "It's of no matter, normal hazard of the Wind, and a small price to pay for the opportunities that so much goodwill will afford me." You take it out to a cratered clearing almost entirely free of vegetation near Altdorf that the Colleges own collectively to put it through its paces, brace yourself, hold the arm that has the Seed in it behind your back just in case, and drink. The taste is both painful and confusing, as if your tongue can't decide if it's unbearably spicy or more conventionally boiling but does know it doesn't like it, but it seems to evaporate before it hits your stomach. You stand confused for a moment until a sensation very like an oncoming sneeze starts to build, and you do your best to aim your face as the charred tree stump you'd decided on as a target before you unleash whatever's trying to happen. With a sound like a reverberating bark, Aqshy explodes from your mouth and nostrils, and you're momentarily blinded as the world before you transforms into fire. After you collect yourself, you examine the site of the former stump as best you can as you wipe your streaming eyes and brush pieces of ash from your scorched eyebrows. Everything above the ground and several inches below it was apparently transformed into splinters and sent directly away from you at a substantial speed, and the field beyond is peppered with small, smouldering craters. A crunch underfoot reveals that wood wasn't the only victim, as some of the soil surrounding the stump was apparently vitrified and shattered by the heat and force of the blast. It's certainly effective, but as you blow your nose and consider the soot it leaves in your handkerchief, you think you might have been better served if you had specified something more self-contained. While you're in the Empire, you also make a concession to sentiment by commissioning an artist from the University of Altdorf to travel to the Karak to paint a group portrait of the resident Wizards. Normally you'd think that sort of thing is just tempting fate, but travelling into the Chaos Wastes is tempting fate plenty all on its own, and you'd very much regret not having a keepsake should members of your little Order not make it back. You go back and forth on whether to include Esbern and Seija, and eventually instruct the artist to leave space to add them in later if an opportunity presents itself - after all, the two of them aren't on hand to sit for it in person. --- "The end is in sight," Belegar says wearily. "The gleam of ore at the end of the tunnel." "Our Clans have banded together to keep from giving the Okral any excuse to start trouble," Edda says soothingly. "It's brought them together. I don't want to say 'common enemy', but..." "Common affliction," you say, and Edda smiles and nods. "I think the dragon has the Okral off balance," Kazrik chimes in. "It's one thing for them to be told it's around, it's another for it to fly overhead every so often." "Everything okay on that front?" Belegar asks you. "It's never encountered Dwarves directly before, it's borrowed some reading material to get to know a bit more about you." You figure that's a better way to put it than to let it be known that it's trying to draw direct links between the Ancestor-Gods and the Elven deities. "It's not acting like any dragon I've ever heard stories of," Dreng says, sounding a little put out. "It's a Hysh dragon," you say, to blank looks. Right, Dwarves. "To channel a Wind, a being has to cultivate a mindset that aligns with it. For example, fire dragons channel Aqshy, the Wind of Fire, which makes them impulsive and temperamental. Hysh, the Wind of Light which Cython channels, requires a calm and thoughtful mental state." "And yours?" Kazrik asks curiously. Deception, skulduggery, and plots. "A focus on ambiguities, mystery, and the unexpected," you say instead, and Kazrik nods thoughtfully. "Dreng, any news?" Belegar asks. "Since we now know for sure that Birdmuncha is dead, I've had my Rangers prodding Karak Drazh to get the name of their new Warboss. Apparently they now answer to Warboss Gorfang the Hungry, which according to captured Skaven intelligence," he pauses as he grimaces at the thought, "was the Big Boss in charge of the Red Fang's Underway front before the Battle of the Caldera." "Hopefully the experience has taught him to be wary of the Dwarves," Belegar says, to a chorus of approval. "In six months time, we'll be opening a new chapter in this Karak's history, and I intend it to be one of prosperity and growth." Mandatory Actions: Pick one from each category. Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his metalworking studies. [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. [ ] MAX: Have him train Hubert (optional: specify in what) (NEW) [ ] MAX: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Write a paper: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which. Must be taken with a 'dictate' action. Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Have him continue to teach Adela what he knows of engineering. [ ] JOHANN: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Have him train Hubert (optional: specify in what) (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks [ ] DUCK: Work with Panoramia to try to implement the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. [ ] DUCK: Panoramia's about ready to test for Magister, but she's putting it off because she doesn't have a lot of free time to prepare. Work with her to help make the most of every spare minute. [ ] DUCK: Aid Hubert in his search for a Familiar. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Gretel and the Besiegers for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Adela and some human siege weapons and operators for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Recruit all the remaining ducklings for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Panoramia and a team of crack Fieldwardens for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Esbern and Seija and their compatriots of the Knights of Taal's Fury. [ ] DUCK: Each of your three ducklings can fight in melee. Spar with them, and teach them what you can. [ ] DUCK: Study an artefact with one of the Journeymen: specify who and which. The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 175 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Expansion along the Aver EIC Handler: The Hochlander [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. Will remove this section from future turns and regain the half-turn invested in it. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in your fief. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Julia to find out if she's interested in being poached or passing on information. [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Improve the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Sell some of the Grand Urbaz Bank coins to collectors and museums on King Belegar's behalf. [ ] EIC: Integrate the Gong Farmers and the Niter Factory into the EIC, and expand production. [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. Personal Actions: you have four actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. Current overwork status: [ ] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. Current Task: Karag Dum Expedition preparations [ ] Seek out merchants who have travelled the Skull Road to learn what they know of it. [ ] Trawl around the bars and brothels of Tilea, looking to talk to the actual mercenaries that have walked either the Skull Road, or the Great Steppes. [ ] Attempt to recruit assistance for the Karag Dum Expedition. (specify the individual, mercenary group, cult, College, or other; two choices per AP spent) [ ] With the help of a gyrocarriage, personally scout part of the route (specify: High Pass, Road of Skulls, Western Great Steppes, Karag Dum vicinity) [ ] Attempt to learn the Greenskin tongue to communicate with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Attempt to learn Kurgan to communicate with the Kurgan of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Kurgan of the Steppes. Spoiler: Qrech Qrech [ ] Despite him considering it treasonous, push Qrech to share the Moulder dialect of Queekish. [ ] Despite him considering it blasphemous, push Qrech to share High Queekish. Qrech Gambits (can be taken for free alongside a Qrech option): [ ] Convince Qrech that you seek an arrangement with Clan Moulder, and that you will release him as an ambassador for that arrangement once you are satisfied he'll cooperate. [ ] Convince Qrech that the Under-Empire has no way of knowing he's even alive, and that he should prioritize the comfort with which he will live the rest of his life. [ ] Convince Qrech you're ambitious and loyal only to yourself, and you're willing to repay his cooperation in ways that will benefit the Under-Empire. [ ] Other (write in) Self-Improvement: [ ] Ask an acquaintance to train you in a skill: specify who and what. [ ] Attempt to learn a spell from scrolls (specify which, will be harder than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Hire a trainer to come to Eight Peaks and teach you: specify what. (costs favours for Dwarf or College trainers, money for human ones) [ ] Travel to the Grey College and attend lessons there. (1 College Favour per class; 100gc can be paid instead for non-magical classes) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Gain enough control of your unruly shadow to still it temporarily. [ ] Gain enough control of your attraction to smoke and gases to have it collect away from your face. [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Try to create them. [ ] Have one of Prince Gotri's pilots teach you to fly a gyrocopter. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] Dictate papers: select which two, must be taken with Max's 'receive dictation'. [ ] Investigate the possibility of using one Wind to directly manipulate another. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. [ ] Try to establish a relationship with the Cult of Verena, with the intent of offering them access to your rarer tomes in exchange for copies of some of their own. Aethyric Vitae (12 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item with a Fiendishly Complex or easier spell (specify what and which) [ ] Attempt to enchant an object to translate Windsight into a visual image. [ ] Attempt to deepen your skill with Enchantment (will be more difficult than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Continue to work on your 'Fog Path' spell (NEW-ish) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff from mundane materials. [ ] Turn a staff from the horn of a Storm Dragon. Karag Nar Penthouse: each turn, you get ONE free choice in this category. Additional selections cost actions. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have a tower built atop Karag Nar: -100gc for 1 room, bonus to room's purpose. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have additional rooms excavated underneath your Penthouse: -150gc for 6 rooms. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add security measures to your Penthouse to prevent forcible entry. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have firing platforms built around the Penthouse so that it can be defended from flyers or climbers without granting access to it. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add preservation Runes to your library: -4 Dwarf Favour, can be paid for with book budget DF for next two purchase periods. [ ] PENTHOUSE: No additional construction. Setting up rooms for specific purposes will have to wait until new rooms are constructed or excavated. Only one construction or excavation can take place at a time, but you can do one of each. Building downwards will increase by 1 each time; second set of excavated rooms will be 3 rooms, third will be 4, and so on. Building upwards can be added upon; towers can be added on to or additional towers can be built. The distinction between the two is entirely cosmetic. Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in the Sylvanian campaign (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Marienburg affair (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Black Waters project (specify how) Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting with a fellow councillor's task: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Warp Lightning observations - shared with Adela (FADING) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition. (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual. (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae. (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Next turn, when the Expedition begins, will have two less AP than normal, with an option to spend a third AP to be with the Expedition from Praag instead of meeting it at High Pass, which is where everyone else (Wizard volunteers, Winter Wolves, Asarnil, et cetera) will be joining it. There will be no serenity action, everything else as per normal. - For reference, here's the sustainable speeds for various possible recruits for the Expedition: Spoiler: Travel speeds Steam-Wagon: 3-6 MPH, 12-16 hours/day. Estimated 50-100 miles/day. Human: 3 MPH for 6 hours/day. 18 miles/day. Dwarf: 3 MPH for 10 hours/day. 30 miles/day. Heavy Cavalry: 4 MPH for 8 hours/day. 32 miles/day. Light Cavalry: 5 MPH for 8 hours/day. 40 miles/day. Ogres: 4 MPH for 12 hours/day. 48 miles/day. Steppe Horse: 6 MPH for 10 hours/day. 60 miles/day. Cold Ones: 10 MPH for 6 hours/day. 60 miles/day. Steppe Horse w/ remounts: 8 MPH for 10 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Bretonnian Horse: 8 MPH for 10 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Demigryphs: 10 MPH for 8 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Winter Wolves: 5 MPH for 16 hours/day. 80 miles/day. Shadowsteed: 15 MPH for 6 hours/day. 90 miles/day. Mathilde's Shadowsteed: 25 MPH for 10 hours/day. 250 miles/day. Bretonnian horses have Magical Bullshit Genes from crossbreeding with Elven horses. Demigryphs and Winter Wolves are slightly cranked up numbers from cougars and wolves. Steppe horses are based on what the Mongols achieved.

Turn 32 Results - 2485.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan Perfectly Balanced -[*] Contains 1 Overwork action -[*] With the help of a gyrocarriage, personally scout part of the route: Western Great Steppes -[*] Attempt to recruit assistance for the Karag Dum Expedition: Karak Azul Runesmiths + Light Wizards -[*] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Try to create them. -[*] Enchant an item with a Fiendishly Complex or easier spell: Aethyric Armour Robes --[*] Goal: Incorporating mastery and persistent effect --[*] Using powerstone(s) + helldrake scales + We silk as available/necessary -[*] Continue to work on your 'Fog Path' spell. --[*] Coin: The Gambler -[*] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. -[*] JOHANN: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. -[*] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Esbern and Seija and their compatriots of the Knights of Taal's Fury. -[*] EIC: Integrate the Gong Farmers and the Niter Factory into the EIC, and expand production. -[*] PENTHOUSE: Have a tower built atop Karag Nar: -100gc for 1 room, bonus to room's purpose. -[*] SERENITY: Write a paper: Warp Lightning observations - shared with Adela (FADING) Having finally been told the details of the rift between Karag Dum and the rest of the Dwarves, you're in a position to weigh the decision of whether to seek Runesmith recruits for it. On the one hand, there's none better at shielding against the machinations of Chaos, into whose land you will be venturing. On the other, as Thorek said himself, it's a situation that could have massive repercussions on the wider Karaz Ankor. In the end, pragmatism wins out. If there are political aftershocks, then so be it. It's not your responsibility to shield Runelords from the consequences of their own decisions. [Rolling...] Thorek hears you out, and spends some time considering it. "If you had asked me a decade earlier, I would have said yes," he eventually says. "Karak Azul as it was then could have lasted without me, should the worst happen. But now, my priority needs to be maintaining my Karak's renewed connection with the Karaz Ankor. Should your Karak come under threat, my Anvil and my Apprentices must stand ready to defend them, and we cannot do that if we are journeying in the frozen north, or never return from doing so." You open your mouth to thank him for his time anyway, but stop yourself as you notice he's still lost in thought. "However," he eventually says, "I can contribute in some small part to the preparations. I shall send my most promising Apprentices to assist Karak Kadrin in outfitting the Expedition." "I thank you, Runelord Thorek, as does King Belegar and the Expedition," you respond formally. He nods. "May the Ancestor Gods watch over your path. And my advice to you: enjoy your youth. A time will come when the burden of responsibility will outweigh the pull of adventure." You consider pointing out that you're thirty-five, but decide against it; by Dwarven standards that's barely an adult. You instead thank him once more, and move on to your next recruitment candidate. --- Ah, the Light College, natural conceptual rivals to the Grey. Perhaps time spent with Cython was rubbing off on you, or perhaps you've no choice but to acknowledge there's no better Wind for directly combating Chaos, but you were eventually forced to acknowledge that securing their assistance was one of the best ways for you to contribute to the Expedition. As much as the Light Order enjoys their privacy - or at least, enjoys denying entrance to any outsiders - sending a letter in advance saying you are acting with the full authority of King Belegar Ironhammer, King Ungrim Ironfist, and the delegated authority of King Thangrim Firebeard is enough to open even their doors. An Apprentice waits by the appropriate street corner to let you in without having to go through their bizarre entrance ritual, and reality unfolds before your very eyes as the buildings and streets are pushed back to make way for the Light College: a massive pyramid of pure-white marble so filled with ethereal light as to be transparent. And that you didn't immediately mentally question that light made marble transparent, and that you mentally described the light as 'ethereal' rather than 'garish', rather suggests that your initial reaction of awe was not entirely natural. You scowl up at the towering display of magical puissance- No. You refuse. You glare upwards at the overgrown caltrop and dare it to insert any more purple prose into your internal monologue. "Um, Magister? Sorry, Loremaster?" says a voice, and you turn to the Apprentice who's awkwardly shuffling from foot to foot. "The entrance is this way," they say, as if the massive building-sized opening that is the only interruption in the otherwise smooth sides could be overlooked. You give the exterior a final glare before following the Apprentice inside. --- Magister Patriarch Alric is the kind of person best described with 'was' instead. He was a great hero, who fought in countless battles for the Empire. He was a widely-respected Supreme Patriarch. He was, indeed, the Savior of Apesto. But he also was the one in power on the Night of a Thousand Arcane Duels in 2415, when High Luminary Horx ambushed him, sealed him in crystal, and went on to unleash a Storm of Magic upon Altdorf that led to fifteen years of the Colleges being outlawed and besieged. He stepped down from the position of Supreme Patriarch in the immediate aftermath, and that should have been the end of his chapter in history. But he kept going, apparently on sheer inertia, and apparently had sufficiently recovered from his shame to retake the position of Supreme Patriarch in 2439, and then lost it in '47, then regained it again for '55-'62. In recent years he's been alternating leadership of the Light College with part-time Magister Matriarch Mira, and from the outside it's not clear if it's an arrangement to take pressure off failing faculties or if leadership is being yanked back and forth like two dogs with a bone, but either way it bodes poorly for the Light College. The man you are introduced to is unbent by age and rises to greet you when you enter, and glows with a luminescence that matches the walls around him to an extent that you have to squint to tell where the building ends and the Wizard begins. "Ah yes," he says, in a quiet voice that nonetheless seems to echo through the room. "The Dwarf-Friend of the Greys. I have heard good things of you in recent years." "Thank you, Magister Patriarch," you say respectfully. Though not too respectfully, as you used the standard title instead of whatever it is they call the position within the Light Order. "Karag Dum, the letter said," he says thoughtfully, his long, boney fingers drumming out a melody on the arm of his chair. "It was lost when we were founded. Perhaps something must be lost for something to be gained. Still, no reason not to try. Are you going yourself?" "I am, as are several of my colleagues." [Rolling...] "Mmm. Much as I would like to join such an adventure, I fear the Light College requires my leadership too much. Instead, I will send with you the greatest assistance it is in my power to give: my former apprentice, Magister Egrimm van Horstmann. He has been a stalwart assistant of mine in internal matters, but I am sure I could spare him for a few months." "My thanks, Magister Patriarch." A single Magister. Well, better than nothing. --- Some knights venture across the Old World and even beyond, making them difficult to get ahold of. Not so with the Knights of Taal's Fury, who believe they must return to the Talabec to renew their vows to King Taal and refresh his blessing upon them, and since they're returning anyway they might as well do so in time to winter in their nice comfortable chapterhouse, right? You greet Esbern and Seija at the entrance with hugs, and Wolf greets their demigryphs with a series of barks which they answer with squawks. Leaving the three beasts to frolic together and probably find something in the forest to kill and eat, the three of you make your way inside the peak as you explain the details of the expedition to your fellow Magisters. The Grand Hall of the not-Chapterhouse is made of carved stone, with the walls covered in wall hangings that can be rolled up and securely stored when the Knights are abroad. Each is dedicated to a victory of either Taal or the Knights, and from the few moments you get to glance around you recognize depictions of greenskins, Skaven, Marauders and Ogres, but more frequent than the rest combined are Beastmen. Of all of the forms of Chaos, King Taal hates Beastmen most of all, as they are His beings twisted into unnatural forms and bent to serve the Chaos Gods. The room is filled with a haphazard assortment of sturdy wooden chairs and tables with no indication of who should sit where. You know not to be too taken in by this - the Knights still believe in hierarchy, they just believe it should be unadorned, with all men knowing where they stand without needing ornamentation to remind them. "Magister Weber!" calls out a booming and faintly familiar voice, and you bow in greeting to Grand Master Sigwald Kriegersen, who's warming his hands by the fire. You never spent much time with him during the Expedition, but you did share the Council of War with him. "Thank you for receiving me, Grand Master," you say as you approach him. "A brother-in-arms - or sister-in-arms, for that matter - needs not stand on ceremony with us. Look." He points across the room at one of the wall hangings, and after a moment of looking at the depiction of Knights striking down greenskins, you recognize the silhouette of the Citadel in the background and what the ring of mountains around it must represent. "Most glory fades, but the glory of Eight Peaks is only growing as it proves it's not going anywhere. And I hear you might have another opportunity, and one that would be a thumb in the eye of the Great Enemy besides." "Karak Kadrin seeks to re-establish contact with the Dwarven stronghold of Karag Dum in the Great Steppes, which was lost during the Great War Against Chaos," you say, taking a seat. "They've built a convoy of cannon-armed land-ships that will be setting out from Praag this coming spring. They're formidable, but the pace they'll set means that conventional cavalry would be left in the dust." "So you came to us. Who's involved?" he asks thoughtfully. You smile at the question. If the preparations for the Karak Eight Peaks Expedition taught you anything, it's that success breeds success. Nobody wants to be the first one to volunteer, but nobody wants to be last, either. "Karak Kadrin's supplying the Dwarves and gold, Zhufbar the expertise, Karak Azul the Runes, and Karak Eight Peaks is supplying Wizards - we have four Magisters confirmed so far - as well as having reached an accord with the Ice Witches of Kislev to guarantee that High Pass will be open. A substantial portion of the Winter Wolves have also joined, and the Expedition has reached an accord with the mercenary Asarnil." "Asarnil," he says, frowning. "Worked alongside him in Kislev. Thought he was heading west." "I managed to lure him away from Marienburg." "Marienburg? Glad to hear it. Would be a costly day if we had to take that pair down." He scratches his beard thoughtfully, and looks to the two other Wizards standing nearby. "Esbern, Seija, your thoughts?" "We'll be going with the Magister," Esbern says firmly, and Seija nods. [Rolling...] Kriegersen grunts and nods. "Says all that needs saying. We've got commitments here in the Empire for this coming spring, but none that require our full numbers. I'll peel off a pair of Wings and send them north. Praag, you said?" You nod. "Right then. Let's wrest this mountain from the grip of the Ruinous Powers." --- Though the exact size varies depending where one draws the line between steppe and Chaos Wastes, the Great Steppes are undeniably immense, at least four times the size of the entire Old World. The Kurgan-populated Western Steppes, sandwiched as it is between the Chaos Wastes and the Mountains of Mourn, is the smallest section, about half the size of the Central Steppes and a quarter of the Eastern Steppes. That still leaves an area the size of the entire Empire. Thankfully, you aren't concerned with the entirety of the Western Steppes; your only concern is the narrow corridor between the Skull Road and Karag Dum. All you have to work off is a Dwarven map that was out of date even before Karag Dum fall, annotated by Borek's only slightly more recent recollections. Even for someone well acclimated to gyrocopter travel, the trip from Karak Eight Peaks to northern Kislev is quite a marathon, and you have only the drone of the engines and your books for company. That voyage takes you through two Karaks and two cities, as even a gyrocarriage modified for endurance cannot cross the Old World in a single trip and must stop every so often for fuel and maintenance. Your journey finally terminates on a narrow plateau high above High Pass which currently serves as a supply depot. The Karak Kadrin Rangers that are currently calling it home are glad for company and pass on everything they've seen, which amounts to the occasional heavily-armed caravan, and less and less of those as the year wears on and winter approaches. You fill a pack and the gyrocarriage with food, ale and other supplies, and set off even further. Not east, as you've no desire to fly over Chaos Dwarf airspace. Instead you go north, over the first leg of Borek's original intended route - across the ice of the Frozen Sea - and then flying directly east towards the steppes. Though it avoids enemy territory it has its own dangers, as if one goes too far north the laws of physics upon which Dwarven machines depend become less reliable, which would be annoying for steam-wagons but disastrous for gyrocopters. After setting you off in the seemingly endless grasslands beyond, the pilot sets off once more to identify a suitable mountaintop to set up a forward base and watch for your signal from. Your first priority is simply to get a feel for the terrain. The terrain remains identical day after day, a gently rolling series of hills covered in hardy grass, with occasional herds of deer and goats peppering the terrain. The skies are almost always empty of clouds, the only interruptions in the blue being birds of prey hovering far overhead. The wind is almost always strong and almost always blowing from north to south, and if you don't keep an eye on your course you find yourself veering southwards to go along with it. And though to mundane eyes the terrain might grow tiresome, to Magesight the sky blazes with every colour. This far north the Winds constantly blast from the Chaos Wastes in vast bands of magical energy, and on hilltops they're so close you could reach out and touch them. You can see how spellcasting would be fraught out here - there's no ambient energy to draw from, you have to reach upwards and grasp one of the magical rivers overhead and do the best you can to control the flood of magical energy. From this sojourn, you can reasonably conclude that the terrain itself won't be much trouble to the steam-wagons, as slopes steep enough to trouble them are rare and easily circled around. The biggest problem is likely to be navigation, as once the mountains on the edge of the steppe disappear into the distance, the only way to tell direction is the sun and the only way to tell distance travelled is the passage of time. It's not a novel problem, however - it's one that sailors have to wrestle with every day. You're sure that Barak Varr will be able to supply some solutions, and make a mental note to pass on the advice to Borek. That said, while the terrain might be easily manageable, you doubt the inhabitants would be. You're not entirely sure how far to go in investigating them. Scouting from overhead might give you a general idea of how many there are in the area, but any hard information on a nomadic people expires very rapidly. Should you be content with what you've uncovered so far and what a few flights overhead might reveal, or should you seek to make very cautious contact with the locals? They're said to serve Chaos, but so did the Kislevites once. You don't speak Kurgan, but as it did with Qrech, Khazalid might prove a common tongue. After all, the Kurgan are said to deal with the Chaos Dwarves for weapons and armour. [ ] Make contact with the Kurgan [ ] Do not make contact with the Kurgan - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Canonical events involving Egrimm van Horstmann have yet to pass, and therefore may or may not lie in the future of this version of history. - I've read that there is a novel telling the full story of Alric and Egrimm van Horstmann. I have not read it, and what I do know indicates it is incompatible with what has already occurred in this quest, so it should be disregarded for quest purposes.

A Meeting in the Western Steppes

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Make contact with the Kurgan In the end, you decide that there's no reason not to try to make contact with the locals. You figure that any tribes this close to the Chaos Wastes that react violently to wandering magical strangers won't have survived long, and you have the mobility to avoid any unfavourable meetings. The people of the Steppe are rightfully known for their prowess in the saddle, but no horse of flesh and blood can match one of shadow. The process of making contact is not difficult. You simply ride until you spot a large herd of sheep and halt your Shadowsteed atop a hill overlooking them. Despite how empty the plains around you look, no domesticated herd is ownerless in the Steppes, and somewhere nearby a watcher has a puzzle on their hands. You're clearly not attempting to steal any of the herd, but neither are you moving along, and your horse and your dress makes you impossible to place in any mundane category. The only sensible conclusion is to send word back to the tribe and make it someone else's problem. As the time passes, you refresh your memory with one of the books on the Kurgan you'd brought with you while waiting for them to present themselves. Eventually, riding in clear view and at a speed that gives you plenty of time to notice and react to them, a party of Kurgan are approaching, all visibly carrying bows that are currently unnocked. 'We don't offer violence, but it is an option' is a solid foundation to build first contact on. [Rolling...] At the head of the band is a man who looks slightly younger than yourself, dressed in leathers and wearing multiple necklaces of fangs and claws. Your books say there's no one mark of a Shaman as cultural practices vary widely across the Steppes, but that he thrums with the power of Ghur seems a solid indication to you. The band pauses at the next hilltop to consider you and exchange words, and then the Shaman approaches further. You tuck your book away and grip your staff in the same way that the watchers are gripping their bows - not quite ready to use, but not far from it either. He calls out what you hope to be a greeting in a language that sounds very slightly like Kislevarin, then again in another that makes the Winds ripple unpleasantly, and then a third time, in guttural almost-Khazalid, "blood or tea, stranger?" That he speaks the Chaos Dwarf equivalent of Khazalid makes things a great deal easier. "Today, tea," is your response, and one of only two acceptable answers. Your books tell you that the Cathayan drink is even more popular amongst the Kurgan than it is in Altdorf cafes, and is a central part of the culture of the tribes who live close enough to the trade road to steal or buy it. You carefully dismount as the Shaman does the same; the Shaman makes a show of removing the knife from his hip and placing it in a saddlebag. You normally carry no knife as you can summon them as needed, but you'd brought one for this purpose, and leave yours next to your horse as the Shadowsteed can only carry a rider, not cargo. He approaches cautiously, and holds out a flask to you; you wet your finger in it and flick some northwards before taking a sip and suppressing your grimace. If tea would be inconvenient, a guest will be offered alcohol, and for most of the Kurgan, the alcohol is fermented horse milk. Your host seems to relax slightly. "I am a Shaman of the Dolgan Tribes. I serve the Untamed of the Eight." "I am a Shaman of the Mountain Ring Clans. I serve the Shadowed of the Eight. I travel from the west and will travel to the south." He nods. "You are far from the salt-water," he observes. "Your business must be important for you to travel so far." You nod but don't elaborate, happy to leave him with the misconception that you're from Norsca. "Can you tell me of the neighbouring tribes?" He nods. "You came through the mountains? The proud Kul are to the north of the mountains, their claim stretches all the way to the Blessed Lands. Dolgan land stretches to the Tea Road. Between Tea Road and Dwarf-Land is the Iron Wolf Tribes, who serve an Old One. East are the Kvelliges and Khazags, and north are the Yusak, who have lost favour with the Four and seek lands further from them." You nod thoughtfully, checking that against your mental map of the Eastern Steppes. It sounds like the Expedition's route will go through Dolgan and then Yusak territory, and that Karag Dum itself would be about at the border between Yusak and Kul, and the Yusak are currently vulnerable, while the Kul... you don't know their current state, but about 180 years ago their leader Asavar united the Kurgans and was anointed as Everchosen, sparking the Great War Against Chaos. Your books had some information on the Dolgans, describing a people on the edge between civilization and barbarism to the extent that some served Kislev as mercenaries - but that described a people between Kislev and Norsca, far from here. How similar are these Dolgans to the ones your books spoke of? The information this Shaman has given you out of simple courtesy is already valuable, but if you could reach an accord with his people, even greater things could come of it. An agreement to allow passage would make safe what could otherwise be a very dangerous leg of the journey. If they would sell livestock to the steam-wagons, supply concerns would vanish. If they would take advantage of the weakened Yusak at the right time, the entire passage from the Dark Lands to the Chaos Wastes would be laid open, and it's likely all that would take is the Dolgan being prepared to take advantage of the Yusak being distracted by the steam-wagons and the many knights passing through their territory. Or if they could even be talked into selling military aid to the Expedition... Dolgan mercenaries would be able to live off the land and wouldn't need transporting all the way from Praag, they'd be in their element for any conflict that might need them, and they might help in dealing with any other Kurgan that might present an obstacle to the Expedition. Or on the other hand, it might be best to leave well enough alone. Any deal would likely involve precious metals changing hands, and paying the servants of Chaos is unlikely to sit well with many - though you should be able to keep the details concealed from most. And though you'd do your best to not give away details that would leave the Expedition vulnerable to betrayal, could any deception serve if the Plotter might be involved? Then again, if the Plotter's attention does turn this way, it's very possible that no amount of secrecy would serve... If an accord is to be reached, it should be now. The Dolgans are more likely to be amenable to a deal now than when they have giant metal behemoths on wheels show up on their lands. You're not sure whether they'd see the steam-wagons as as a threat, as prey, or as loot, but they'd probably not see them as a potential trade partner. [ ] Only seek passage for the Expedition [ ] Seek passage and supplies for the Expedition [ ] Seek passage, supplies, and for the Dolgan to attack the Yusak [ ] Seek passage, supplies, and to purchase the service of Dolgan mercenaries [ ] Do not seek any accord with the Dolgans [ ] Seek to make contact with the Yusak instead [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - If Mathilde seeks to make contact with the Yusak, she can't safely fly into Yusak territory, so would have to ride. This means the Dolgan would know she went out of her way to speak to the Yusak. Spoiler: Updated Map This represents Mathilde's estimation instead of being necessarily accurate. For reference, these six territories make up an area about half the size of the Empire.

Turn 32 Results - 2485.5 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [X] Seek passage and supplies for the Expedition You look at the Shaman, weighing him up. "My Clan," you eventually say, "will be travelling through here on a pilgrimage to the Blessed Lands, north of what you say is Yusak territory. We do not wish to expend our strength before we arrive. We would be willing to pay for safe passage through Dolgan land and for cattle to feed us on our journey, and then again as we return, in silver or gold or amber." The Shaman nods. "It is wise to not seek conflict with the Kurgan on the steppe, just as we would not seek conflict with the Norscan on the waves. How many mouths have you to feed?" "Eight hundred, some hungrier than others due to their form." He looks curious. "You travel with your Blessed? That will be a sight to see. Remain here." The Shaman remounts his horse and rides back to the other Dolgans, hopefully only to confer on a reasonable price. You do your best to suppress any signs of nerves as he returns back. "Silver," he says as he dismounts once more. "It spends easiest." He names a price for passage that would be challenging for a Norscan clan but trivial for a Dwarven Karak, as well as a set of prices for livestock that seem, if your mental conversion is correct, no dearer than an Averland stockyard. You nod thoughtfully. "I will take this price back to my Clan," you say. "We will arrive in the second half of the coming spring, carrying both steel and silver." The Shaman nods, not at all taken aback by the warning. "May the Gods find your efforts entertaining." --- The way Kragg told you of the Rune of the Unknown and the way you've been using it so far is that it means you don't need a scabbard, freeing up space on your back for your newly-turned staff. The only other utility it was designed for was that it would prevent you from being disarmed. However, there are many more possibilities to the Rune than that. A great deal of the sword training you have undertaken is focused on bypassing defences and recovering your guard after a swing, both of which are difficult when swinging what amounts to a large and heavy piece of metal around. Both of which could become much less so if you learn how to apply the Rune of the Unknown properly. Your early experiments with the Rune proved that all momentum that Branulhune possesses is lost (or possibly harnessed) when the Rune is activated, even if it's just 'flickered' for an instant. This should allow for more rapid changes in direction, especially since Kragg's signature Rune ensures that the blade always hits with sufficient force, making preserving momentum less important. [Developing the momentum dump: Martial, 17+23=40.] It turns out to be significantly easier said than done. You've spent a not inconsiderable fraction of your life learning, honing, and retaining techniques built on certain assumptions about physics and biology. Being able to make most of the momentum of a swing vanish with your blade undermines every one of those assumptions and you're forced to start from the very basics, running yourself through the basic drills and forms and forcing yourself to pay attention to what had become second nature. Something as simple as a pattern of alternating cuts uses a figure-eight pattern to let the momentum from one swing carry over to the next, which is much more efficient than using muscle force to negate that momentum and then start it afresh from a new direction, but is less efficient than vanishing the blade at the most downward point and having it reappear in your hands when they're in position to begin the next swing. Complicating matters further is the jerk of summoning an unmoving sword into moving hands, which takes a lot of getting used to. In the end it takes you an entire month of self-study and adaptation to rebuild your sword style to incorporate this new technique, leaving no time to even scratch the surface of the other possibilities. [Branarhune aspect developed: momentum dump. Remaining aspects: guard bypass, quick-draw, hand switching.] --- It's been almost eight years since you constructed the enchantment in your robes, but even though said enchantment has prevented most of the wear and tear that clothing would typically see after that much daily use, it's still come time for you to replace it. Since the time you made it you've become a better Wizard, a better Enchanter, and your knowledge of the spell Aethyric Armour specifically has evolved into an effect that shields your muscles from fatigue even as it shields your skin from blades. Unfortunately the local spider-silk industry is still mired in technical difficulties, so with the Expedition rapidly approaching and filled with the perverse certainty that every one of those technical difficulties will evaporate as soon as you complete your new robes, you settle for wool. Though you are quite pleased that you managed to get your hands on a bolt of naturally silver-grey wool, a rarity in this modern age of animal husbandry that has lead to pure-white sheep becoming the norm. You spend some time consider the Helldrake scales that have been gathering dust ever since you acquired them on impulse in Barak Varr. The only mention of them you can find in your library is in the books on dragons, and even there more ink is spent on speculation on the nature of their relation to 'true' dragons than on their properties or inclinations. Still, the few paragraphs reveal to you that they're known primarily for being bred by the Elves of Naggaroth for war, and for such unbridled ferocity that their handlers are often unable to prevent them from attacking each other in the heat of battle. That gives you something to work with. Scales are, of course, a good fit for a component in defensive enchantment, but a nature of unflagging aggression is something you might be able to tap into for tirelessness. [Drawing board: Learning, 10+28+5(Library: Enchantment)=43.] That's the theory, anyway. You've come a long way since your first clumsy attempts to bind magic into permanent enchantment, and part of that is a healthy respect for planning ahead. The health of that respect begins to suffer quite a bit as every thaumaturgic equation runs right into a brick wall, as you try to put your instincts into numbers and run into mathematical insistence that what you're trying to do is impossible. Days evaporate in a blur of numbers and symbols and stacks of reference materials until you finally reach your limit and shove the stacks over in frustration. Gentle shoves, of course, and onto rugs. Even if they are being obstinate, those books are far from cheap. It isn't necessarily hubristic to bypass the preparations, you tell yourself. Putting magic to paper is a much less developed art than putting magic into reality. Every Magister of the Colleges is capable of a number of things that have no theoretical underpinnings proving them possible. There comes a time when a Wizard simply must put aside the books, start throwing magic around, and see what happens. [In the workshop: 74+28+20(Room of Dawn and Dusk)+10(Enchanter)+5(Library: Enchantment)=137.] [Integrating power stone: 48+28+20(Room of Utter Neutrality)+10(Enchanter)+2(Library: Power Stones)=108.] [Integrating scales: 10+28+20(Room of Utter Neutrality)+10(Enchanter)+4(Library: Dragons, halved)=72.] Success, it is said, requires no explanation. It may not be required but an explanation would be nice, you think to yourself as you're torn between pride and frustration that you couldn't even begin to put to paper why those painstaking equations were proven so thoroughly wrong by the end results. Guided by instinct and Ulgu, you've managed to rather literally weave your unique form of Aethyric Armour into your robes, anchored by the Helldrake scales you've turned into pauldrons and powered by the pearl of Crystal Mist, taking the appearance of a jewelled brooch though it's quite firmly fastened in place. Truth be told, you're not entirely happy with the individual elements; the Crystal Mist seems to be reasonably integrated as a power source but its full potential as a lodestone of altered reality has a lot more to offer, and the scales are about as well-utilized as an atlas being used to pin down one corner of a map. But the overall effect is much greater than the sum of its parts: any mundane blade would shatter long before it could mar the weave of the robe, and a tap of the brooch extends the effect around your full body while filling your muscles with vigour. The length it lasts is frustratingly inconsistent, seeming to vary based on time of day, the level of light around you, and another variable you suspect to be the phase of the moon, but even under the worst of conditions it lasts fifteen minutes - about five times the duration of the spell cast conventionally. And you're quite pleased with the imposing touch the scales add to your silhouette. --- You return once more to your many chalkboards, and spend a day carefully copying everything down into notebooks before erasing the notes that lead to the eleven symbols you've reduced Skywalk to. You've got the most basic component of your 'Fog Path' spell completed, but there's more to a sword than just the blade. Even in this energy-efficient form it would take an unfeasible amount of power to create an entire surface for prolonged periods out of this spell, so you don't just need a mechanism to deploy it over and over, you need a way to identify where it must be deployed. [Identifying targets: Learning, 34+28+5(Library: Ulgu)+20(Coin)=87.] You spend a great deal of time wrestling with a single question: can Ulgu itself recognize the difference between surfaces? It could tell a well-illuminated surface from a dim one, sure, but determining material properties is much more in the realm of Chamon, and determining properties of soil specifically is Ghyran. Rock and soil have no inherent properties that would resonate with Ulgu enough to use the Wind itself as the means of identifying where the spell is needed. And that's the result you're stuck on until you break the question down a step further. Inspired, perhaps, by Panoramia's chatter about the many different components you'd previously lumped under a collective label of 'dirt', you realize that Ulgu can't tell whether a surface is stable, but it can tell whether a surface is uniform. The caster will still need to determine whether the surface itself is suitable for passage, but if pointed at a suitable surface, it can identify what isn't entirely of that surface. And by that mechanism, it can identify the trouble spots. Mud? Soil interrupted by water. Pothole? Stone interrupted by gravel. Ditch? Grass interrupted by air. Even thin ice - though Gods forbid the Expedition ever has to travel over ice - could be identified by Ulgu recognizing that the ice is interrupted, just under the surface, by water or air. And once identified, the nature of those interruptions - being neither one thing nor the other - means they can also act as anchor points for the overarching spell, from which the individual iterations of Skywalk can sprout. [Implementing identifier: 94+28+5(Library: Ulgu)+20(Coin)=147.] Days turn to weeks as you painstakingly construct this identification framework and make sure it stands up to any imaginable scenario. You visit Gotri and ask him and his Engineers of every obstacle they've ever encountered in getting a siege weapon from point A to point B. You visit Kragg and Thorek and ask if they've ever encountered any particularly difficult obstructions when it comes to getting their Anvils to commanding positions. Francesco contributes stories of wagon break-downs, Oswald his father's adventures with Steam Tanks, Soizic every hazard she has ever encountered or heard of that could lame a horse. At each stage you make tweaks to the design to cover more and more obscure edge cases. Now all that stands before you and a finished spell is the final component: the way the spell travels from the Wizard to the anchor-points. --- The final project for the year is the second half of paper-writing for the results of the Warp Lightning experiments you undertook with Adela. Unfortunately, it proves to be far from a culminating high note, as the two of you struggle to bring to bear any insight that hasn't already been documented in the scarce few books the Colleges have on the subject. It's a struggle to fill an entire paper, but in the end you think the result just manages to be worth the effort it takes. It might not bring anything new to the table, but it does present a thorough and detailed description of something usually only seen in flashes across a battlefield. And perhaps more importantly, Adela seems much more satisfied than you with the end result, and practically radiates satisfaction at having put her name out there as a budding scholar of esoteric sciences - especially one linked to an already-established figure of some prominence. [Mathilde paper writing: 16+28+4(Library: Skaven Warp Magic)=48.] [Adela paper writing: 26+20+4(Library: Skaven Warp Magic)+10(Uncanny Memory)=60.] [Observations on Warp Lightning, 2485. Subject: Rare, +1. Insight: Agreement, +0. Delivery: Competent, +0. Thorough, +1. Precious, +1. Secondary Author, -2. Total: +1.] --- Mathilde has begun a romantic relationship with Panoramia of the Jade Order. What are her future intentions in this realm? [ ] [ROMANCE] Continue a monogamous relationship with Panoramia. [ ] [ROMANCE] Seek a romantic relationship with a second partner. [ ] [ROMANCE] Break up with Panoramia in favour of seeking a relationship with a new partner. [ ] [ROMANCE] Break up with Panoramia in favour of remaining single. If Mathilde seeks a new partner, who is your preference for that partner? [ ] [ROMANCE] Magister Johann [ ] [ROMANCE] Elector Countess Roswita van Hal [ ] [ROMANCE] Baron Anton Kiesinger II [ ] [ROMANCE] The Ice Dragon of Karag Zilfin [ ] [ROMANCE] Chief Bombardier Oswald Oswaldson Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The four with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] The Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks (locked in) [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) [+] EIC Reports (does not cost a choice) Fellow Wizards [ ] Gretel, who's apparently spending her newly-earned wealth to make herself at home. [ ] Hubert, as he settles in to his niche with Ulrikadrin. Karak Eight Peaks Notables [ ] Elder Hluodwica, High Priestess of Esmerelda and civilian leader of the Eight Peaks Halflings. [ ] Francesco Caravello, proud Viceroy of the Undumgi. [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart, leader of the frontier town of Ulrikadrin. [ ] Cython, to discuss the Gods of Kislev and the Kurgan. [ ] Qrech, to discuss his newly-acquired diploma from the University of Altdorf. Foreign Relations [ ] Stirland, to see for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. Friends Abroad [ ] Julia, to see what she has gotten up to as Stirland's most experienced spy master. [ ] Eike Hochschild, to get to know your future business partner. [ ] The Dolgan, to get to know the people of the western Steppes who will hopefully be feeding the Expedition. Following Up [ ] The Amber College, to check in on the salamanders. [ ] The Gold College, to see what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - It would be possible to try the robes enchantment again, but trying to disentangle the scales and power stone risks destroying one or both of them. - As always, new suggestions for social actions are welcome. They're most likely to be added if they're a shared activity that allows for interesting interaction or a specific topic to be discussed, rather than 'be social at [person]'. - This is a bit more abrupt than I'd preferred the romance process to be, but it appears that on this matter a choice must be made between voter agency and thread civility. - Speaking of civility: I do hope that drastic measures won't be needed to maintain it during the coming debate. - If Mathilde seeks a polygamous relationship, it will be with the knowledge and consent of everyone involved. - The romance vote assumes that a voter's preferred romance partners are the same whether they are pursued polygamously or monogamously. My apologies if this is not the case for you, but it is required to keep voting straightforward.

Turn 32 Social - 2485.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [ROMANCE] Continue a monogamous relationship with Panoramia. [*] Cython, to discuss the Gods of Kislev and the Kurgan. [*] Qrech, to discuss his newly-acquired diploma from the University of Altdorf. [*] Eike Hochschild, to get to know your future business partner. [*] Elder Hluodwica, High Priestess of Esmerelda and civilian leader of the Eight Peaks Halflings. "It seems I have erred in overlooking what you call the Old World - an admirably egocentric label - in my research of the Gods," Cython says as it peruses the books on Kislev you've brought down into the guest room dedicated to it. "I visited it a few times in the aftermath of the Elf-Dwarf War, but their Gods seemed mostly aped from the Elves whose ruins they built upon. Hoeth and Morai-Heg as parents, Isha as the daughter, Myrmidia being the only novel element. But then they decided on a new addition to their pantheon, and I admit that at first I was as fooled as they. A horned God of savage competition and self-interest? Kurnous, clear as noon. When I next visited, the few survivors were scattered far and wide." "We call them the 'Classical' or 'Southern' Gods," you note, "as opposed to the 'Elder' or 'Northern' Gods that the ancestors of the Empire brought with them - Taal, Rhya, Manann, and Ulric." "The wilds, fertility, the ocean," it says dismissively. "Ulric is another puzzle. Ellinilli, perhaps?" "I once heard a Laurelorn Elf theorize the same. Who or what are the Ellinilli?" "Elven Gods of natural destruction fathered by Ellinill, who then grew mistrustful and devoured most of them. Some of them have grown beyond their origins - Mathlann became God of the Sea, Drakira the Goddess of Vengeance, Addaioth has been trying to become a God of Weapons. Ulric may have been a God of blizzards or similar that grew beyond His origins." "Ulric is said to be brother to Taal," you note. "It is my suspicion that mortal labels do not apply well to relationships among the Gods." It snorts. "Or perhaps they do, and they are as tumultuous and variable as those of mortals. Ask a Priest of Asuryan who sired Nethu." "Why do you theorize that there must be so much crossover between the different pantheons?" It tilts its head. "Why would there not be? Do two dragons share a hunting ground? Two kings a kingdom?" You consider the point, and have to admit there could be merit to it. You've yourself witnessed Ranald in conflict, first against Stromfels and then against Mork. You've also recently read of Kislevite Gods, and Ursun's Cult is said to have fraught relationship with Ulric's. Did that reflect the relationship between the Gods, where Ulric and Ursun's conceptual territories are too similar, bringing the two into conflict because it causes them to... what? Detract from each other? Be able to prey upon each other? "I can see the question roiling inside you like a gathering storm," Cython notes. "To Hysh, it is the moment of realization that is most satisfying, and the rest is simply the thrill of the hunt. To Ulgu, the seeking itself must energize." You turn your attention to your Windsight, and note that indeed the Ulgu in the room has gathered around you like an aura. It's not enough for you to notice unless you're looking for it, though maybe that changes as one grows more and more attuned to a Wind. "As a Wizard, maybe," you say. "As a scholar, I'd like some hard answers." "And as a dragon, it is a matter of great regret that I cannot hunt and eat light. We can never satisfy every facet of our nature." --- "The Kurgan worship the Chaos Gods," you say to Cython later, after it had moved on from Kislevites to Chaos Marauders. "Which I expected. But they have a pantheon of one-two-four-eight - one sun, two moons, four Chaos Gods, and Eight Winds. It was surprising to me to read about, and then encounter, a people that consider Priests and Wizards to be so similar." "I doubt they worship Asuryan or Lileath, so it might be erroneous worship - I doubt the celestial bodies care for or respond to worship. Their worship of..." It flips through the book. "'Ghyranek' might be an aspect of Chaos worship, perhaps a representation of Chaos Undivided. I have heard of Beastmen that worship Chaos itself and spurn the Chaos Gods. But as for the Winds, to worship them as Gods is incorrect, but why is it incorrect?" "I assume you're going for something deeper than 'because Winds aren't Gods'." "Correct. What is the vital difference between these two varieties of foreign energy with distinct preferences?" A hefty question, but one you are not approaching unassisted. "Winds are reliable and ambient. 'I do not wish to trust the continued benevolence of a deity whose need for my faith and dedication might far outweigh my own need for His or Her aid.' That was said by Volans, the first leader of the Empire's Colleges of Magic." "It is a vital difference, and one that makes all the difference in the wisdom of adopting one or the other. The Winds are available freely, acting according to their nature in the same way that air and water and soil are. But I observe that though Hysh asked nothing of me, it has dictated as much of my life and preferences and activites as the most demanding God. Could you say differently?" You consider the question, and have to admit that as much of a constant presence Ranald is in your life, Ulgu is more so. "No, I couldn't. Are you suggesting that the Winds are, what, Gods playing the long game?" "I do not believe that to be the case," Cython says, ruffling its wings in a draconic shrug. "But I have yet to find a way to prove that it isn't. There are many theories as to why the energies of the Aethyr change so drastically and fundamentally when they enter this world, and that there are Eight guarding the entrance to this world and countering the corruption of the Four is far from the least likely of those theories. There is also an argument to be made that the Winds are Gods that exist primarily in this world, where the other Gods exist primarily in the other. To prove or disprove either requires more insight into the nature of the Gods than I possess." It grins, a sudden flash of glinting vertices. "Yet." --- To all to whom these Letters shall come, Greeting; The Warden of the University of Altdorf, on the recommendation of the Council of Masters and by virtue of the authority in them vested, have conferred on Quirin Waramunt who has satisfactorily pursued the Studies and passed the Examinations required therefor, the Degree of Baccalaureate Philosophiae in the Social Science of Near Eastern Studies with all the Rights, Privileges, and Honours thereunto appertaining. Given this Eighth Day of Vorgeheim, Two Thousand Four Hundred and Eighty-Five. The framed certificate is on display on the wall of Qrech's cell, nestled amongst the many shelves filled with books and carved wooden figures. Qrech chitters with pride every time his eyes fall upon it, but judging by the papers resting upon his desk Qrech is far from finished with his terrorizing of the University of Altdorf. Ever since he learned that an advanced degree would confer upon him the title of 'Doctor' his eyes have been set on it, apparently as a balm to a sense of inadequacy that every Skaven of House Moulder who do not participate in the art of their Clan feels. "And then I shall teach," Qrech says, in between carefully gnawing a fresh point onto his quill. "And in doing so, reveal the vulnerabilities of the Chaos Dwarves to the surface races. Every blow that weakens them will strengthen Moulder." He seems to mean it, but there was more conviction and pride in his voice at the start than at the end. He seems to be trying to convince himself that the comfort he's found in his academic niche is still serving his distant Clan. And then he perks up and waves a claw at his bookshelf. "And when all respect my words as master of the doom of the eastern foes? A book. All Qrech's knowledge carved onto wood and stamped onto a hundred, a thousand copies. And when those books grow old, copied into new books. I have read of the Ambush at Mount Cragg, words from ten lifetimes ago. The Battle of Kurgel's Gulch from fifty lifetimes ago. The song of Sir Baldrin of Brionne from seventy lifetimes ago." He chitters, patting the spines of his books. "Qrech will die, but Qrech's words will outlive all. Even the favoured who get the long-life concoctions. Even Throt. Even Lord Verminkin." "That's a worthy ambition," you note. "Qrech has many advantages," he says with clear pride. "One Professor has personally fought Chaos Dwarves. Did so during an attack on his caravan. A paltry skirmish with their lowest soldiers. Very respected, treated as an authority." He sniffs. "Qrech has lead small armies against the Eastern Dwarves. Qrech has slain them. Qrech has feasted on their flesh. Qrech has seen Bull Centaurs and Daemonsmiths and K'Daai. Qrech's victory is assured." --- "Gods above," Wilhelmina says, settling back gingerly into the well-cushioned seat on the balcony of the EIC's headquarters. "The years sneak up on you. I've spent too many years sitting on hard wooden carriage seats and the bill's come due." "From the paperwork, you don't seem to have lost a step," you observe as you sit yourself on a significantly less cushioned one. "Here's hoping you're right, and it's just my back that's playing up. It's easy to hunker down, we'll really see how well I'm doing when that canal is finally done and we have to fight off everyone with a boat and a dream." She sighs, and runs her hand through her hair. "Anyway, what brings you here today?" "I wanted to spend some time with Eike, get to know my future partner." "Good idea, better to inculcate the proper terror of the Grey Order early on. My sons might have turned out worth a damn if I had you around to scare them into submission. Tillie!" A few moments later a frazzled-looking assistant pokes her head out. "Go get Eike and bring her up." "Do you want to be there while I talk to her?" She shrugs. "Probably for the best not to, she and I haven't been getting along of late. Inherited my temper, probably." You let that pass uncommented as Wilhelmina hauls herself back up with a groan. A few minutes after Wilhelmina disappears back inside, Eike appears at the doorway. "You wanted to see me, Dame Weber?" "Take a seat," you say. She moves to do so, but hesitates halfway. "Something wrong?" "Your shadow is looking at me," she says - her voice wary rather than outright scared, to her credit. "It does that. It's harmless, it moves around a bit but in other respects it's like any other shadow." Eike takes a seat, still watching the shadow. "Is that a Wizard thing?" "A Grey Wizard thing, yes. Give it a poke if it will make you feel better." She does so hesitantly, then with a frown of concentration as her pokes try to chase the retreating shadow along the wall. You take the opportunity to give her a once-over - she's neatly if plainly dressed, sports a few inkstains, and seems to be in good health. Under your Windsight she's largely untouched, but close scrutiny reveals a few traces of Chamon and Aqshy. She'd probably been in tutoring before being called to meet you which could explain the Wind of Metal. The Wind of Fire is tricky, it could be the result of enthusiasm or annoyance, so it's hard to draw any conclusions from that. You refocus on the physical world as the shadow finally retreats entirely from Eike's reach and she turns back to you. "You're going to be my partner in the EIC one day," you comment. She nods firmly. "When oma retires. Going to Keep The Wagons Rolling and help everyone by getting the things where they need to be." You can practically hear the capital letters in her voice as she parrots a phrase she probably heard from Wilhelmina. You smile. "That's one way to describe what we do." "Oma says that you're here to Keep Us Honest and it's a good thing that I'd be in charge because if my father was you'd have to shoot him." She eyes the revolvers on your hip curiously. "Would you?" "If I had to," you admit. "Getting everything where it needs to be is important. Some people think they can make money by interfering with that." "They try to Skin The Sheep," she says, nodding. "Oma says not to, and that when my Dooming said to 'beware the cloven hoof' it wasn't talking about sheep, and it's a metaphor anyway." "She's probably right." You consider all the other possible cloven-hoofed dangers, and decide to move the conversation along. "So if you've had your Dooming, have you had your Quickening too?" She makes a face. "The Priestess explained a whole bunch of things she said I'll be interested in one day." You nod. The Dooming and the Quickening are supposed to happen at about the same time, but in small villages they happen whenever the right Priests come by, so you'd ended up never having yours. "And what did you do after?" you ask casually. "Fed the doves. I had to go to the park to do it because oma said if I fed them here they'd hang around and poop on her chair." You nod. She's a Shallyan, then. You can work with that. --- "Done?" Wilhelmina says distractedly as you enter her office. "Seems like a decent kid," you say, and note Wilhelmina's frown. "You don't agree?" "She's ten, she's supposed to be an adult now, but she's nowhere near where she should be. Her tutors say she's getting there, but I half-suspect they're just saying that so I don't fire them. She seemed so bright when I adopted her." "If she's getting there, she'll get there. Are you in a hurry to retire?" "Far from it. I just don't want what I build collapsing the second I settle down or keel over." She sighs, and shuffles some papers. "While you're here, I might as well get you updated, save some money on scribing." "Sure." "Short version: Sylvania's still quiet and those last two holdouts are still besieged, and there's rumours that Roswita will finally finish it this coming spring - but then, there's been rumours of that for every spring since she showed up. Piracy is still huge, still taking big chunks out of the competition, still taking very few chunks out of us - those galleys have been a big help in filling gaps in River Warden schedules." She slides over papers and you run your eyes over the distilled reports to see if anything jumps out at you. "Outbreak of disease among the canal workers?" "Bad meat or bad water," Wilhelmina says with a shrug. "It happens, especially with that many people in one place. The Dwarves say it shouldn't set back the schedule too much." "You think it's natural?" "You don't?" "It'd be normal most of the time, but this is a Dwarven project in a remote area. They'd be supplying food and water, and they'd be making sure they were clean." "Surely the Marienburgers wouldn't..." She frowns. "They wouldn't, would they? I mean, sure, piracy and sabotage, but fomenting disease? That would be..." Her frown deepens. "I'll have a word with some Witch Hunters." "Good. I do hope that it's nothing, but if they're willing to even flirt with the Ruinous Powers like that..." She shudders. "Gods, I hope it's nothing. In other news..." You raise your eyebrows as Wilhelmina drops two bulging purses on the table. "Business has been that good?" She shakes her head exasperatedly. "It's not your cut, it's already yours. You haven't touched the profits from that factory since you first left for Eight Peaks." "Oh, right." You frown and eye the purses, trying to calculate if the Bursar is going to get snippy about this. "Bloody Wizards. That shadow of yours and the smoke and the candles playing up, that's par for the course. But 'oh, right'? That's just not natural. It's enough money to buy a house and you just had it sitting there." "I am supposed to be under a Vow of Poverty," you protest. "That's why I asked you to plough it all into expanding instead of buying me out." "Which I did, but I'm not taking your actual money to do so. There's a line and that's it." She shakes her head again and rummages in her papers. "Right, gong farming. I kept the model you were using - subscription to pay for the collectors, fertilizer sales to pay for the factories. Where it already existed it was mostly ad hoc for fertilizer, only a few big towns were doing it for cleanliness and health, so Rudiger was able to use the threat of undercutting and a promise of better wages to absorb what there was without much trouble. We've broken ground on factories in Blutdorf and Franzen, should be ready when the first round of the material is ready for processing. The only question is the output." She eyes you across the desk. "How do you mean?" "It's a lot of management and set-up for a modest return on investment. You wouldn't be bothering if it wasn't about the niter. Zhufbar has the current output locked into a contract, but a lot more is about to be made. What's the plan for it?" [ ] Sell the niter to Zhufbar [ ] Sell the niter to Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Sell the niter to Nuln [ ] Plan to set up EIC gunpowder production in Stirland [ ] Plan to set up EIC gunpowder production in Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Other (write in) - Qrech's portion was meant to be a fair bit longer as he and Mathilde hashed out a suitable future for him, but while double-checking Skaven lifespans I came across the death scene of Sleek Sharpwit and Qrech's ambition fell right into place. - Keep in mind that Cython's theories are not WoG about the setting's metaphysics. This is recreational for Cython, rather than being approached as a hard science. - The text of Qrech's diploma was originally posted here. Spoiler You think... you think any beyond your own scrap of hill knows or cares who you are? You think in fifty years any will remember? You are impossible, mad-thing. You do not know the meaning of forever. Look at me! I am still alive and already forgotten! [...] We scurry through time, like the rats in Fizqwik’s wheel. Over and over the same mistakes. I am glad to be done. I am sick of it. We steal so much from the dwarf-things, more than any care to admit, but never that. Respect for what is past. [...] It would be nice... to be remembered.

Turn 32 Social - 2485.5 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan to set up EIC gunpowder production in Stirland "Stirland is currently reliant on importing gunpowder, and dealing with the unreliable quality of Nuln's gunpowder - since the purest goes to those currently in the Elector Count's favour - or paying a hefty premium for powder from Zhufbar," you say, steepling your fingers. "Considering how reliant the Repeater is on good powder, it's a limiter to how much the Army of Stirland will be willing to expand its use." "Can you get your hands on the proper techniques?" Wilhelmina asks, leaning forward. You consider it for a moment. "I might be able to get Dwarven ones, but I'd be on the hook for them - that's an uncomfortable position when I'd usually be a continent away from the factory. But I've got an in or two with the Imperial Gunnery School. If we tie it into non-compete contracts I should be able to get Nuln's techniques out of them, and I doubt we'll be able to exceed the requirements of both Stirland and the Undumgi." "Alright, we'll stockpile any excess niter production for now." Wilhelmina frowns thoughtfully. "The factory will probably have to be in Wurtbad. I can't see Roswita allowing it outside her demesne." You nod. "We've got a lot of eggs in Blutdorf's basket as it is. And Wurtbad's better located to take in niter from a province-wide network." "Not what I expected for the EIC, but it's not like gunpowder will ever not be needed," Wilhelmina says, then smiles and pats the hip where a pistol would usually be, though her gunbelt is currently hanging from a hook on the wall. "I like the idea of being able to pull good powder right out of the factory too, instead of paying a king's ransom for the good stuff." --- "A question for you, Magister," Algard says as he leads you through the halls of the Grey College. "What is the location of the Grey College?" You've mapped it out, most Grey Wizards do as Apprentices. You have to decide based mostly on guesswork which access points are physical and which aren't to get a solid answer, so most end up with different answers. "Just below the Imperial Mint. I assume to add its defences to our College's, and vice versa." He smiles. "It's the sort of thing we would do." He stops at a blank section of wall, and your mental map of the Grey College tells you you're on the outer edge of the College - or at least, the portion you know. You eye it suspiciously for any trace of secret entrances. "'Would do', but not 'have done'." "To hide something from a Grey Wizard, give them enough false clues to reach a wrong answer that makes them feel clever," he says with a smile. "To hide it from many, have enough wrong answers for them to argue over. Who says any of the access points are physical?" "Basic logic," you retort. "The College has to be somewhere, so having at least some of the access points be physical is only sensible. Saves magical power and effort, and allows an access point in case of local magical collapse." "The College has to be somewhere," he repeats, his smile widening. "A logical assumption." He places a hand on the wall and it ripples and melts away, revealing... nothing. A uniform field of grey on the other side, stretching as far as you can see in all directions. "The problem with logical assumption is that logic often has nothing to do with our profession." He walks through the opening and without any visible trepidation you follow suit, walking atop an invisible floor. The wall heals below you and vanishes, enfolding the pair of you in an endless grey void. It's just as featureless to your Magesight as it is to your eyes. "Where are we?" "To everyone else, the border between this world and the Aethyr is as thin as a dream. To those with the right attunement, the border can be a plane in its own right." He takes a seat on a chair you're certain was not there a moment ago. "It is the source of some of our most potent abilities. This is where objects enfolded within Substance of Shadow reside, this is the impossibly thin and thus infinitely sharp edge summoned by Penumbral Pendulum, this is where the Pit of Shades opens into, creating a wailing as the air itself is crushed. And through Teclis' techniques that I've only begun to scratch the surface of, it can be permanently expanded into a pocket big enough for a College." "It is the Hedge," says Provost Kurtis Krammovitch, and you turn to see him sitting just beside Algard. "And the Hedgewise have been visiting it since before the time of Sigmar." "It is the Shadows that give the Forest of Shadows its name," says Lord Magister Walther Kupfer, "stolen by the Goddess Halétha to empower those who are opposed to it." "It is a portion of the Aethyr that has been cut off from the rest, which happens more often than you might think," says Lady Magister Grey. "It is a metaphor, fed by Ulgu until it grew fat enough to visit," says Bursar Wilhelmine von Bucht. "It is part of the Grey Vaults, the threshold of Morr's Realm," says Porter Reiner Starke. "It's simply a novel application of existing principles," says Lord Magister Melkoth. "It's a secret, even to us," says Algard. "Ours to puzzle over, and ours to keep." You complete your circuit, and see an empty eighth chair in the circle surrounding you. "And now yours. Take a seat, Lady Magister Weber." Without a moment's hesitation you do so, happiness and pride radiating through your body. You knew you might be close to earning it, but after the promotion to Magister you half-expected it to be a curt letter or something. But a circle of chairs in a secret pocket-dimension formed by Teclis? This is exactly the sort of thing you had hoped for. Part of the upholstery of the chair springs to life, throwing itself onto your robes and forming the ornamental trimmings that indicate a Wizard Lord of the Empire to those who know the patterns. "Don't ask me how long it took to set that up," Lady Magister Grey grumbles. "Eight years wearing the same robe, and you make a new one just as we're about to promote you." "We had planned to let you season a few more years," Algard says with a smile, "but if you're going into hell, it's only proper you shall do so in the rank you have earned." --- Master Baker Hluodwica, Elder of the Karak Eight Peaks Halflings and High Priestess of Esmerelda, is easily the most important personage in Karak Eight Peaks that you haven't spent much time with. It's easy to justify why - the Halflings are happy to be left to their fields and their food, and if there were any problems Kazrik or Edda or Panoramia would be the logical people to handle them - but it's still something you've been meaning to correct when you had a spare moment. The local Temple to Esmerelda is a three-sided building placed amongst the fields equidistant between Karag Nar and Karag Lhune, with an entrance on each side for Halflings from the fields, Dwarves from Karag Lhune, and humans from Karag Nar to visit it freely. This is an offer taken up much more often than those unfamiliar with Halflings would expect, for Esmerelda is worshipped by making, supplying, and consuming good food. Some might consider this a trivial sphere for a Goddess, especially one that is the head of a Pantheon, but only if they were very sure where their next meal is coming from. In many of the darker periods in Imperial history, simple lack of food has killed more than disease or greenskins or the forces of Chaos. Even the humble pie, the much-derided object of worship during Pie Week, has more to it than those that dismiss the Halflings as simple gluttons would realize. In the distant past, long before humanity had come to the Old World, food preservation was poorly understood and starving during the winter was a constant threat. Pottery was fragile, difficult to transport, time-consuming to make, and required access to the right sorts of clays. Granaries were immobile and took a lot of effort to make, and meant all your food was in one place and fire or rot or vermin could take the whole structure in one fell swoop. But encasing food in a shell of flour before you cook it? That was quick, easy, portable, divisible, and if done right, delicious. It was that secret that gained the Halflings a position in the nomadic tribes that predate the Empire, and it's why the human tribes had Halflings among them when they entered the Reik Basin. You introduce yourself to the Priestess at the bench, and know better than to resist as she pushes the meal of the day on you before she goes off to fetch the High Priestess, and put a couple of silver coins into the offering bowl before taking your seat and examining the meal. It's a thick wheat-based soup with beans and vegetables of a sort that had been mildly popular in Altdorf when you were an Apprentice and you've made good progress on it by the time Hluodwica arrives and seats herself across from you, placing a bowl of her own in front of her. "Magister-" She looks again, and corrects herself. "Lady Magister Weber. Are you enjoying the meal?" "Haven't had this in almost twenty years," you say. "Minestrone, right?" "So it's known in the Empire, but that's simply Tilean for 'soup'. They now know it as polus but the basic recipe dates back to their earliest records, from the times when they'd boil spelt in salt water and add whatever vegetables they had on hand, and called it pulte." "You study history?" you ask curiously. "I study food, and food is history," she says, with perfect confidence. "Or at least it is to those of us who didn't have the fortune of being given magical paradises by their Gods. You can't build a city until you have enough food that someone can focus on building instead of hunting or gathering or farming. How many missed meals would it take to reduce Altdorf to rubble?" You smile. "I was there for the Dunnage Tax riots. Sometimes it seems like you'd barely need one." "You might be right. I'm glad it's Hisme that has to deal with it, and not me. So, is your business here today mild enough that it can accompany eating?" "Purely a social call," you say, and she nods and takes up her spoon. "As you've just pointed out, the Halflings are important to the Karak, and you lead them. I've been meaning to find the time to get to know you better for some time." "And unlike our Panoramia, you don't have a lazy winter to fill with socializing," she notes. "Dusk and dawn she said, and it's never far from one of those, is it? Busy as..." She smiles. "Almost said busy as a bee, but even they're lazy as anything when the snows come." "Sow that you may reap, then reap that you may sow," you say with a shrug. "Always something that needs doing." "That's a Stirlandian saying," she notes. "You're from there, then?" "Spymistress there for eight years," you say, not inaccurately. "There's very few of our kind that isn't aware of that. Many a tragedy for us wandered over from the Haunted Hills or the Ghoul Wood, and it seems that course in our history is finishing. But that's not what I asked." You consider several answers. "Kelham," you say eventually. "Ah," she says, looking at you with an undecipherable expression. "I thought I heard a trace of it in your accent." "I left when I was ten," you continue, "and have not practiced their traditions in twenty-five years." After a long moment, she nods. "Carrots and weeds grow in the same soil, and Panoramia and Titus both have nothing but good to say of you. I apologize for bringing it up." You think of the many figures hanging from trees and being beaten with sticks in your earliest memories that you're only mostly sure were straw-stuffed effigies, and nod in acceptance. "So! That Panoramia, hm? Quite a girl." You're happy to seize the change in topic. "I quite think so." "Our kind only very rarely produce Wizards, even more so than yours, and while we're happy not to have the fire and death and wild animals, we could use a few more Panoramias. Only has to spend a day in a field and she knows it like her family has been farming it for three generations." You're happy to let the conversation linger there until the meal is concluded, and then make your farewells. Not quite what you expected, but you've still gotten to know the disconcertingly perceptive Elder of the local Halflings at least a little. --- The applause when you arrive at the meeting is almost instant which leads you to suspect Panoramia had tipped them off, but it's heartfelt and gratifying nonetheless. You don't think you'll ever get sick of hearing 'congratulations, Lady Magister'. But as tempting as it is, your ego cannot be the sole focus of the last official meeting of the Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks before you leave for Karag Dum, so you wrap it up and move the meeting along. Even as the meeting goes through its usual patterns the shadow of Karag Dum is ever-present, as most of those present have been focusing on their preparations for it these past months. Adela and Gretel don't have much to contribute, having been busy working their way deeper into the local Gunnery School and the Besiegers respectively. If nothing else, it's something to be proud of that each of your Ducklings have found a niche for themselves here in the Karak. Afterwards, Panoramia lingers as the rest of the Wizards file out. "Hey," you say with a smile. "Hey," she replies. "Something wrong?" "You haven't asked me if I'm coming," she says softly. "I figured you'd tell me when you decided if you would." "Do you want me to come?" You take a moment to consider that. "I have a preference," you admit, "but it's much less important to me than you deciding for yourself." She smiles. "That's sweet of you." She sighs, and stretches out her legs while leaning back in her chair. "I think I could. Missing most of the spring would set the timetable back, but probably only by a year - the Halflings know the conditions well enough to maintain them. I think. And it's not like the Karak is in danger of starving, or running out of gold to buy food." She looks at you. "What's it like up there?" "It's the same terrain as the Veldt in Ostermark. It all seems shockingly normal, except for the sky. The Winds blow so hard that they can't settle, and they flow in rivers overhead, lighting up the sky. It's supposed to be worse further north, but Kurgan land stretches all the way up to the Karag so I think logically it can't be any worse than Mordheim. I suppose it makes sense that it couldn't be too disrupted until it's nearer the pole, there's supposed to be Norscan tribes living as far north as the far side of the Frozen Sea." "Do you think it will succeed?" "Succeed," you muse. "I think it'll find out what happened. I think that if it's necessary, I can make the Expedition turn around. And I think that in the worst case scenario, I can make it home." "I'll hold you to that." She goes quiet as she considers it some more. "I don't think I can. I've been doing this for seven years. If I went north, my mind would be here the entire time. Are they keeping it in check, have there been any spore outbreaks, is the soil enrichment staying balanced without any ability to gauge it..." She sighs. "I'm sorry." You shake your head firmly. "Don't apologize. I asked you to decide. I'm glad you did." "Thank you for understanding." She reaches across the table and places her hand on yours. "You know, I've been noticing a pattern," she says a few moments later with a teasing smile. "Dragonbone staff, enchanted flask for firebreathing, dragonscale pauldrons. Should I be worried about the time you're spending with Cython?" "No," you say simply. "I chose you." She laughs, then stops when she realizes you're serious. "Wait, really?" "I mean, we are dating now, aren't we?" "That's not what I-" She realizes you were playing with her, and you can see her eyes dart around the area to see if there's anything she can throw at you that's not so heavy that it could actually hurt. "I mean, you're attracted to dragons?" "I'm attracted to clever and interesting," you say with a shrug. "And I guess dangerous, a bit. Beyond that, it's all just..." You wave a hand. "Details, and logistics." She considers that. "I'm not dangerous." "Have you seen the thorn thing you do?" She cocks her head. "I guess put that way, I can kind of see it." She nods to herself. "Plus your Magesight is visual. I suppose Cython's just one big flare of Hysh to that, just like I am with Ghyran." "I admit, you look really impressive drawing on the Waystones." "Really?" She leans back in her chair to place her fingers on the smoothed stone of the wall, and after a moment she brightens in your vision as Ghyran trickles into her. "I'll have to keep that in mind." --- [ ] [TOWER] Battery (COLOUR) Seek to expand the capability of a tower to absorb and store its wind for future use. 50gc. [ ] [TOWER] Far Sight Filled to the brim with refraction cantrips, this tower would allow anyone in it to see in detail any point within line of sight. 2 College Favours. [ ] [TOWER] Protection (COLOUR) Build a tower to magically reinforce or protect the others. Specify wind. 5 College favours. [ ] [TOWER] Anti-Air (COLOUR) Build a tower to magically attack any airborne enemies. Specify wind. 5 College favours. [ ] [TOWER] Smoke and Mirrors Build a tower to enable longer-range teleportation. Will require an action to set up, exact implementation will be determined by rolls and choices with that action. [ ] [TOWER] Greenhouse A tower infused with the Jade Wind and temperature controls to allow for horticultural experimentation and fresh fruit year-round. 50gc, 2 College Favours, 2 Dwarf Favours. Library Purchases Budget: 300gc, 2 Dwarf Favour. Anything not spent will not accumulate. [ ] [LIBRARY] No purchase. [ ] [LIBRARY] Write-in. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - This is the last chance for purchases before the Expedition. - Suggestions for new towers are welcome. - The promotion portion of the update was originally posted here.

Ambush on the Skull River 1

At long, long last, the Okral have finished their work, packed up, and returned to Karaz-a-Karak. Though the tension never really eased through their long stay in Karak Eight Peaks, it never came to a head either, which is a relief. Belegar isn't quite looking for an excuse to escalate his feud with Karaz-a-Karak, but he wouldn't turn one away if it knocked on his door either. It's a small miracle that he never received one. The planned celebration, officially for the reclamation in general but unofficially because the Okral is finally gone, is still some time off as its preparations are put on the backburner in favour of moving everyone around. The growing Clans of the refounded Karak are spreading out into the newly-restored twin peaks of Karags Rhyn and Mhonar, which have been dedicated to Valaya and Smednir respectively. Karag Lhune was far from running out of space, but the logic is that it wouldn't do to leave too much of the mountains empty as it would invite something to fill it. You fully expect to have a nice and long quiet period to put the finishing touches on your preparations for the Karag Dum Expedition. Unfortunately, the sounding of the Citadel's signal horn just as the sun is setting - a design gifted to the Karak by King Kazador Thunderhorn, which says all that needs to about how loud and impossible to ignore it is - dashes those hopes, and as quickly as you safely can you wind down your manipulation of magical energies and rush to the balcony. You're supposed to look to the signal flags first, but your attention is firmly grabbed by the first full demonstration of Gotri's 'honeycomb' hangar design as Karag Lhune's slopes expel its full complement of gyrocopters, each of which circles the mountain to throw itself northwards at all possible speed. You're already developing a suspicion as you tear your eyes downwards to see the signal flags on the Citadel - 'Karaz-a-Karak, army, under attack'. With a moment's concentration you expel a cloud of Ulgu in the shape of your coat of arms, and you're hugely relieved to see that of the Angrund clan answer it, and a gyrocarriage is already touching down outside the King's Gates. After it collects its cargo, you're mostly glad and only a little nervous to see it beeline straight in your direction, rather than immediately following the angry swarm of copters north. In what seems like a moment it's touching down on the landing pad on your balcony and you're clambering aboard to see three familiar faces - Belegar, Gotri, and Dreng. "Part of the Okral's been attacked," Belegar yells over the sound of the engine. "Skull River, near the southern edge of the Forest of Gloom." "Forest Goblins?" you say. You really hope it was Forest Goblins. "Bandits." Even over the engine you can hear the suspicion in his voice. "How many casualties?" "Gotri?" [Rolling...] [Rolling...] "Unconfirmed," he says, double checking some hastily-scrawled notes, "but it sounds like a lot. An entire passenger monitor went down while carrying several hundred passengers, perhaps as many as a thousand. My pilot who was escorting the convoy said there was some sort of explosion below the waterline, then musket fire from the shore. And that's not a good river to go down in." You suppress a shudder at the thought. Skull River is named not so much for the bones that litter its banks, but for the skull-shaped markings on the ravenous swarms of predatory fish that fill it. "Weber, we're all thinking it. Can you rule out Marienburg's involvement?" You remember your own suspicions regarding the disease outbreak in southern Stirland. "I can't," you admit. "If it was their agents, they might have mistaken the passenger ships for a supply convoy, bound for the canal." "Damn," is all Belegar says. "On top of the river itself," Dreng says, "that's right on the border between Black Spider and Bloody Spear territory. If the explosion attracted their attention they could do even more damage." If it had been quieter in there, you'd have described the atmosphere that falls upon the passenger bay as a grim silence. --- The journey is as tense as it is long; as much a miracle of engineering the gyrocarriage is, it's still a long way from Karak Eight Peaks to the Skull River, especially once the sun fully sets and the pilot has to follow the Blood River north to keep on course. When you finally arrive, it's to see by the light of a gibbous Mannsleib and a crescent Morrsleib that the Okral's convoy has beached itself on the eastern bank of the river, and the very tip of the steam funnel of the wrecked ship just peeking out from the top of the rapidly-flowing waters. Several burning fires illuminate a nearby hill where this segment of the Okral are fortifying themselves and gyrocopters buzz overhead in wary circles. "Barak Varr's reinforcements should arrive by dawn," Belegar says as the gyrocarriage begins its descent. "Our first priority is to make sure that nothing further happens to them. Second is answers. Third is vengeance. Understood?" You, Gotri, and Dreng nod as the gyrocarriage alights atop the hill, and the four of you clamber out and are instantly met with a crowd of angry, shouting Dwarves. As the Okral lists its grievances, primarily the apparent death of the leader of Karaz-a-Karak's Metalsmiths Guild, you consider your options for how you can best contribute. Your Magesight makes you the best option for scouting, tracking, or investigating, where everyone else has to wait for the rising sun to make their contributions possible. But there's only one of you. [ ] Remain here and guard the Okral [ ] Try to track the bandits [ ] Scour the river banks for anything the bandits left behind [ ] Use Substance of Shadow to check the wrecked passenger ship for survivors [ ] Scout for any approaching greenskin forces - There will be a one hour moratorium. - You can only choose one thing to do right now; there might be opportunity to do more later, but with every passing moment the tracks get fainter, evidence could be washed away, and any greenskins could get closer.

Ambush on the Skull River 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Use Substance of Shadow to check the wrecked passenger ship for survivors Dwarves don't skimp when it comes to building... well, anything, but doubly so for something that Dwarven lives will be depending upon. The passenger monitor may have sunk, but it hasn't broken apart and it remained upright. There could be Dwarves still alive in air pockets, and any rescue attempts must not only contend with the frigid waters, but also the ravenous fish surrounding the waters, undoubtedly in even larger numbers than usual, drawn to the spilled blood and the bodies of the fallen. Their only chance of rescue before Barak Varr's forces arrive at dawn is you. "Do the monitors have sailcloth? Or any other very large pieces of fabric?" you say, interrupting the Okral leaders. "What?" says one of them, bristling, the eldest by the look of his beard, but the others are already looking around for the captains of the beached vessels, and one of them hurries over. "Yes," he says after you repeat your question. "As back-ups in case the engines fail, and for fothering. Why?" "I need the entire submerged vessel cast into moon-shadow. And at least one river bank, ideally both." "What? Why?" says the captain. "Do it," says Belegar firmly. There's grumbling, but it's accompanying the scattered Dwarves moving to do so, likely glad to have something productive to do. It doesn't take long for sailcloth and ropes to be fetched from the beached vessels, and very quickly a spiderweb of ropes tied to trees and rocks and spikes hammered into the ground begins to form as you explore the layout of one of the vessels, trying to get a feel of where you'd be most likely to find access, while its captain tells you as rapidly as he can of what would have likely occurred in the ship after the explosion - what would have been sealed, what would have been opened, where survivors might be. You could simply step through the hull of the ship with Substance of Shadow, but if any survivors inside have a lit lamp or any other source of light - unlikely, but possible - that would cause your messy and probably painful death. Once that's done, under your direction Dwarves throw long chains towards the ship, one end secured to the shore, so that hopefully no part of the ship is far from a gleam of Chamon that will lead to dry land and safety. And with that done there's nothing left but to have the Dwarves row you out to the funnel, centre yourself, wrap yourself in the magic of Substance of Shadow, hold your breath, and cautiously lower yourself into the water. It's a disconcerting experience. The water surrounds you but does not touch you, so you drop through it as if it was air, landing on the top of the sunken deck with a reverberating clang. Then you let yourself drop through that surface as well, knowing that you're positioned just right to fall into the central corridor of the topmost enclosed deck, which would certainly have flooded and thus would be filled with water and, more importantly, darkness. And though the darkness prevents your magical protection from vanishing and leaving you halfway embedded in metal plating, it also means you've only your Windsight to navigate by, which is as disorienting as you feared. Above ground, every day the land is illuminated by the Hysh-rich sunlight, swept by the weather of Azyr, and pulses with Ulgu at dawn and dusk. The water knows nothing of any of that. There's traces of natural Ghyran in the river itself as flowing water resonates with the Wind of life, but water cut off from the flow stagnates quickly and fades into magical inertness. The only magic around you is the faint Chamon residing within Dwarven steel and, everywhere you look, tiny daggers of Ghur flitting about, full of ravenous hunger and gathering in clouds around pockets of Shyish. Magesight has many advantages over conventional vision, but one that it lacks is depth - regular sight has two eyes, but Magesight only has one soul, so with Chamon on every side it takes utter concentration to make out any details. With rising discomfort in your chest you move down the corridor, running your hand down the wall. The corridor is filled to the ceiling because there's a hatch in the roof, but each room connected to the corridor has an ovular doorway, and even if they were open - which they easily could have been in the rush to escape the sinking ship - there'd be an air bubble in the ceiling. You're proven correct, and take a few deep breaths with relief before pressing on. You don't have much hope for finding survivors on this uppermost deck as anyone up here could have easily reached the deck and swam for it, but you check it anyway, both to be thorough and to acclimate yourself to this strange new environment. You find many reasons to be glad for the peculiarities of Substance of Shadow, as its selective intangibility lets you refill your lungs without having to bring yourself into contact with the water that surrounds you, leaving your robes dry and your passage through the corridors unencumbered, and not least of which because you're sure that if you could see the water, it would be red with blood. You have to push past several bodies who by their silhouette of Shyish are all but skeletonized. It's on the next deck down that you encounter the first sealed door, and find yourself hesitating before it. You can't open it without water and hungry fish flooding in, almost certainly dooming anyone who might be inside. But you won't help them by stepping through the door and being fused with it as some lantern or candle on the other side shatters your spell. You concentrate your Windsight as much as possible, straining to see any hint of Aqshy on the far side, but you're not entirely sure you'd be able to see the Aqshy of a candleflame on the far side of a wall of steel. There could be nobody inside. There could be someone inside who's dry and safe and perfectly fine to wait for Barak Varr's forces to arrive and perform a more conventional rescue. Or they could be neck-deep in freezing water and on the verge of hypothermia. What are the chances that whoever's inside has a light source? One in ten? One in five? Fifty-fifty? How do you weigh an unsure chance of death against the equally unsure chance that whoever's inside needs immediate assistance? You move on. The individual rooms, you remind yourself, are not your primary objective. Your exploration of one of the beached ships revealed that these monitors are dual-purpose, and when they're not holding passengers they hold cargo. So just above the bilge are the cargo holds, equally capable of holding row after row of crates and barrels as they are of holding row after row of passengers sitting on wooden benches. They're where most of the Dwarves would have been, and unless the deck hatches were open or breached, that's where the largest air pockets would be. You make your way down several ladders and pause at the final one, which would lead into the aftmost cargo hold. It's sealed. Why would it be sealed? During normal operation, it's left open to allow air to circulate, especially with hundreds of Dwarves inside. After the explosion, Dwarves escaping would have left it open. It would be sealed if water was entering through it, but the explosion was near the front of the ship, and the doors between cargo holds are kept sealed while moving so that one being breached won't fill all of them. The only scenario it would be sealed is if water started pouring in from above. That would prevent anyone from being able to climb out, but the hatches are designed to still be easily closable in any scenario. You knock on the steel of the hatch and after a few long moments a rapid, almost frantic hammering responds from many hands at once. You picture the cargo hold of the beached ship you explored, the row after row of wooden seating. At least a hundred, probably more. That shifts the odds. You mutter a prayer with the last of your breath and drop through the hatch... [Rolling...] And fall with another clang into a pitch-black room, filled with a babble of Dwarven voices as they try to scramble away from whatever just dropped into the room. "I am Loremaster Weber of Karak Eight Peaks. I am here to rescue you." You climb partway up the hatch's ladder - rematerializing inside water is ill-advised - to release the spell, and then fold Ulgu into a simple light. In a ring around you, shivering and miserable and wet and waist-deep in water, are scores of Dwarves staring at you in confusion and hope. And on the far side of the hold you can see an open door, and more Dwarven faces peering through at you from the next hold. You allow yourself a moment of relief and happiness before you get to work. --- 'Rescue' is easier said than done, but there are few problems that arbitrary amounts of Dwarven artifice can't make easier and this proves to be no exception. A series of pulleys is set up with a chain threaded through them, and one of them is affixed to a boulder that is sunk right outside the cargo hold. Through sheer muscle-power the chain is pulled by a team of Dwarves so that it constantly rotates at a steady speed. In theory, anyone affected by Substance of Shadow in such a way that they are not subject to gravity that then grips onto the chain will be pulled through the water and onto the shore and moonlight will first fall upon them as they dangle slightly above the ground. At that point gravity would reassert itself, the Dwarf lets go, and they can be led away to warm up and recover. Then comes the next one, and so on. The Dwarves inside are lined up roughly in order of how badly they need to go ashore, with the wounded and frail first under the stern direction of their Guildmaster. It's all ready to begin. The only bottleneck in this basic machine is you. Chain-casting is very strenuously warned against by the Colleges. Much as someone who says the same word over and over will soon find themselves garbling it, someone casting the same spell over and over is in extreme danger of garbling that, with much worse consequences than some mangled syllables. But here and now, there's no real choice in the matter. With the cargo hold as flooded as it is and the river filled with snowmelt from the mountains, the only reason there's still survivors is the legendary toughness of Dwarves. But even that can't last until dawn, and until more mundane methods of rescue are able to reach them. So there's nothing for it but to do your best to not garble. With a small lantern brought from the shore on the far side of the compartment and a stack of benches casting your half of the compartment into shadow, you take the first Dwarf's hand, envelop the pair of you in Ulgu, and pull him through the hull of the ship. It only takes a moment to recognize the moving Chamon of the chain and you place the Dwarf's hand upon it, and it only takes a few grasps for the spell to recognize his intentions and for his hand to make contact with the metal. They disappear into the Windsight-obscuring murk of the water and you step back through the hull, step atop another stack of benches to be out of the water, and release the spell. And repeat. And repeat. [Rolling...] And repeat. You can't claim to have done it all perfectly. Several times the spell escaped your control and you were unable to discharge it in time, and your ears are plugged with wax, a milky film is covering your vision, and your muscles ache in a way they shouldn't. But these are the most minor and temporary of manifestations of magic run amok, and after what can't have been much more than two hours but felt like a lifetime, the compartment is finally empty of living Dwarves - an unfortunately necessary qualifier, as three Dwarves heavily injured in the initial blast did not survive the wait. Knowing what you know of Dwarven beliefs surrounding death you try to think of a way to recover them too, but unfortunately one of the many quirks of Substance of Shadow is that it is much easier to apply to living beings than inanimate objects, including formerly living beings. An entire body is beyond your capabilities. You hesitate before leaving the compartment for the final time, thinking of the sealed rooms above. It was pure luck that the lanterns in the compartment you dropped into had fallen off their hooks in the initial blast, and the compartment was too flooded for them to be relit. Do you roll those dice again and in larger numbers for fewer Dwarves? If every sealed room was filled to standing room only, that could represent as many as fifty or more, but if there's at most one or two in each, less than a dozen. And there's still the matters on shore you could concern yourself with. Any approaching greenskins could present a much greater threat to many more lives, and discovering the instigator of this attack and ensuring the Grudge is levelled against the correct party could have geopolitical ramifications that could affect, or even end, thousands of lives. [ ] Return to shore and guard the Okral [ ] Try to track the bandits [ ] Scour the river banks for anything the bandits left behind [ ] Scout for any approaching greenskin forces [ ] Despite the risk to yourself, attempt to save any Dwarves left in the ship [ ] Use your spare Power Stone to save any Dwarves left in the ship This will be achieved by supercharging an Illusion to make it loud enough to be heard throughout the ship, despite the water and metal muffling you. This will tell them all to douse any lights they have on them, making it safe to enter their compartments and retrieve them. Mathilde will only enter compartments that return her knocking, which would signify that there's someone inside who would have heard and followed her instructions. - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Roll for number of survivors was made here and here. - To be clear about the danger SoS rescues represent, if you had rolled a 1 when dropping into the compartment, the quest would have ended instantly. Other results of varying unpleasantness were lined up, up to a threshold I won't share. - Current headcount: 300-400 rescued, including KaK Metalsmiths Guildmaster. Novel rescue plan FAQ: - Using a SoS'd stick to see if there is light on the other side of a door or wall would not result in the stick neatly and quietly merging with the wall. The result would be completely unpredictable, probably dangerous, and have a high chance of breaching the compartment. - Likewise, Branulhune is not an implement for neat incisions. Trying to use it to cut open compartments will be functionally identical to hitting that wall with a cannonball, with negative results for anyone on the other side and on the structure as a whole. - A Dwarven equivalent to morse code does exist, but those aboard would not know it. It's a Guild secret of the Miners and Engineers. - Ulgu-based illusion spells cannot penetrate through the Chamon-rich metal without a lot more Ulgu than is available inside the ship. - Ulgu-based illusion spells can't communicate through water and steel. Sound can't create speech, and Illusion requires too much power to crank up the volume enough.

Ambush on the Skull River 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Scour the river banks for anything the bandits left behind You shake your head. You've gotten lucky so far that your miscasts have been relatively benign, pushing that luck any further could have disastrous results not just for you, but for those you'd be trying to rescue. You wrap yourself in Substance of Shadow one last time and step through the hull to grab the chain, allowing you to be pulled onto the shore. "That's the last of them in the passenger holds," you say to the waiting Dwarves. "There's still some sealed compartments, but I can't access them without risking breaching them. They'll have to wait for Barak Varr." You try not to pay too much attention to the expressions of those that were waiting. Though you saved more Dwarves than you could have hoped and there's still some possibility of rescue for the others, there were still plenty that died long before you arrived. Not everyone is coming out of this with a happy ending. Instead you seek out Belegar who's deep in conversation with the leaders of those present, including the one you had rescued from the sunken ship. Belegar notices your approach and wraps up the conversation before coming over to you. "Near as I can tell, there were about five hundred and fifty aboard the ship when it went down," he says. "Only twenty reached the shore. You just added three hundred and twelve to that tally." "Not a bad night's work," you say, trying to resist the urge to speculate how much larger that number would be if you'd cleared every compartment. He's squinting at you in the lamplight. "Are you okay? Your eyes look odd." You shrug. "It's temporary. I had to do a lot of magic in a short time." "If you need to rest, you've done your share and then some. One of the gyrocopters brought word from Barak Varr's incoming reinforcements, they're fully equipped for rescue and retrieval, and Dreng is leading a band of volunteers from the Okral to try to track down the ambushers, more to keep their minds occupied than in the hopes of actually finding them. Everything's in hand." You shake your head. "I've got enough left in me to at least search the shoreline for anything the attackers left behind." "You're sure?" "I'm the only one that can usefully do so right now. Could be something they left that'll be washed away by dawn." Though Belegar doesn't press the issue, he does assign a few of his Hammerers to go with you. In case any of the ambushers are still out there, he says. You don't try to argue. You think you're still more or less okay, but if you're wrong, you'd much rather be carried back than pass out in the river mud. --- To the eyes, the banks of the river are an indistinguishable mess of mud and tangled vegetation in the moonlight. Magesight makes it much easier to pick out the details, as the vegetation thrums with Ghyran while the mud only glows faintly with it. Picking out something out of place is as easy as looking for the inert silhouette amongst a background of jade. This strategy quickly pays off, as not far behind the sunken ship you find a length of thick rope leading into the water. It has a series of knots tied at regular intervals towards the end, and judging by the marks in the mud the current has been tugging at it insistently. The Skull River will have to go without this piece of detritus. With the help of the Hammerers you overcome the weight of water and mud and reel it in. It ends abruptly, and after wiping the mud off the end you frown at it. It's heavily frayed and feels stiff to the touch, more so than the fibers in the rest of the rope. So you suspect this was used to hold the explosive in place while the ambushers waited for their prey. You don't see any Aqshy. So no Bright Magic was involved in the explosion, and this confirms the reports that it happened under the waterline. If either or both of those were the case, the Aqshy in the explosion - either directly from a magical component, or drawn in by the moment of detonation - would have been embedded in the rope with such force that it would take days or weeks for it to fade. It doesn't take long to find what you expected to on the other side of the river - another length of rope tied to a gnarled tree. Pulling that up as well reveals similar fraying and singeing to the other end, and an identical lack of Aqshy. So they use the tree as an anchor and hold the rope at the other end. The explosive charge is either weighted or heavy enough to sink on its own, but not all the way to the bottom because it's being held in place. The first ship in the Okral's convoy arrives, and... it explodes. Somehow. Set off by the musket fire? No, it exploded below water. By a pull on the rope? Too easy for it to have been set off by the pull of the river. On impact? That has possibilities. You've read books on Dwarven chemistry that mentioned chemicals that could be ignited by impact or by mixing them with other chemicals or even on contact with water. But while anyone with gold can get their hands on a barrel of gunpowder, those chemicals are significantly more exotic, with much fewer sources... You shake your head. Speculate when you've exhausted the available evidence, not before. The explosion happened underwater, that means the explosive was either weighted or heavy enough to sink on its own, which means the weight or the remains of that explosive would have sunk to the bottom of the river. You commandeer one of the rowboats from the beached monitors and have the Hammerers row you out to a point between the two ropes and secure the boat in place by tying it to the shade cloth still suspended above the river. Substance of Shadow served well before, but that was when you were moving through a ship full of air pockets. To search the riverbed you'll need to come up to the surface for air, and that would risk coming up outside of any cast shade and then having the moonlight dispel the effect and suddenly finding your body existing in the same place as the river water. But unlike the boat, your only obstacle here is the water and the fish. With a summoned knife you prick your finger and allow a drop to fall into the river, and after a moment you activate your Robes and dip your hand in after it. The blood has already attracted the attention of several fish and it takes only a few seconds for you to feel the slight pressure of powerful jaws closing on even more powerful Aethyric Armour, and then blood blooms in the river as the Rune on your belt returns the chomp twofold to the fish. You withdraw your hand, double-check that it's unmarked, and then take a breath, summon Branulhune, and jump over the side. Of all the possible uses for a runic gromril greatsword made by one of the greatest Runelords in the Karaz Ankor, being a sinker is a particularly humble one, but it serves as admirably in that role as it has in every other you have put it to. The weight of the star-metal pulls you straight downwards as you do your best to ignore the bolder fish attempting to make a snack of you and being immediately punished for it. The river water around you is still flowing and vibrant with Ghyran, but that just makes it easier to pick out what doesn't belong. Over the course of several dives you retrieve several fragments of metal, and when your lungs start to ache you dismiss Branulhune - which disappears with an odd flash of light that it's never displayed before, which is a puzzle for later - and allow the buoyancy of your still-full lungs to bring you back to the surface. When you're unable to find more, you have the boat return to shore, and you spend some time drying out as best you can at the fires that were built for the Dwarves you rescued. When your teeth are no longer chattering, you confer with Belegar and Gotri. "Steel," Gotri is saying, "not the worst I've seen, but definitely not Dwarven. If I had to guess, I'd say Tilean or Imperial." "They're all curved back on each other," Belegar observes. "Every one." "Hoops," you say, "around an exploding barrel." Gotri turns the fragment over in his hands. "That would cause these stress patterns," he concedes. "Barrel full of gunpowder - or something else - hanging from a rope, one end of the rope tied to a tree, the other held by the ambushers. It's heavy enough to sink and it's held below the waterline, either to avoid the monitor's armour or to prevent it being seen or both. If they had a particular target in mind they could give it enough slack for the barrel to sink to the bottom and allow non-targets to pass by unharmed. When this monitor arrives, it hits the barrel and it explodes. Don't know the exact mechanism." "I could think of a few ways to do it," Gotri says after a moment, "but it would require very careful manufacturing, and not minding terribly much if it explodes prematurely." "It could also be done with magic, and I suspect chemistry. But even if you combine all three possible triggers, that narrows it down a lot more than just a barrel of gunpowder." You turn the steel over and over in your hands. "I might be able to find out more back in Karak Eight Peaks. And if Barak Varr can find the slugs shot at the ship, I could get something out of that too." "I'll see to it," Belegar says. --- Dawn arrives without further complication, and everyone present breaths a sigh of relief as a deep, reverberating horn signals the arrival of Barak Varr's reinforcements. Like an outraged goose rushing to the protection of its goslings, the Karaz Ankor's only riverine ironclad rushes upriver bristling with both guns and with heavily armed Dwarves, and leading a convoy of smaller but equally battle-ready monitors. It pauses only long enough to disgorge a King, several Guildmasters, and a small army to begin taking control of the situation, then turns its attention to the stricken ship. How long does it take to divert a river? Months? Years? Decades? You don't know. But you now know how long it takes to divert half a river, at least if you're Barak Varr: about a couple of hours. With extremely precise driving it lines itself up so that its bow is almost touching that of the sunken ship and its stern is on the verge of running aground, and somewhere inside the massive vessel, a certain series of valves that are very rarely turned are turned, and water floods in. With an almost stately grace it settles lower and lower in the water until it touches the river bottom, its top decks still well clear of the surface. The water level on one side of the wreck begins to sink as it rises on the other, and working with coordinated grace, hundreds of Dwarves begin to fill and stack sandbags to further increase the discrepancy. By the time the first hour is over the top of the wreck is piled high with sandbags to keep all the water on one side and not the other, the river has receded enough on the dry side for some wary Dwarves to start bludgeoning beached fish, and water from inside the ship has begun to pour over the massive hole in its front. By the second, the first new survivor emerges, blinking in the light as they're lead to warmth and care. You'd like to bask in that moment, but like two Kings and more Engineers than you can count, all your attention is fixed on the hole that sunk the ship. "Dead center of the bottom corridor," says the Grandmaster of Barak Varr's Slotchokri, the Riverine Shipwrights, speaking loudly to be heard over the rushing of the nearby river. "And the blast radius was large enough to partially open up the corridor above and the compartment below. They couldn't have found a more crippling shot if they tried." "We see this sometimes, from-" a moment of hesitation from the Grandmaster of Barak Varr's Skarrenokri, the Oceanic Shipwrights. You turn to him, and find his eyes on you. "She knows," Belegar grunts. "The Frurndar have weapons that strike below the waterline. We've begun armouring against it, but..." He shrugs. "You can only put so much weight on a ship. More steel below the waterline means less above it. The Slotchokri were thought to never need to protect against more than an errant boulder." "We'll explore whether that was in error later," King Byrrnoth says. "Focus on this." "A barrel of an explosive substance was held in place by rope," Gotri says. "One side tied to a tree, the other held. The ship hits the barrel, the barrel explodes. Possibly some sort of impact trigger mechanism." "Gunpowder?" One Engineer says. "Must have been a hell of a lot of it for a hole that big," says another. "I'll be able to say how big the barrel was as soon as I get the metal back to my workshop," you say. "From there you should be able to determine whether it was gunpowder or something..." Your voice trails off as you stare at the jagged edge of the hole. "Something what?" says one of the Engineers, but you're already halfway up a ladder against the side of the hole. The last trickles of bloody water have just finished emerging from the frontal compartment, and without that steady stream of Shyish you think you can see a trace of something, something that fire and water haven't quite washed away. Embedded in the steel here and there are what you'd call splinters if they weren't so pulverized. Magically speaking, many types of live wood are very mutable and can absorb just about any magical energy that it finds itself surrounded by, for better or worse. Dead wood retains these properties to an extent, so prolonged exposure can leave a mark. You wouldn't be surprised to see Ghyran from the river or Shyish from the dead Dwarves in the pulp, but you're not seeing that. Lurking inside the wood pulp is the very faintest touch of Dhar. "Traces of Dark Magic," you say. "Not from the trigger mechanism, a Dhar trigger wouldn't have lasted long enough for the wood to absorb it. It's from the explosive substance. And I only know of one explosive substance that would radiate Dhar." "Skaven blackpowder," Belegar says, and you nod. The atmosphere wasn't exactly jovial before, but it darkens even further as hands tighten on weapons. --- There's still a great deal of work to be done, from tending to the most badly in need of it to the recovery and standing vigil over the corpses of the fallen to the refloating of the stricken ship for it to be towed back to Barak Varr and restored. But your work here is done. You'd intended to discuss the matter further with Belegar and the others in the Gyrocarriage, but as soon as you sit down and are enfolded in the now-familiar thrum of the engines you find your eyes closing of their own accord, even as Dreng begins to launch into an extended grumble over not finding anything useful. It's been a very long day, and there'll be time for talking later. - Start of the new turn to come shortly. - Rolls were made for what you were able to find, but were not displayed to avoid giving OOC information. Mathilde does not know if what she found is all there was to find.

Turn 33 - 2486 - Karag Dum, We Are Coming

Spoiler: Voting results [x] [TOWER] Greenhouse [*] [LIBRARY] Chaos Dwarves: Extensive Imperial + Extensive and Esoteric Dwarven (300gc + 4DF), Chaos Sorcery: Extensive Imperial + Extensive Dwarven (200gc), Hobgoblin Khanates: Extensive Imperial + Extensive Dwarven (200gc) [*] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [*] [DWARF] No purchase. [*] [PURCHASE] No purchase. Unfortunately, you don't have the privilege of seeing the Council react to your new promotion. Among Dwarves the news of such things spread quietly behind the scenes so nobody inadvertently gives offence by addressing a newly-promoted craftsman by their former title, and everyone transitions seamlessly to referring to you by your new title, or at least various attempts at it. Khazalid doesn't have established labels for Wizards - not complimentary ones, anyway - so you find yourself referred to as everything from the relatively brief Dalokri to the intimidating mouthful Dalmhornzhufokralaki, which isn't precisely correct but you take the compliment in the spirit that was intended. The beginning of the Council meeting is dedicated to touring the work of the Okral, which you suspect is being treated with a great deal more respect than would have been the case if their trip home had been uneventful. Karags Rhyn and Mhonar have been restored and dedicated to Valaya and Smednir respectively, and most of the Clans of Karak Eight Peaks are moving into them from Karag Lhune. It's far from necessary as Karag Lhune would only begin to approach cramped if every Dwarf, Halfling, and human in the Karak decided to live there, but it does mean that five of the Eight Peaks are at least partially populated. It's never a good idea to leave a vacuum in the mountains for too long, as there's a great deal of hostile beings that will eagerly fill it if given half a chance. Besides, the smelters and forges that have been established in Karag Mhonar are a big step on the way to the Karak being self-sufficient. Also toured are the exterior Sentinels and Morzund's Wall, a series of walls and watchtowers that keep a wary eye on the gaps between the southern Karags where the terrain isn't quite difficult enough to fully dissuade a determined attacker on its own. The Western Gates are the final stop and certainly impress, as the towering stone edifice looks forbidding enough even before you factor in the cannon that line the battlements. Not toured, but definitely important, was the great deal of work put in to the tunnels below the Karak, mapping their extent, exterminating anything left in there that shouldn't be, and collapsing, filling, and barricading until what was left presented as defensable and patrollable an underground perimeter as possible. "Time for settling in properly," Belegar says as you all make your way back from the Western Gates. "No doubt there'll be some sort of teething troubles as entire Clans move in to what will hopefully be their homes for the rest of time." Belegar grimaces. "I'd planned a celebration, but with the attack on the Okral it seems like it would be in poor taste. And speaking of which," he nods to you, "anything you can uncover before it's time for your Expedition will be of great help." "I wish the timing was better," you say with a frown. "The attack, matters with Marienburg... I worry I'm going to come back to a war." "If we waited for good times to get things done, we'd never do them," Belegar says, to nods of agreement from the other Dwarves. "Karag Dum called for help a hundred and eighty-five years ago, it's about time somebody answered." Mandatory Actions: Pick one from each category. Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his metalworking studies. [ ] MAX: Have him scour all the reference materials at his disposal for any other Dhar-radiating explosive, as well as how difficult it might be for non-Skaven to replicate their blackpowder. (NEW) [ ] MAX: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. [ ] MAX: Have him train Hubert (optional: specify in what) [ ] MAX: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Write a paper: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which. Must be taken with a 'dictate' action. Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Have him continue to teach Adela what he knows of engineering. [ ] JOHANN: Have him investigate the metal evidence taken from the Skull River ambush. (NEW) [ ] JOHANN: Allow him to spend all his time on his own preparations. [ ] JOHANN: Have him train Hubert (optional: specify in what) [ ] JOHANN: Learn a skill: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Learn a spell: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. Wizards of Karak Eight Peaks [ ] DUCK: Work with Panoramia to try to implement the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. [ ] DUCK: Panoramia's about ready to test for Magister, but she's putting it off because she doesn't have a lot of free time to prepare. Work with her to help make the most of every spare minute. [ ] DUCK: Aid Hubert in his search for a Familiar. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Gretel and the Besiegers for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Attempt to recruit Adela and some human siege weapons and operators for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Recruit Gretel and Adela for the Karag Dum Expedition. [ ] DUCK: Each of your three ducklings can fight in melee. Spar with them, and teach them what you can. [ ] DUCK: Study an artefact with one of the Journeymen: specify who and which. The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 175 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Expansion along the Aver EIC Handler: The Hochlander [ ] EIC: Completely and over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. Will remove this section from future turns and regain the half-turn invested in it. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in the Sunken Palace. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander set up a shadow headquarters for the EIC in your fief. [ ] EIC: Have the Hochlander investigate how feasible it would be for a non-Skaven to acquire warpstone-enhanced blackpowder. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Suggest Eike spend a few weeks in Karak Eight Peaks, so she can grow familiar with Dwarves and their ways. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Julia to find out if she's interested in being poached or passing on information. [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. [ ] EIC: Improve the EIC's paramilitary river navy. [ ] EIC: Sell some of the Grand Urbaz Bank coins to collectors and museums on King Belegar's behalf. [ ] EIC: Have a blackpowder factory built in Wurtbad. (NEW) [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. Personal Actions: you have TWO actions you can apply without engaging in overwork. Current overwork status: [+] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. Current Task: Karag Dum Expedition preparations [ ] Join the Karag Dum Expedition in Praag, rather than at High Pass. (NEW) [ ] Seek out merchants who have travelled the Skull Road to learn what they know of it. [ ] Trawl around the bars and brothels of Tilea, looking to talk to the actual mercenaries that have walked either the Skull Road, or the Great Steppes. [ ] Attempt to recruit assistance for the Karag Dum Expedition. (specify the individual, mercenary group, cult, College, or other; two choices per AP spent) [ ] With the help of a gyrocarriage, personally scout part of the route (specify: High Pass, Road of Skulls, Western Great Steppes, Karag Dum vicinity) [ ] Attempt to learn the Greenskin tongue to communicate with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Attempt to learn Kurgan to communicate with the Kurgan of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Hobgoblin Khanates of the Steppes. [ ] Learn what you can of dealing with the Kurgan of the Steppes. Spoiler: Qrech Qrech [ ] Despite him considering it treasonous, push Qrech to share the Moulder dialect of Queekish. [ ] Despite him considering it blasphemous, push Qrech to share High Queekish. Qrech Gambits (can be taken for free alongside a Qrech option): [ ] Convince Qrech that you seek an arrangement with Clan Moulder, and that you will release him as an ambassador for that arrangement once you are satisfied he'll cooperate. [ ] Convince Qrech that the Under-Empire has no way of knowing he's even alive, and that he should prioritize the comfort with which he will live the rest of his life. [ ] Convince Qrech you're ambitious and loyal only to yourself, and you're willing to repay his cooperation in ways that will benefit the Under-Empire. [ ] Other (write in) Self-Improvement: [ ] Ask an acquaintance to train you in a skill: specify who and what. [ ] Attempt to learn a spell from scrolls (specify which, will be harder than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Hire a trainer to come to Eight Peaks and teach you: specify what. (costs favours for Dwarf or College trainers, money for human ones) [ ] Travel to the Grey College and attend lessons there. (1 College Favour per class; 100gc can be paid instead for non-magical classes) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Gain enough control of your unruly shadow to still it temporarily. [ ] Gain enough control of your attraction to smoke and gases to have it collect away from your face. [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. (NEW-ish) [ ] Have one of Prince Gotri's pilots teach you to fly a gyrocopter. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] Dictate papers: select which two, must be taken with Max's 'receive dictation'. [ ] Investigate the possibility of using one Wind to directly manipulate another. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. [ ] Try to establish a relationship with the Cult of Verena, with the intent of offering them access to your rarer tomes in exchange for copies of some of their own. Aethyric Vitae (13 gallons): [ ] Experiment with integrating the Vitae into enchantments. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts with Divine Magic. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to a power stone. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item with a Fiendishly Complex or easier spell (specify what and which) [ ] Attempt to enchant an object to translate Windsight into a visual image. [ ] Attempt to deepen your skill with Enchantment (will be more difficult than studying it at the Grey College) [ ] Attempt to complete your 'Fog Path' spell (NEW-ish) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff from mundane materials. [ ] Turn a staff from the horn of a Storm Dragon. Karag Nar Penthouse: each turn, you get ONE free choice in this category. Additional selections cost actions. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have a tower built atop Karag Nar: -100gc for 1 room, bonus to room's purpose. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have additional rooms excavated underneath your Penthouse: -150gc for 6 rooms. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add security measures to your Penthouse to prevent forcible entry. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Have firing platforms built around the Penthouse so that it can be defended from flyers or climbers without granting access to it. [ ] PENTHOUSE: Add preservation Runes to your library: -4 Dwarf Favour, can be paid for with book budget DF for next two purchase periods. [ ] PENTHOUSE: No additional construction. Setting up rooms for specific purposes will have to wait until new rooms are constructed or excavated. Only one construction or excavation can take place at a time, but you can do one of each. Building downwards will increase by 1 each time; second set of excavated rooms will be 3 rooms, third will be 4, and so on. Building upwards can be added upon; towers can be added on to or additional towers can be built. The distinction between the two is entirely cosmetic. Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in the Sylvanian campaign (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Marienburg affair (specify how) [ ] Involve yourself in the Black Waters project (specify how) Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting with a fellow councillor's task: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (FRESH) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition. (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual. (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae. (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a two hour moratorium - This turn has two less personal actions and no Serenity action, due to Mathilde leaving for the Karag Dum Expedition partway through it. - If the Coin is set to the Protector, it will cover the actions Mathilde undertook during the Ambush on Skull River. - For this turn and this turn only, I am allowing a conditional in the form of 'if we fail to complete X, use overwork to try again'. - Any negative effects from Overwork taken during this turn will not begin until next turn. - This concludes my three-month rendition of Immigrant Song in the threadmark names. Spoiler: Word Nerding Let's conjugate 'ok': Ok - cunning or skilfull Okri - Craftsman Okrak - the craft itself Okrul - craftsmanship Okral - Group of craftsman, Guild (informal) Okralaz - Guild (formal, usually only applied to respected Dwarven Guilds) Okrali - Guild member in good standing Okrit - Apprentice Okreni - Journeyman Okrari - Master ('Okri' is often used instead, 'Okrari' is only needed when specifically referring to the rank) Dalokri - Grandmaster (informal) Dalokruli - Grandmaster (formal) Dalokrali - Grandmaster in good standing with a guild Dalokraki - Grandmaster of exceptional skill Dalokralaki - Foremost Grandmaster in a specific guild Dalokralazi - Leader of a specific guild Dalokraz - something very well-made Dalokrulaz - something made by a Grandmaster Dalokrulakaz - greatest pinnacle of a particular craft in the current era Dalokralakaz - most impressive work created by a specific guild in the current era Dalokrulakaz-ha - greatest pinnacle of a particular craft era, usually reserved for the works of the Ancestor Gods Dalokrulakazi-ha - greatest ever craftsman of their type, usually reserved for the Ancestor Gods. Words to specify the specific craft go before the 'ok'. Eg: Grungokri = miner, wutokri = carpenter, zhufokri = Wizard, mhornzhufokri = Grey Wizard. Dalmhornzhufokralaki = Foremost Grey Wizard Lord of their Guild, applied to Mathilde due to a lack of understanding of the internal structure of the Colleges and how the K8P Wizards fit into them.

Turn 33 Results - 2486 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan: SQUEAK, Panoramia variant -[*] MAX: Have him scour all the reference materials at his disposal for any other Dhar-radiating explosive, as well as how difficult it might be for non-Skaven to replicate their blackpowder. (NEW) -[*] JOHANN: Have him investigate the metal evidence taken from the Skull River ambush. (NEW) -[*] DUCK: Work with Panoramia to try to implement the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms as an aid to spellcasting. -[*] EIC: Have the Hochlander investigate how feasible it would be for a non-Skaven to acquire warpstone-enhanced blackpowder. (NEW) -[*] Attempt to complete your 'Fog Path' spell (NEW-ish) -- [*] Use overwork if necessary -[*] Join the Karag Dum Expedition in Praag, rather than at High Pass. -[*] PENTHOUSE: Add security measures to your Penthouse to prevent forcible entry. -[*] The Protector Max and Johann are pulled from their own preparations for the upcoming Expedition to aid you with your investigation into the attack on the Okral. Max is sent to investigate the possibly too-easy answer of 'Skaven did it' while Johann is turned loose on the metal fragments recovered from the ambush site: the fragments of barrel hooping and a single metal slug extracted from the ship's upper deck. Modest evidence, but hopefully enough for him to be able to pull information from. Barak Varr and Karaz-a-Karak are both performing their own investigations, including the former hiring a Jade Wizard to interrogate the river and trees, so hopefully between the three different avenues of investigation the truth of the matter can be uncovered. It's actually something of a relief that those parallel investigations preclude you from performing your own. The Fog Path spell is tantalizingly close to being completed and you very much want that arrow in your quiver before joining the Expedition. You have the individual Skywalks, you have the mechanism for identifying where they're needed. All that's left is the overarching delivery mechanism to go from you to the path to be travelled. You spend some time considering a shadow-based delivery mechanism, since you've found so much success with Burning Shadows and Substance of Shadows, and after all 'Fog Path' is just a working title. But for something intended to be used on the move, having to control local light levels to properly use it would be too big a handicap. So you instead turn your attention to Universal Confusion, which hasn't seen any real use since you learned it almost five years ago but did manifest quite promisingly as a billowing cloud from its interaction with your Mantle of Mist Arcane Mark. That has quite a pleasing mental image to it - a rolling carpet of fog emanating from your person and covering the landscape ahead. You dig out your notes from when you learned it and get to work. [Fog Path delivery mechanism: Learning, 2+28+5(Library: Ulgu)=35.] It does not go well. You'd thought it would serve perfectly well as a delivery mechanism. It covers the ground in a near-uniform carpet of opaque fog and hides obstacles from the eyes, so why not hide obstacles from the legs too? But though it's trivial for you to billow out fog, controlling its flow and weaving a spell into it proves to be as frustrating as... well, as frustrating as trying to herd fog would be to someone who isn't a Grey Wizard. [Attempt to work around it: Learning, 69+28+5(Library: Ulgu)=102.] A more dramatic person would have dramatically crossed out all the accumulated notes on your chalkboard. You are more sensible and simply move to the next one, as you might still need to refer to those notes later. But you have been looking at it all wrong. You've gotten hung up on using fog as a mechanism. No wonder you're getting nowhere. Fog isn't a mechanism, it's a medium. (Okay, you're compelled to admit that fog might still be used as a mechanism, but you've hit a wall on that front so for now you're disregarding the possibility altogether.) So step one, emit and corral the fog to where it needs to be, step two, have the delivery mechanism flow through it. Doing two moderately difficult things versus doing one slightly more difficult thing... probably isn't a great trade-off, but it's better than failing entirely. Days turn to weeks as you map out this alternate path, and eventually you're left with all your notes properly transcribed into a notebook and with nothing left to do but to take it for a ride and see what happens. [New delivery mechanism: Learning, 45+28+5(Library: Ulgu)=78.] [Putting it all together: Learning, 19+28+20(Grey Tower)+5(Library: Ulgu)=72. [First cast: Req 50, Learning, 31+28+20(Grey Tower)-20(first time)=59.] The inside of your Room of Dawn and Dusk isn't typical casting conditions, but you're glad you opted to do it there rather than anywhere else. As roiling fog fills the room and the identifier flows unsteadily through it, looking in vain for any interruptions in the smooth floor below you, you exhale shakily and let the spell dissipate. If you had done it in less ideal conditions, or if you didn't have your Staff to make channeling the fog that much easier, that spell would definitely have ripped itself out of your control. You now know the final few pieces to make it more reliable, and over the coming days you test it in a variety of conditions. It's... not bad. Not great, but not bad. If you stuck to the few hours around dawn and dusk, you could probably maintain the spell for three or four hours a day without pushing yourself, as many as six if the weather cooperates. That's certainly a lot better than nothing, but is it enough? You know you're capable of better, but as you eye the calendar, you're not certain if you can do better before it's time to leave. And it would mean a lot of late nights and early mornings to even try. [ ] Push on and try to improve the spell Use overwork to spend another action to try to create a better delivery mechanism for the spell. [ ] It's good enough for now It will be possible to try to improve the spell further after returning from the Expedition. --- Johann has been buried in maps and frequently absent as he tries to nail down specifics. Tale of Metal is a very useful spell, but as he frequently complains, people are rarely considerate enough to mention their name and precise location while crafting. The barrel hoops prove especially frustrating as the cooper neglected to even open a window in his workshop, leaving Johann to spend fruitless weeks trying to narrow down a location based off the colour of the wood and trying to identify an accent in the cooper's mutterings. In desperation he turned away from the cooper and towards the steel itself, and though he remains tight-lipped about this stage of the investigation, he comes out of it claiming with complete confidence that the steel was smelted in Morlenfurt, a Reikland town on the foothills of the Grey Mountains. He also gives you the dimensions of the barrel in question which matches that of a hogshead. The lead ball that was shot at the ship takes him on an equally frustrating journey. Cheap shot of questionable quality is still made with molten lead poured into moulds of metal or sand, but the modern method is to use shot towers, where precise amounts of molten lead are allowed to fall a great height and naturally form a round drop before plunging into water and being near-instantly quenched. While a triumph of modern engineering, this also means that the 'creation' process lasts only a few seconds and is contained within a featureless tower, though thankfully there are enough windows for ventilation that he is able to get the lay of the land around it, one glimpse at a time. There's only so many shot towers in the Empire and each is known to its administrative apparatus so that if necessary they can be pressed into service of the Empire's military, so while the task is a tedious one, it's also a finite one. He eventually finds the shot tower that matches the one that he saw: Kreutzhofen of southwest Wissenland, the crossroads of the Vaults, which stands at the intersection of passes leading to Tilea, Bretonnia, and the Border Princes. For his part, Max has spent weeks buried in your library surrounded by ramparts of books on engineering, chemistry, and warpstone. He complains at length that it would have been a matter of minutes instead of weeks if you had Skaven-authored books on chemistry, but does concede that the Skaven-authored books you do have are all that makes it possible to reach an answer without flagrant breaches of the Articles. "It's a matter of conditions," he says, leafing through his notes. "You know the Colleges, 'assume a perfectly spherical ball of Chamon in a magically inert plain' and all that. Skaven engineering doesn't work that way, at least not the stuff that ends up widely used. They assume that their equipment is going to be poorly maintained and stored in the damp by incompetents before it's dragged onto a battlefield, and often intersperse their notes with extended rants on the subject. That's what the warpstone is for. When used with a warplock trigger mechanism it makes for a much more reliable means of ignition than a snaphance or a flintlock, and even with mundane mechanisms, finely-ground warpstone is ignitable, and detonates hard. So if the blackpowder is damp it still works as long as any of it is dry enough to ignite, because that sets off the warpstone which forces even wet powder to ignite, and makes it go off all at once instead of in a wave. So for a relatively small amount of warpstone, you get a more reliable ignition and a more efficient explosion than blackpowder on its own." "How easy is it to create?" "Depends how much you care about others. The Skaven have a process to make it much less radiant and therefore more efficient as well as safer to handle and use, but if you don't care about that you can just use the raw stuff. Grinding and mixing it would do terrible things to whoever does it, and you wouldn't want to be downwind of it when it ignites, but it could be done. The only tricky bit would be getting the warpstone in the first place." You grimace. "Any way to tell if the explosion used refined warpstone or raw?" "Not unless you were there to see it." "Damn. You turn up any other type of explosive that would radiate Dhar?" He shrugs. "Nothing solid. There's accounts of various Chaos Dwarf weapons that would radiate all kinds of malign energies, but they tend to have more exotic effects than just exploding. The Zombie Pirates of the Vampire Coast are said to use some sort of altered gunpowder, and I could easily see it having some sort of necromantic component that would radiate Dhar. Cathay are said to use both Dark Magic and blackpowder." "The list of possible suspects is long enough without venturing outside the Old World. Johann says the barrel was a hogshead, does that fit the results?" He drums his fingers. "It's all variables. I have a decent idea about what sort of steel the monitor would have been made out of, but not the thickness or the design. How tight was the barrel bound? How much pressure did the depth of the water exert? How close was the barrel to the hull when it exploded? But with all that said... yes. It would fit." "It matches logistically too. It'd be unwieldy to carry, but easy enough to move around with a rowboat or a cart or even a wheelbarrow. Good work, Max." He smiles and goes about clearing up his work area. The final stop on this tour is with the Hochlander's reports. Warpstone, or wyrdstone as it is known to the ignorant, is highly illegal to trade in but very profitable to those willing to take the risk, as the gullible believe it to have all sorts of mystical properties, and those that know more than they should can use it to power all sorts of forbidden magics. The Hochlander's first step was confirming that that's just as true as ever and indeed it is, and he leaves a trail of burning pyres as his Witch Hunter contacts follow in his wake. The second step is to investigate the cottage industries of the Empire, where second-rate blackpowder is made to a thousand different recipes which often owe more to guesswork and superstition than chemistry. He comes out of it with a frankly terrifying list of additives that might grace the weapon of anyone who cheaps out on blackpowder, and though some are of dubious legality and one or two result in still more pyres, none seem to have hit on ground wyrdstone as an additive. The third step is the most dubious and requires reading the Hochlander in on the Conspiracy of Silence: see if any can be acquired more directly. There's ample evidence that some humans are in league with the Skaven as Cults worshipping the Horned Rat crop up from time to time and need to be burned out. Considering the ambition and duplicity that Skaven are capable of, and, admittedly, the ambition and duplicity that humans are capable of, it's not all that outrageous to think that there might be some crossover between the black markets of the Empire and the black markets of the Under-Empire. This comes up bust, though the Hochlander does make some new friends among Witch Hunters, Excisemen, and one of Algard's Hands from encounters where both tried to bait the other into admitting something incriminating - good thing you made sure he has all the right documentation to prove that he really is acting on official orders. Either the theoretical black market crossover is even better hidden than you thought or it doesn't exist. But he does find something in parts of Reikland - blackpowder circulating among criminal organizations, said to be more reliable and produce a harder-hitting shot than regular blackpowder. His investigation is unable to find exactly who the ultimate supplier is, but all the trails seem to point in the direction of Ubersreik, where the Skaven undercity was recently exterminated. Not quite collusion with the Under-Empire, then. Just ordinary corruption. You make sure to pass the information on to where it needs to go to begin a formal investigation and sit back to collate your information. So. One hogshead of what was very likely warpstone-infused gunpowder. Its source could be Ubersreik, or it could be made by someone with knowledge enough of the Skaven to replicate their gunpowder and the contacts and wealth to acquire wyrdstone enough for a hogshead worth. The barrel was hooped with Morlenfurt steel, which is just north of Ubersreik, and the bullets of the ambushers came from Kreutzhofen. Probably not Skaven, then. Someone of a mind to suspect Marienburg could draw a line directly south from Marienburg to Ubersreik for the powder, to Kreutzhofen for the equipment, to the Border Princes for the lackeys, and then to the Skull River for the ambush. Someone of a mind to clear Marienburg could quite reasonably point out that anyone in or around the Empire with money and contacts could have made this happen. You look over your notes one last time, and consider what you're going to tell Belegar, and what he will go on to tell King Byrrnoth and High King Thorgrim. [ ] The evidence points to Skaven Warpstone-infused gunpowder. It's open and shut. The Karaz Ankor doesn't need new enemies. [ ] The evidence does not point to Skaven The Dwarves could easily overlook the actual culprit if they're too caught up on their ancestral foe. [ ] The evidence points to Marienburg It could be true, and the Empire could benefit if it becomes believed that Marienburg is committing murder with dark magic. [ ] The evidence points to a framejob Somebody is trying to drive the Dwarves into war with Marienburg. Nobody wins when the forces of Order fight amongst themselves. [ ] The evidence is inconclusive It could be anyone. It could even still be the Skaven. Nothing you've learned rules out anyone. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - There were rolls for the investigations, but they were hidden because Mathilde doesn't know for sure whether these results are all there is to find or not. - It is valid to vote based on the result you want your words to have, rather than what you think the evidence reflects. - The volume of the barrel in question is about 54 imperial gallons, 65 US gallons, or 250 liters. - You have not yet used any overwork this turn. This vote is for the second box of overwork, which will give a -10 penalty to actions next turn. - Reminder: penalties from taking overwork now will not kick in until after the Expedition.

Turn 33 Results - 2486 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Push on and try to improve the spell [*] The evidence points to a framejob With the date to set out drawing closer and closer, you return to the drawing board - metaphorically speaking, since you're neither a barbarian nor an artist, you use a proper drafting machine - and begin to work longer into the nights to refine the delivery mechanism for Fog Path. What you've created so far is certainly functional, but it's also exhausting and would be highly reliant on spikes of ambient Ulgu at dawn and dusk to function for extended periods. There are parts of the initial attempt that can be salvaged, but it's going to take some creativity. [Fog Path delivery mechanism, round two: Learning, 91+28+10(learning from mistakes)+5(Library: Ulgu)=134.] The problem is simple: you're being too literal. You're allowing the spell to billow out from you and then dissipate, which is certainly thematic but hugely wasteful. Even in the roughest terrain, there'll be individual instances of Skywalk that are unnecessary, and allowing them to disappear and take the energy with them is pure folly. You need a way to draw back and reuse them. And rather than reinventing the wheel, you'll draw from nature. Specifically, the motion of waves on a beach. Granted, you've never actually been to a beach - the closest you've been to the ocean is Barak Varr, which is all forbidding cliffs - but a close search of your library uncovers a number of Dwarf-written books that describe the formation and motion of waves, albeit in the way that one describes the habits of a dangerous and implacable foe, as you suppose saltwater in eternal motion must represent to a number of Dwarven endeavours. You consider and discard the ubiquitous undertow, as it would create too much turbulence at ground level where the individual spells are supposed to be activating. What you need is a rip current: a central column of returning energy that can then be sent out again, over and over until each part of it reaches a place where it is needed. This means that the only constant draw on the caster will be to provide enough motion to keep the spell going. This could come with its own challenges, as instead of a constant and steady outpouring of new Skywalk instances, the caster needs to provide more only as they are needed. But instead of getting caught up in the design of a feedback mechanism you decide to take what you have now into a field experiment. It's entirely possible that the spell as it exists now would have cues for a watchful Wizard to spot when it's running low, and implementing something separate would be wasted effort. So you go over your notes one more time and then adjourn to the Grey Tower for testing. [First cast: Req 50, Learning, 29+28+20(Grey Tower)-20(first time)=57.] Once more you're surrounded in a cloud of turbulent fog as you barely manage to finish the spell, and once more you consider yourself quite lucky to have both a staff and a testing chamber perfectly suited for this activity. The first time casting a new spell is always troublesome, but it sure beats the Elven method where a spell candidate is meditated on for decades to study it for any possible flaw. You make the requisite corrections to your casting notes, perform the spell a few more times in perfect conditions to be sure, then you move onto stage two of testing. --- "Go!" Under the staring eyes of a still-growing crowd of Halflings, Johann begins to push the wheelbarrow with its cargo of Grey Wizard, his golden muscles allowing him to quickly accelerate through the billowing fog. The field in question is the most broken terrain anywhere in the Eastern Valley, having been harvested, ploughed in, left fallow, frozen, snowed on, thawed, and had the snowmelt carve furrows across it. Panoramia told you it's about to be ploughed once more so even if the spell fails you'll not be doing any lasting damage, but your confidence is rewarded as the wheel of the barrow glides over pits, rifts, and furrows. As your chanting continues - a simple mnemonic for the components of the modified Skywalk, but it sounds nice and mystical - Johann reaches a speed comparable to a galloping horse over terrain that it would be difficult to walk through. That's as good a confirmation as you're going to get, and you bang the side of the wheelbarrow to signal Johann to slow. Your audience doesn't know what to make of what they just saw, but they do know they were entertained by it, and to their polite applause you dismount your wheelbarrow and turn to look over the field. If there was no trace of your path that would be a sign that you were wasting power, but on the few flat stretches you can see the wheel marks and footprints you left in your wake, showing that the spell only activated when needed. And you could feel the spell thinning out as the amount of Skywalk instances circulating lessened, serving as a suitable indicator of when more needed to be added. You thank one Halfling for the use of her field, another for the use of his wheelbarrow, and Johann for the use of his muscles. This version of the spell is still too energy-intensive to be anything but Battle Magic, but the sustained energy requirements are reduced based on the terrain it encounters. If you're trying to drive over quicksand or something equally ill-advised you'd still be limited to a few hours at dawn and dusk, but for any more sensible terrain you should be able to manage it through the daylight hours and still be fresh enough that a good night's sleep will have you ready to begin again the next day. There's only one remaining component of the spell that requires work - its name. [ ] Spell name - write in --- You normally come to Belegar when you've got news to report, but with how sensitive the matter could turn out being, he comes to you - which allows you to set up a proper display of the evidence, including indications on a map where each piece was acquired and the relevant books on hand if he wants to drill deeper into any one component. "Steel from Reikland, ammunition from Wissenland, powder from Ancestors-know-where," he summarizes once you're done laying it out. "What do you read into it?" "My initial thought was that it indicates Marienburg. If you draw a line from Marienburg to Winter's Teeth Pass, you pass almost directly through sources for all three. If you're already primed to think of them - as anyone would be for an attack on the Skull River - it's a very easy conclusion to reach. But Marienburg isn't a continental power like the Empire or the Karaz Ankor, they're a maritime one. Their idea of a direct line circles around the Old World and drops agents off somewhere on the Black Gulf or the Lagoon of Tears, and there'd be an Estalian barrel and Tilean shot or something like that." "You think someone wants us to think of Marienburg?" "I don't think it's the Empire, and I don't think it's just my own allegiances talking. The Empire might hypothetically want to retake Westerland at some point, but not now, not when Stirland's occupied with Vampires, Wissenland is still licking its wounds after the attack on Under-Nuln, Ostland is dealing with Yhetees, and things between Middenland and Nordland are still tense. All they want now is for the blockade to be lifted. "If they wanted to force the issue, they've got the First Fleet in Altdorf and the Second Fleet in Nordland, they'd start attacking Norscan ships with the Second Fleet and make hue and cry to Kislev and Bretonnia when Marienburg refuses to lift the blockade and keeps the First Fleet from the battle." You phrase this as a hypothetical instead of the Chamberlain of the Seal's explicit idea, which makes it slightly less of a breaking of confidence. And besides, it's for the best of causes. "Marienburg has to be suffering from the blockade already, if they start losing business overseas as well they'd have to cave." "Who, then? Back to Skaven?" "It's certainly possible. Eshin were probably able to claim the credit for Mors being wiped out here, and this sort of thing would be within their usual practices. It could also be Naggaroth, they'd benefit more than anyone if the Karaz Ankor and Ulthuan go to war once more, and we know they've got contacts of some sort with the Skaven. And Chaos Cults are always a possibility. On top of that, if we consider that it might be an attempt to frame the Empire for attempting to frame Marienburg, that really opens up the suspect pool. Lahmian Vampires trying to take pressure off the Sylvanian holdouts, Chaos Dwarves trying to split the Karaz Ankor from its oldest ally, it could even be Marienburg - war between the Empire and the Karaz Ankor would definitely spike the canal project." Belegar sighs. "So you're telling me it could be anyone." "I'm telling you that I think someone's playing games. I think if the culprits get tracked down, they'll claim to have been put up to it by either Jan Jansen who wore silks and smelled of fish, or Max Mustermann who was munching on a sausage and had three feathers in his hat." Belegar frowns, stepping closer to run his fingers along the map of the Empire. "This all makes someone suspect either Marienburg or the Empire," he says slowly. "But if it was Marienburg, they wouldn't have sourced the materials like that - even if they wanted to frame the Empire, they'd find it much easier to get Empire-made materials from somewhere on a coast or a major river, not that far up obscure tributaries. And if it was the Empire, they would have used Marienburg shot and barrels." "That's my read." "So it was either an incompetent plotter - and while nobody is short of incompetent plotters, they wouldn't be used for something so important, so if it was it must have been an independent actor who thinks they're smarter than they are - or it's someone that wants the Karaz Ankor to be weakened by war." He sighs. "Sometimes I miss the days when the enemies were right on the other side of a barricade. Thank you for taking the time to look into this." You smile and give a short bow. "Of course." --- Your return to the matter of the Waaaghsoak Mushrooms is a perfect opportunity to show off your Green Tower to Panoramia, who nods along as you explain the different components of it but is obviously itching to be unleashed upon the planters you set up, which occupies her for the next several days. It's certainly pleasant to have her nearby while you work on other things, but once she considers herself satisfied with the conditions that your fruit-bearing saplings are growing in (which are now significantly larger and noticeably lusher) it's time to return to the matter at hand. The central planters are set up in such a way that they can be magically isolated from each other and magical energy can be channelled in from elsewhere in your growing cluster of towers. You set up five groups of growing fungi: Ghyran, Ulgu, Aqshy, Azyr, and a magically-neutral control group. Though Panoramia can't use magic to directly accelerate their growth, she's quickly able to identify near-ideal growing conditions and it only takes a few days for the first harvest. Careful examination within your White Tower confirms that they each possess only the Wind they were soaked in while growing, and careful experimentation reveals that once plucked their ability to absorb Winds decreases, making the danger of accidental contamination and creation of Dhar negligible if properly stored. With all that confirmed, there's nothing for it but to move on to actual testing of how useful a gutful of mushroom is. [Casting with fungal assistance: Learning, 78+28=106.] Yep, just as unpleasant to eat as you remembered. You grimace your way through chewing on it and wait for the odd sensation of magic being 'digested' - technically the mushroom being digested and the magic flowing into you as it becomes no longer able to cling to the substance of the mushroom. You run through a few spells and notice that you do have slightly less need to draw on ambient magical energy than normal, but it's far from a surge of power, and a surge of power is the sort of thing that the Goblins who originally grew these mushrooms would have been looking for. Panoramia tries reducing the mushroom to a powder to be mixed with water and drunk, but the drying of an Ulgu-rich mushroom causes the Ulgu to escape. The same proves true for the Aqshy and Ghyran mushrooms, but the Azyr ones retain their energy. You consider turning testing over to Hubert, but even if he hadn't already left with the Winter Wolves it probably wouldn't be a great idea. It's common knowledge that cooked mushrooms sit easier in the stomach than raw ones, so your hope is that the magic inside would be more easily unleashed as well. So you and Panoramia take advantage of an often underappreciated resource: the cooking skills of the Halflings, who turn out to know of more ways to prepare and preserve mushrooms than you could have begun to guess. Hluodwica appears to take the mushrooms as a personal challenge, and when unleashed upon the control group manage to find ways to perform the impossible: making the mushrooms not only palatable, but actually tasty. You turn the techniques that Hluodwica has created onto the Wind-rich mushrooms and are able to find ones that work for each of them: smoking for Aqshy, pickling for Ghyran, and for Ulgu, mincing, spicing, lightly cooking in butter, and being reduced to a paste that is placed inside a bite-sized pie. Careful study confirms that it still contains the magical energies, and further study confirms that it is delicious. The magic inside flows into you much faster, and while it's not really enough to tip the scales for someone at your level of spellcasting ability, it could make a significant difference to those not yet able to easily draw on large amounts of ambient Winds - which could be a very useful resource for Journeymen. You prepare a significant amount of the Azyr specimens for Hubert to use on the Expedition. [New papers available: Windsoak Mushrooms - Ulgu, Aqshy, Ghyran, Azyr.] Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The three with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] Panoramia (locked in) Expedition [ ] Greet and get to know the Wizards joining the Expedition as they arrive at Praag. [ ] Join Hubert and the Winter Wolves for the final leg of their journey to Praag. [ ] Join Esbern, Seija, and the Knights of Taal's Fury for the final leg of their journey to Praag. Fellow Wizards [ ] Gretel, who's apparently spending her newly-earned wealth to make herself at home. [ ] Adela, to see how her gradual nepotistic takeover of the Karag Nar Gunnery School is going. Karak Eight Peaks Notables [ ] Francesco Caravello, proud Viceroy of the Undumgi. [ ] Spend some time exploring the Karak now that everyone has spread out into their hopefully permanent Clan Halls. Foreign Relations [ ] Stirland, to see for yourself how the war against Sylvania is progressing. Friends Abroad [ ] Julia, to see what she has gotten up to as Stirland's most experienced spy master. [ ] The Dolgan, to get to know the people of the western Steppes who will hopefully be feeding the Expedition. Following Up [ ] The Amber College, to check in on the salamanders. [ ] The Gold College, to see what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Follow up on your donation of the Skaven organ-vat, and see what has been made of it. [ ] Pay a visit to your fief, to see if anything has changed. It probably hasn't. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Panoramia is a lock-in for this turn only. You're about to go voyaging into hell's front yard, if she wasn't a lock-in she'd be coming for your Initiated By Someone Else slot that would be there instead. - There'll be a run-down of all the practice and advancement people have made in their preparations for the Expedition separate to the social turn. - Other suggestions for social actions are welcome. - My current plan for the Expedition is that I'll be switching to a Karak Kadrin avatar for the duration of it, as they're the primary sponsors of it and as far as I'm aware there's no canonical Karag Dum flag or insignia. If anyone's feeling creative, a fan-created Karag Dum flag or insignia would fit much better.

Turn 33 Social - 2486 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Spell name - Rite of Way [*] Greet and get to know the Wizards joining the Expedition as they arrive at Praag. [*] Adela, to see how her gradual nepotistic takeover of the Karag Nar Gunnery School is going. [*] Spend some time exploring the Karak now that everyone has spread out into their hopefully permanent Clan Halls. Since you're about to take your first prolonged absence from Karak Eight Peaks since it was retaken, you've decided to spend some time walking its halls and valleys and taking it in with fresh eyes. It's evolved quite significantly from the time when fungus was being hacked and burned out of ancient tunnels, most of it far from your view. Karag Nar you're quite familiar with, a large and prosperous town in its own right with a charming Tilean-Imperial cultural blend with heavy Dwarven influences. And the Eastern Valley is turning more and more into a slice of the Moot each year, providing the Karak with food and you with a breathtakingly idyllic view that remakes itself each season. But what of the other Karags? The Citadel? The Under-Karak? To satisfy your curiosity, and perhaps a little to wallow in self-congratulation for your part in retaking the Karak, you set aside some time to explore these, once more assisted greatly by the fact that wandering around and being nosy is entirely within the job description of a Loremaster. Karag Lhune was originally the home of all of the Karak's odds and ends, such as the airship port, the orphanage, and various temples and vaults. As it was the first Karak to be retaken, it was until this year the home of most of the Karak's Dwarves. Now it's only home to two Clans - Angrund, Belegar's kinfolk, and the second incarnation of Clan Stonebeard, which is being refounded by Prince Gotri. It's a clear symbol that Belegar does not intend to cleave too closely to the Karak's past, as the now-rebuilt Hall of the Moon is to serve permanently as the new Throne Room. In place of the jewelled constellations that were looted millennia ago is a collage of coats of arms of all who contributed to the original Expedition, both Dwarven and otherwise. It takes a while to find your own - three Knightly Orders means there was a lot of Coats of Arms to be carved - but you eventually find it nestled close to that of Angrund right above the throne, among the banners of Gotri's and Edda's and Kazrik's Clans. The Chiselwards has changed roles a number of times throughout history. As its name suggests, it was originally a home and school for Dwarves whose Clans were unable to provide those, and for the children of Clanless. During the Time of Woes it became home to refugees from other Holds - first Ekrund on the far side of the Badlands, then those from nearby holds when the southern Holds came under collective siege from the greenskins and the Skaven. It was assumed that Karak Eight Peaks would be the safest of them all, and tragically it was the first of the southern Holds to fall. During greenskin occupation it was a mushroom farm, and until recently part of it was home to the We. When Karag Lhune was retaken, the mushroom farms were burned, the We allied with, and the Chiselwards became home to all the Dwarves of Karak Eight Peaks. Now only two Clans remain, and a massive reconstruction effort is underway to convert the Chiselwards from sprawling communal barracks to proper Clan Halls for them. The hangars atop Karag Lhune are even more filled with activity than ever as miners and masons begin plans for expanding the honeycomb of hangars. Prince Gotri's vision is that every flightworthy gyrocopter will be launched at short notice and as one when needed, and as was demonstrated when the Okral came under attack, it's one that works quite well. Each launch bay has heavy doors on both sides set up so that only one can open at a time - an external set so that the gyrocopter is not vulnerable to surprise attack, and an internal set so that an open launch bay cannot serve as an entry point to the Karag. The Okral's engineers claimed Guild secrets and refused to contribute to expanding the air corps directly, but they did overhaul the repair bay and install elevators that will make the expansion without them much easier. The Temple of Grimnir is the other major landmark of the Karag, and it's very different to the one you've visited in Karak Kadrin, as it is not a Slayer Shrine dedicated to Grimnir the Slayer, but instead a Hall of Oaths dedicated to Grimnir the Oathkeeper. It was sealed by mighty Runes as the Karak fell and remained untouched until Kragg unsealed it seven years ago, and it's impossible to begin to estimate the tally those Runes must have taken from ambitious Goblins and Skaven in those three thousand years. Carved on the walls inside are the names of every Dwarf to ever fall in the Karak's defence, and in sealed adjoining rooms are the remains of those that fell in the reconquest. The only alteration that has been made since your last visit is the addition of fresh names. It's hard to take in the scale of the vast walls covered in neat chiselmarks, the amount of time and death that the innumerable lines represent. It's harder still to comprehend that the earliest entries were the names of Dwarves that marched and fought alongside the Ancestor Gods. --- The Citadel was once the ceremonial heart of the Karak, but after it was the front line of the Karak's reconquest for three years it was repurposed to be the home of Clan Huzkul and the muster point for the Karak's defenders. If the cliff between the Eastern Valley and the Caldera below wasn't enough of a divide, the former is filled with lush fields and Halfling cottages while the latter has only just begun to sprout scraggly grasses in the wake of millennia of greenskin occupation and the magical onslaught that defeated Waaagh Birdmuncha. Atop its battlements is the great signal horn to sound the alert for all the Karak at once, and the flag flying alongside it tells everyone at a glance who is the highest-ranking member of the Karak's military hierarchy present there. Part of you still feels a little nervous every time it's not Dreng or Belegar. The only thing detracting from the Citadel's image as quintessentially Dwarven is that flying atop one of the two tallest towers is the flag of the Amethyst Order. Below the Citadel is the former Throne Room that has been turned over to Clan Huzkul and transformed into their Clan Hall, the walls of which are covered with banners and weapons taken as trophies by the Karak's youngest Clan, as if to remind visitors, or possibly themselves, that they have earned their place here. Below that is the Hall of Pillared Iron, carved out of a natural cavern and filled with metal pillars to support the weight of the Citadel above millennia ago and now home to the Karak's strangest ally, the We. With the sixty-four pillars as supports the spider-hive has been growing year by year, the labyrinth of silken corridors expanding to swallow up more and more of the room. From your study of them you know the sprawling complex exists not just to disorient and entangle attackers - the walls are filled with hibernating spiders who are able to serve as reinforcements, replacements, or rations as needed. In the deepest part of the Hall are the six current Egg-Layers, each the size of a house and caring for a separate cluster of eggs. A braided rope of silk extends from the hive to the entrance and down an adjoining tunnel. This is the guide-thread for the We's Hunters to guide them to where they should hunt without having to use up too much of the limited amount of memory they have to fall back on when outside the guidance of the We. Following this takes you underneath Karagril to the Karak's final actively hostile frontier: the entrance to the Underway to Karak Drazh. Though the greenskins would be quite capable of learning that charging into a solid wall of ballistas, grapecannon and handguns won't get them anywhere, they've instead elected to use it as a sort of population control, and on a regular basis the losers of the Red Fang tribe's internal politics are forced to charge down the underground gauntlet. It's quite clever if you follow the internal logic of the greenskins: their fungal ecology means there'll be a constant stream of new Goblins and Orcs whether there's room for them or not, so by forcing their rivals to charge down the gauntlet at regular intervals the tribe becomes no weaker, the position of the winning individuals becomes stronger, and the Dwarves are forced to pay a constant tax in ammunition, gunpowder, and attention. Unbeknownst to them, the predations of the We alter the economics of the situation, as once Karag Nar's weavers figure out how to convert the We's silk into bolts and garments, the presence of neighbouring greenskins will more than pay for the defences that must be arrayed against them. Which you hear will happen any day now. Which you've been hearing for years. It's a source of much grumbling to you and Gretel, and a source of much smugness to Johann, who stole his silk sheets from a Naggarothi Elf. Above the gauntlet is Karagril, the northernmost peak, home of the Karak's miners and masons and the hub of its mining operations. Like the rest of the Karags the useful minerals inside it were exhausted generations ago and it is now only home to Clan Halls and to a temple to Grungni the Miner. The actual mining operations and quarries can be found on the far side of Death Pass, and you gather it has taken a great deal of work to clear them of anything that had taken residence in them and make sure that the shafts and tunnels have remained structurally sound. The Okral were a great help in that, and in clearing and in many places remaking the tunnels and roads to allow the fruits of Dwarven labour to be returned to the Karak and sent on to where it can be used. Now iron and silver ores flow in a constant stream to Karagril and onwards to Karag Mhonar to be smelted, and the Karak is producing truly new materials and goods instead of merely scavenging the wealth of the past. The Temple of Grungni makes you wonder. He is the principal deity of the Dwarven pantheon, and is usually celebrated by Dwarves in a huge and central temple to Grungni the Father. But here the Temple is dedicated to the Miner, and is tucked away in the least-populated corner of the Karak. You haven't raised any questions about this because you're worried that this is due to the rift between Belegar and Thorgrim, the latest heir to Grungni's throne, and the way to deal with that sort of problem in Dwarven culture is to never bring it up and hope it goes away. But you suppose it might owe more to ancient history than modern. Karaz-a-Karak is where Grungni built his throne, but Karak Eight Peaks is where Grungni first mined gromril. Given those circumstances, perhaps it's only natural that Karak Eight Peaks pays more deference to Grungni the Miner than Grungni the Father. --- Following the ore tunnels takes you to the most recently refounded Karags. Karag Rhyn and Karag Mhonar lie at the southern edge of the Karak and are the twin peaks of the titular eight, as the two are connected at their base instead of being spaced out like the others. It is into them that the Okral poured most of their effort and into them that most of the Karak's Clans have now moved. Karag Rhyn is the more populated of the two and its Clan Halls are built around a great temple to Valaya the Mother, and is also home to the Karak's sprawling breweries run by Clan Dourback. It's unquestionably dominated by the Grimbrow settlers from Karak Izor, as most of the other Clans that call it home are significantly smaller in number and prestige. It's not uncommon for a Karak to have multiple Royal Clans, but normally all but the native are royalty in exile from a fallen Hold. Perhaps if Princess Edda had been successful in wooing King Belegar they might have merged with Angrund, but since she got a position on the Council instead and has been quite involved with Prince Kazrik for some time, that seems to be out of the picture. Perhaps it might cause trouble down the line, but for now everyone gets along well enough that it's not a problem. The only other Clan capable of challenging Grimbrow's dominance is Clan Helhein, an ancient and celebrated Warrior Clan from Karak Norn, who are renowned for their ability with crossbows and guard the nearby approaches to the Karak. The terrain nearby isn't quite daunting enough to completely rule out an overland approach, so the ancient fortification of Morzund's Wall stretches west between Karags Rhyn and Yar, and the watchtowers known as the Sentinels run in a chain from Karag Rhyn to Karag Mhonar to Kvinn-Wyr, and then north to the Citadel. Like Karag Nar, Karag Rhyn is dotted with small establishments dedicated to just about every craft and service imaginable, either from individuals straying from their Clan's profession or from ambitious individuals who have immigrated in the hopes of being able to establish themselves on this new frontier. A large hall is dedicated to transient traders and though only Khazalid is spoken, it's not just Dwarves that have stalls there, as traders from Tilea and the Empire have noticed and marked a developing new market on the edge of the map. Traders heading east have started loading their wagons with trade goods instead of food and supplies for the first leg of the voyage so that they can sell the goods and load up on supplies at the Karak and make a profit doing so, and on the way back they drop in to see if some of the famous wealth of Karak Eight Peaks can be extracted in exchange for spices or silks or other luxurious and exotic goods. The EIC has a regular stall here for importing the few human-made goods that the Dwarves can be persuaded to purchase, and there's plenty of Halflings selling fruits, vegetables, and baked goods. Karag Mhonar has been dedicated to Smednir, the son of Grungni and Valaya and Ancestor God of Smelting and Smithing. It's to here that all the ore from Karagril flows to be transformed into ingots and then into useful goods, and it's here that the Karak's mint has been established. Clan Ironfinger holds sway here, who were originally metalsmiths in Karak Eight Peaks that dedicated themselves to smelting when they fled to Karak Azul, supposedly because they wished to assist instead of competing with the Clans of the Hold that had granted them refuge. They grew large and successful enough in doing so that it took a fair bit of negotiating for the Clan to split and send half their number back to their ancestral home, and part of that had been the Okral focussing a great deal of their effort on building facilities worthy of their skills. Belegar's hope is this will be the first domino in a chain as the promise of high-quality metal will convince other Clans to return to Karak Eight Peaks. Somewhere inside it, under the watchful eyes of Clan Angrund and with everyone involved sworn to silence, the vaults of the Grand Urbaz are being melted down, further purified through various metallurgical and chemical techniques that are closely-held secrets, cast into ingots, and minted into fresh coins bearing Belegar's face and name. The other recovered vaults and the loot taken during the reconquest represent a great deal of wealth on their own, but Belegar is a big believer in spending gold instead of blood and is constantly on the look-out for more opportunities to do so. It might not be too many years until that gold is needed. --- Three Karags remain largely empty. Karag Zilfin is the tallest and westernmost peak of the eight and was once the home of the Karak's considerable industry and most prominent Clans, but currently the only part of it that doesn't stink of chemicals is occupied by Cython. It's faded to the point that it's merely unpleasant instead of actively harmful, but it still has a long way to go until anyone would willingly call it home. This is something Belegar's done nothing to dissuade as it makes it that much easier to empty the Grand Urbaz vaults without witnesses. Karag Yar lies to the south of Karag Zilfin and to the west of Karag Rhyn, and it is occupied by the dead. A few individual Clans had tombs that were scattered throughout the Karak, most of which were breached and looted at some point during the long occupation, but the rest sent their dead to rest in the great Ancestral Tombs in Karag Yar, and have since the Ancestor Gods ruled the Karaz Ankor. In the deepest levels are the remains of the founders of each of the Karak's original Clans, figures who are worshipped as Ancestor Gods in their own right by their descendents. When it became clear that Karak Eight Peaks would fall, King Lunn and a team of Runesmiths fought their way through the invaders until they reached the Tomb and King Lunn held the entrance until the Runesmiths could seal it, saving the Tombs from being looted but also sealing themselves inside. Kragg, Thorek, and the Okral's experts spent years unravelling the defences that those Runesmiths erected in haste and desperation, and now Gunnars and his underlings have interred King Lunn and the Runesmiths among their ancestors and are engaged in a long and thorough sweep of every level to ensure that every individual tomb remains sealed. Built into the complex is an ancient temple to Gazul, Lord of the Underearth, and you'd be surprised if Gunnars hadn't also established one to Gazul of the Flame somewhere. Kvinn-Wyr is the final of the eight, and as the name 'White Lady' attests, it was once dedicated to Valaya the Protector. Of the three empty Karags it's the only one without a significant reason for it to remain so, and you wonder if Belegar has any plans for it. So far he seems to be dedicating a mountain to each Ancestor God, which leaves Morgrim and Thungni, patrons of Engineers and Runesmiths respectively. You're sure Belegar would like very much to lure more engineers to the Karak, but the original Engineer Clan of the Karak, Clan Stonebeard, dedicated themselves to a more direct form of warfare after fleeing to Karak Drazh and then being forced to flee again to Karak Azul. Now they name themselves Clan Sternbeard in recognition that they've strayed from the path of their ancestors, and even if Belegar could entice them to return to Karak Eight Peaks, what little knowledge they retain of their craft is from an era predating gunpowder. So he's left with trying to convince an existing Clan to split off a founding population, which is a difficult task at the best of times, as Engineers are very aware of their value, as are the Dwarfholds they belong to. The only other options are recruiting Dwarves into Gotri's refounding and training them up pretty much from scratch, or having an Engineers Guild with no associated Clan, which in Dwarven minds makes for a small and unstable Guild. The same problem applies to an even greater degree to the Runesmiths, since the very few surviving Runesmiths from Karak Eight Peaks were reabsorbed into the Karaz-a-Karak Runesmith Clan. In any case, currently the only activity in Kvinn-Wyr is the masons trying to repurify and restore its cisterns after millennia of being lived in by trolls, which is no mean feat. --- All in all, the Karak seems to be in a good state. Still room for improvement, and a lot of room to expand into, but it's come a long way from when the Expedition first arrived at the East Gates and it's finally growing. Though part of you misses the excitement and high stakes of the Karak's early years, you're definitely proud of being a part of making all of this possible. - The length of this one kind of got away from me. Remainder of the social turn to come.

Turn 33 Social - 2486 - Part 2

The Imperial Gunnery School's branch in Karag Nar is an odd phenomenon. It exists in large part due to Prince Kazrik taking advantage of institutional ego, and if any human polity had bought the same amount of guns they would simply have sent along instructors to teach the proper firing and maintenance techniques. But 'sold cannons to a Dwarfhold' is something they're going to be boasting about for decades, and given the chance to double down on that, they happily took it, and if all they get out of it is the chance to casually say 'our branch in Karak Eight Peaks' at every opportunity they'd consider themselves to have done quite well out of the deal. Under normal circumstances, it would be fated to being an overly-dramatic label for the Undumgi arsenal and training facilities. But these are not normal circumstances, and Belegar is no normal Dwarven King. With the Okral returned to Karaz-a-Karak, plans are unfolding to expand the branch into a proper foundry, and Rangers are surveying nearby mountainsides for suitable locations for redoubts along the eastern half of Death Pass. Currently, the artillery of the Undumgi covers the length of Death Pass required for the path to Ulrikadrin and Barak Varr to remain open, and Belegar intends to extend that to cover the path from Karak Eight Peaks to the Dark Lands - both to ensure the Karak remains part of the safest route of the Silk Road, and so that anything unfriendly that comes from the east will be well mauled before it even sets sights upon the Eight Peaks. To do so with human-forged artillery would surely rankle the traditionalists, but it does mean that it could be established within years, rather than decades. So gold flows to Nuln and back comes a steady stream of carefully-selected candidates. The Imperial Gunnery School wants this to go off without a hitch, so they need to ensure that they send just the right people. This is no task for a mad inventor in the tradition of Volker von Meinkopt who would reinforce everything Dwarves believe about human craftsmanship - this calls for more of a Josef Bazalgette, stolid, dependable sorts who would be content to simply create a large number of high-quality guns to proven designs without getting creative, as well as the supporting staff thereof. And as it turns out, that selection criteria has just so happened to include three candidates with the surname Burgstaller, and all indications are they won't be the last. Authority is a funny thing. It is vitally important to the structure of society, but it does not tangibly exist, so it is very easy to claim one holds it even if they do not. That's why doing so leads to very nasty consequences from those who actually do hold it. But there's a grey area you've dipped into a time or two yourself - act as though you have that authority and people will often assume you do, and you never need to actually explicitly claim it. Even if you do get caught red-handed, its deniability is beautifully plausible, and nobody can ever really be sure whether it was intended, or whether it was simply a very fortuitous misunderstanding. For example, if someone is not technically in the employ of the Loremaster but is under their authority and has worked alongside them in the past, it can be very easy for someone to reach the conclusion that they are doing so once more when they start asking curious questions about, say, the selection criteria for the branch's latest round of recruitment. Did they take advantage of a misunderstanding of the authority they held? Or did they simply ask questions of someone who gave answers too freely? The tricky thing is that even Adela might not know for sure. Self-deception is by no means an uncommon ability, and it could be that she convinced herself she was merely innocently asking questions when part of her knew the possibility for misunderstood authority existed. Adela is quite loyal to her family, and people have convinced themselves to do worse for lesser reasons. Or you might be seeing skulduggery where none exists, and Adela was simply able to barter a position for her relatives in exchange for services to the Gunnery School. Either by lending it her own fledgling engineering expertise, or leveraging her contacts amongst the Dwarven engineers to make a few useful introductions, or simply by lending her abilities with fire. Quality charcoal is quite expensive and coked peat even more so, and many an unambitious Bright Wizard has paid their way through life by stoking forges with Aqshy. Is this a problem? Well, that depends. In a perfect world, the procedure that would have chosen the branch's staff would pick those ideal for the job, and Adela's intervention has prevented that. But in the world that is, it's much more likely that if Adela hadn't put her thumb on the scale, someone else would have. And this way you have a set of levers inside the branch that you can access through Adela, should it ever prove necessary. So you simply confirm that they have the qualifications required for the positions they're filling, make a few slightly pointed comments to Adela to make sure that she knows that you know, and leave the matter at that. --- With yourself about to be absent from the Karak for a few months, you've made the decision to upgrade the security of your quarters even further. When Dwarves are involved and they have as much of a vested interest as the Karak does in keeping the area secure, there's really no limit to how much security they'd be willing to apply, but even they have to grudgingly admit that there's a point of diminishing returns here. All that's really needed is to make the entryway sturdy enough that any forcible entry would need to be loud enough that it would alert the entire Karag, and lengthy enough for them to still be on the outside when the Undumgi reached them. The process of making this happen is a rather noisy one, and one that involves rather a lot of Dwarves coming in and out of the upper levels of your home, which in turn supplies ample reason to spend your time elsewhere for the duration, which only compounds the more obvious one. Going away on a multi-month trip is the sort of thing one precedes by spending an ample amount of time with their paramour, especially if that trip is off the edge of the map. This course of action turns out to be quite sound indeed. Panoramia is pleasant company even when not being weighed against a troop of Dwarven masons, and on top of the obvious benefits of spending a lot of time with her, trailing curiously in her wake as she goes about her work proves rather interesting in its own right, and not just for the parts of it where you get to watch her channel enormous amounts of Ghyran and glow quite beautifully to your Magesight. You'd imagined that her work for the Halflings began and ended at doing magic at fields until food happened, and while that's certainly part of it, there turns out to be much more than that. Part of it is mechanical, as she determines the proper amount of water that a given field requires and works with the Halflings to determine the most reliable way to either add or remove water to reach that point. Part is alchemical, as she applies various chemicals to samples of dirt and from the results reaches conclusions about the makeup of said dirt. Part of it botanical, as she inspects underperforming plants and determines whether the blame can be placed on seed, soil, or on an interloper, and when the last turns out to be the case, she displays an understanding for the selection and deployment of toxins that would be quite terrifying if she ever turned it on something larger than a fingernail. With her magic alone, she could make a plot of land give a single bountiful harvest no matter what state it was in. But with this full suite of techniques, she has set her sights on making an entire valley give bountiful harvests for the foreseeable future. It's not quite as immediately impressive as a superweapon, but being able to hold a kingdom is of no use if you can't feed it. As the date of your departure approaches, a lot of the time you spend with Panoramia shifts from the fields to the privacy of her home. Not entirely for torrid purposes, though there is a certain amount of that sort of thing, but mostly for talking. Though you're both Wizards, you're from two very different Orders and had very different upbringings. Panoramia went through her Apprenticeship with her family but no faith, whereas you had faith but no family, and exploring those differences proves just as compelling as the other type of explorations. But all good things must come to an end, and all too quickly the day comes for you to depart for Praag. And when you board a gyrocarriage with Johann and Max, it's with her smile in your thoughts and her kiss on your lips. --- Praag is the oldest city in Kislev, and was once a rival to the capital in wealth and culture. Streets and buildings decorated with silver were ringed by vast, spiked walls lined with cannon and strengthened by Dwarven runes. For a time the Fire Spire of Praag was the center of magical research in the Old World. But that time ended with the coming of Asavar Kul and the Great War Against Chaos. Praag held out for months against the invaders and may have saved the Old World in doing so, for it gave Magnus the Pious and High King Alriksson and Teclis time enough to raise a force capable of repelling the forces of Chaos. But by the time it reached Kislev, Praag had fallen. The war was won instead at the walls of the city of Kislev, and the few buildings left standing in Praag were covered in Chaotic sigils, staring eyes, and seeping blood. All of it was torn down and the ruins burned, and some say that should have been the end for Praag. But the Citadel of Praag never fell, and when the forces of Chaos were pushed back, the survivors that took refuge there refused to abandon their city and instead learned which parts of the rubble were less cursed than the others and rebuilt atop them. It's said that in the aftermath of the Great War, one in two children born in Praag was horribly mutated in some way or another, and that the streets would rearrange themselves each night and had to be rebuilt regularly to prevent them from shaping themselves into sigils of terrible power. The taint of those times has faded somewhat over the decades, but every night the taint of Chaos waxes once more, and black blood bubbles up from below, and the faint screams of those that were sacrificed to Chaos here echo through the darkness. Even in the noon sunlight the streets throb with Chaos taint to your Magesight, as if Morrsleib shone at full strength above. You take a deep breath, center yourself, and put it out of your mind. You'll undoubtedly experience worse before this adventure is through. Right now the steam-wagons should have crossed into Kislev, and the first of the Wizards that are assembling to join the Expedition have probably already arrived. Your focus right now needs to be on them, not on the scars left on this part of Kislev nearly two centuries ago. --- Ice Witches spurn Praag due to the presence of the ruined Fire Spire and Ungol Hags refuse to step foot in the city unless they really need to, so there's no resident Wizard or Wizard-equivalent that courtesy demands you make your introductions to, leaving you free to establish yourself and go about business. You manage to secure surprisingly comfortable quarters at a tavern called the Bow and Bard as well as the use of a card table in the back, and then set off to winnow your way through the more reputable inns and taverns to see if any Wizards have arrived yet, as well as spreading some silver around to ensure that innkeepers know to point them your way should they encounter them. Your sweep of the city pays off immediately as you are told by the proprietress of an establishment heavy with curtains and perfumes called The Red Rose that they have a Celestial Magister currently staying with them, though not currently accepting visitors. You pass on a request for him to meet with you at his convenience, and the next morning he presents himself as requested. "Magister Michel Solmann, at your service," he says with a bow. You gesture at the seat across from you. "Solmann," you say. "Any relation to Klaus Solmann?" "A cousin on my father's side," he says as he sits. "With proper attention to the portents, the gift of magic can be encouraged to run in the family." "Are you yourself portent-inclined?" you ask, hopefully in a neutral tone. "I'm more attuned to the Elemental side of Azyr." "Winds and lightning and such?" "Just so." You nod. "What led you to join this Expedition?" He gives you a thoughtful look before answering. "Encouragement from on high," he admits. "The signs, I hear, are murky, but it's hoped that a fistful of lightning will help tilt things towards positive outcomes." You manage to keep from frowning. "As long as you continue to be this forthright about that sort of thing, we shouldn't have a problem. Magister Matriarch Stossel suggested there was something omenous, and perhaps ominous, about this Expedition. I'd rather that this be kept between you and I - it could cause the wrong kind of concern among the others, once they arrive." "As you wish, Lady Magister." "There's another of your Order that will be joining us, Journeyman Hubert Denzel. He is operating in his capacity as King Belegar's delegate to the Winter Wolves, so I'll ask you not to try to exert Collegiate authority over him - but if he's willing, I'd ask that you give him what guidance you can in matters of Azyr." "As you wish, Lady Magister," he says once more. --- The second new face to arrive is a Jade Wizard, heavyset and deeply tanned. "Journeyman Cyrston von Danling," he says, shaking your hand with a firm grip. "Pleased to put a face to the name." "Pleased to put a name to the face," you reply. "Tell me about yourself." "First generation Wizard from Solland, been on my Journey for eight years now. I have high-to-extreme seasonal attunement, which for the purposes of this expedition will mean that I will grow in power as Summer approaches, and a knack for water magics." "Geyser?" you ask curiously. "Still working on that one," he admits. "Could you learn it within the next month or so?" He hesitates. "Probably not. But I can water-dowse with some reliability." You nod. "That could be of great use. What brings you to this Expedition?" He shrugs. "I've been all over the Old World, but never been east of the World's Edge Mountains. This seems like a fantastic way to change that." Not the worst motivation you've ever heard. You thank him for his time and dismiss him. --- Third to arrive is a woman of about forty wielding what looks like a reinforced wall sconce. "Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler," she introduces herself as. "Kohler by name or occupation?" you ask curiously. Charcoal burners tend to be hardy and careful sorts, as a proper burn takes at least a week, during which the fire must be closely watched. "Formerly both, in the Nattern Forest. Beastmen attacked, and I discovered I could put fire to a different use." "A fellow Stirlander. Northern or Southern Nattern?" "Northern, a ways west of Klam." A former subject of the Countess of Wolfsbach then, rather than of Anton. "Elemental Aqshy, then?" "Yes, Lady Magister." You note the hesitation in her voice before using your title. Magic typically develops between the ages of 15 and 25, but outliers in either direction are hardly uncommon - indeed, the founder and first Magister Patriarch of the Bright College was a celebrated Greatsword commander when his own magic developed. Those that develop late in life often find it difficult to defer to Wizards younger in years but higher in rank. "Fire Ball, Fiery Blast, Curtain of Flame, that sort of thing." "Inextinguishable Flame?" "Yes. About three weeks." "If you're willing, you could earn some Dwarven gratitude by putting that to work on their boilers - I know it won't have the full effect on fires that large, but it will save some fuel." "They'd allow that?" she asks. "I've earned some goodwill for Wizards among the Dwarves, and this Expedition isn't exactly made up of staunch traditionalists." She nods. "Very well. Thank you, Lady Magister." "Why have you joined this Expedition?" "Recognition and promotion," she says simply. You nod. "Fair enough. Thank you for your time." --- The final Wizards arrive as a group - a handsome and well-groomed young Magister that must be Egrimm van Horstmann, and three Journeymen who trail behind him like ducklings of his own. "Lady Magister," he says with an easy smile. "I've heard good things." "And your former Master vouched for your own abilities. May we both live up to our reputations. Who are your fellows?" "Journeymen Citharus and Barbitus, and Journeywoman Timpania," he says, indicating them in turn. Citharus is short and heavyset, Barbitus taller and thin, and Timpania slender and shifting from side to side with nervous energy. "I'm not quite a Choirmaster, but I can lead a quartet, and they are some of the most talented harmonists of their generation." "Are they here with you?" "I'm happy to take them under my wing and we can accomplish more together than we can apart, but their purposes here is their Journeying, rather than obligation to their College." "I see. Your capabilities?" "We wield the scouring light of purity. Shem's Burning Gaze and Pillar of Radiance for if we're lucky, Banish and Daemonbane for if we're not." You nod, grudgingly impressed. Those are some potent spells. "Very well. I'll leave your juniors under your authority. If we could have a word in private?" "Of course." He ushers his ducklings out of the room, and closes the door with a click. "What is it you want to talk about?" "I want to be sure there'll be no misunderstandings about the chain of command here. You are here at the order of your Magister Patriarch, yes, but I am here as the representative of King Belegar. Everyone on this Expedition is under Dwarven authority, and all Wizards of the Colleges on this Expedition are, directly or indirectly, under mine." He smiles and nods. "I have no problems with that." "Glad to hear it. Thank you for your time." --- Wizards Recruited: Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, with Journeyman Citharus, Journeyman Barbitus, and Journeywoman Timpania, of the Order of Light Shem's Burning Gaze, Banish, Daemonbane, Ill-bane, Light's Demand, Pillar of Radiance, Radiant Gaze Magister Michel Solmann of the Celestial College Lightning Bolt, Clear Sky, Wind Blast, Lightning Storm Journeyman Cyrston von Danling of the Order of Life Leaf Fall, Spring Bloom, Summer Heat, Winter Frost, River's Whisper, Ferment Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler of the Bright Order Curtain of Flame, Fiery Blast, Fire Ball, Inextinguishable Flame, Ruin and Destruction - Next update in progress.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 1: Praag

To the delight of every cattle merchant in Praag, the next few days see two hundred knights arrive in town atop large and hungry carnivores. You'll have ample opportunity to get to know their leaders once the steam-wagons arrive, so you reserve your attention for the Wizards travelling with them - Hubert with the Winter Wolves, and Esbern and Seija with the Knights of Taal's Fury. With all the Wizards you're likely to get arrived, and with some internal grumbling that you're one Wind short of the full spectrum, you round them all up to set the stage and lay some ground rules. "Karag Dum was cut off from the Karaz Ankor one hundred and eighty-five years ago by the forces of Asavar Kul during the Great War Against Chaos," you say to the assembled Wizards. "Our mission is to travel there to determine the current status of the Dwarfhold. From there, the mission could be simply to return to the Karaz Ankor with that information, or it could be evacuation or salvaging. Different parties have different expectations due to varying levels of optimism and cynicism, so treat the topic with caution if you discuss it with the Dwarves." "Do you think there could be survivors, after all this time?" Cyrston asks. "Karak Eight Peaks held out for longer than that before falling." Only three years longer, but still. "The Norse Dwarves were isolated in Norsca for seven thousand years before they fell, and Karak Azul survived three thousand. And Karag Dum's sole purpose was to prepare to withstand the forces of Chaos. So I don't think it's implausible." He nods, so you press on. "Speaking of touchy subjects, Dwarves do not like or trust magic, and that usually extends to those that wield it. That Wizards are allowed to join this Expedition at all is because I've spent the last ten years building up goodwill with parts of Dwarven society. Needless to say, I'm protective of that goodwill, so here's some ground rules. Do not cast magic on any Dwarf unless they'll die otherwise, and not even then for the Slayers. Do not use unnecessary magic within the confines of the steam-wagons, and if at all possible, do the necessary ones outside. Stay away from the mechanics of the steam-wagons, and don't ask the Engineers any questions about them. And tread very lightly around the Slayers. Any questions?" "How do we tell which is which?" asks Michel. "Rangers have cloaks and crossbows, Slayers have orange hair, if they don't have either they're probably an Engineer. The Rangers are your best bet if you want to make friends, they tend to be open-minded and most of them would speak Reikspiel. I'll also advise you to keep your distance from the Ice Witch and Asarnil, because if you inadvertently offend either it's likely to go badly for you. And don't bring up religion or politics with the Winter Wolves." You double check your mental notes to make sure you've covered everything before pressing on. "Our route will take us through High Pass, across the Zorn Uzkul, through the Great Steppes, and into the outer reaches of the Chaos Wastes. High Pass should be thawed and is being watched by the Dwarves, so it should be uneventful. Zorn Uzkul is absolutely unfriendly territory, but the local hostiles live underground and will only pick a fight if they're sure they'll win, so I like our chances of getting through without incident. The part of the Great Steppes we'll be travelling through is Kurgan territory, with our route mostly going through Dolgan territory. We've struck a deal with them, but I wouldn't bet my life on them sticking to it. As for the Chaos Wastes, no telling what we'll find there, but we're not going too far in and we shouldn't be there too long. "The magical landscape is going to shift several times between here and there. You've probably already noticed that the Winds are thicker here than they are further south, and that will continue to be the case until we reach the Steppes. There, they blow hard enough that they mostly stay overhead, and ground level is surprisingly low in ambient energy. Tapping into an airborne current will be hard to control but should give a lot of power. And of course, the Chaos Wastes will be thick with Dhar. From my experiences in Sylvania, it will make spells trickier to control and make them go bad worse than they otherwise would. And remember - don't touch the bad magic. There's no circumstance so bad that Dhar can't make it worse. Questions?" "Aren't the Kurgan Chaos-worshippers?" Egrimm asks. "Among other things. We're not looking to marry them, just get through their territory. I hope it doesn't need saying how unpleasant it would be to be harassed by a Kurgan tribe through several hundred kilometers of their own steppe." There's a few winces from the crowd. "This Expedition has support from the highest levels of Dwarven society, and with the Marienburg situation, our alliance with the Dwarves is even more important than normal. There's not going to be any significant blowback for us picking our battles out there." "What enemies might we encounter in Zorn Uzkul?" asks Alexandra. "It's Chaos Dwarf territory - oh, and that would be another touchy subject with the Dwarves. If we do have to engage them, the bulk of their fighters will be their greenskin slave-soldiers, and firearms, sorcery, and a sort of muscled Centaur are all possibilities as well. There are also subterranean Beastmen active in the area who are at odds with the Chaos Dwarves." You try to gauge who amongst the Wizards might know what is meant by that, and Egrimm's sudden poker-face and Cyrston's grimace leads you to believe they do. You'll read the others in if it becomes necessary. That seems to be the end of the questions, so you dismiss the Wizards and move on to checking in, one at a time, with what you suppose would be your inner circle - Johann, Max, Esbern, Seija, and Hubert. They've had a fair while to prepare for this Expedition and you kept your distance to let them get on with it, and you're more than a little curious to see how they've done so. Johann is the most senior of them and your main concern, so you check in with him first to see how he's been adapting to a world seen only through Magesight. You know for certain that he's able to function as he currently is, but that's a different matter to being able to fight. Thankfully, he's just as aware of this and has been working tirelessly to adapt to the new normal. Apparently he's been splitting his time between Gehenna and the Cult of Grungni to hone both his magical and martial skills, and he moves with such confidence that if it weren't for his eyes being entirely tinted a dull gold it would be easy to assume he had recovered his vision. His ability to cast Searing Doom will be extremely useful if you do have to fight your way through the Chaos Dwarves, and against less-armoured opponents his golden fists will undoubtedly prove just as effective as ever. Despite sharing an Order, Maximillian drastically differs from Johann. His skills are in scholarship and blacksmithing, and if he hadn't discovered an affinity for Silver Arrows of Arha he'd likely be of little use on the battlefield. But he did, and it's made all the difference - by using his crossbow as a prop, he can fire silver bolts with pinpoint aim and a shocking rate of fire. He's spent much of the past year tinkering with that crossbow, transforming it from a mere prop into something that could be considered a very unusual staff, making it even more suited for channelling the spell through. He's also added the spell Armour of Lead to his repertoire, and if you do have to clash with the Kurgan, you're sure that their lightweight leathers suddenly become crushingly heavy mid-gallop would prove quite a handicap. If there was ever an opportunity for Hubert to become a more typical Celestial Wizard, it's quite likely that it has passed. The time he's spent with the Winter Wolves has cemented him as a warrior, albeit one with lightning in his off-hand and the ability to fly. That he travelled with the Winter Wolves with no mount of his own makes it clear that he has mastered the spell Wings of Heaven, and it's as common to see him flitting around the sky as it is to see his feet upon the ground. It's possible that he'll never reach the rank of Magister, and it's just as possible that he doesn't care. Their loss is the Expedition's gain, as a flying, lightning-throwing swordsman is the sort of thing that would come in handy in any number of situations. Though Esbern and Seija had little time to prepare for the Expedition, it's also been quite some time since you worked alongside them, and they've evolved quite a bit since their time with the Karak Eight Peaks Expedition. They're de facto Knights of Taal's Fury now, Demigryphs and all. Esbern retains his bow and quite likely his ability to sprout claws and tear enemies apart, while Seija has a new, much-longer spear that can do double duty as a lance. Ghur means that their affinity with their Demigryphs falls just short of a familiar bond and you're sure they'd be devastating on a battlefield. Seija also mentions a crow-summoning spell, and you have to fight the urge to scrutinize her with your Magesight to see if you can spot any signs of a bound Apparition. Hopefully you'll have a chance to see it in action. --- The people of Praag have proven surprisingly welcoming to their unusual visitors, and part of the reason why might be that local gossip is already quite aware you're intending to go on a heavily-armed voyage into the territory of those that tore their city asunder during the Great War Against Chaos. Said gossip knows about the approach of the steam-wagons before you do as well, because though they're capable of maintaining quite a pace, they can't outrun the courier networks, and by the time the Expedition is on the horizon everyone in Praag seems to know about it. Between the columns of exhaust appearing on the horizon and the steam-wagons themselves becoming visible, the walls filled with curious onlookers as news spread through the town. Perhaps 'steam-wagon' does a disservice to the behemoths trundling down the road. They were massive when you saw them in Karak Kadrin, but seeing them fill the entire width of a major road really highlights just how large they are. The four wheels you saw them with back in Karak Kadrin have been replaced with a line of wheels running along the entire length of them, presumably to distribute their weight better, and the dual funnels they had have been replaced with only one. A rumbling roar fills the air as they approach and you take the opportunity to count them. Six, only one more than they had two years ago, but in the center of the column is one wider and taller than the others that you presume to be the newest addition. It lacks the swivel-cannon that the others have but more than makes up for it with the dragon that is perched atop it, watching the terrain crawl past with disdain. As they near the city and a set of gates that will never accommodate such bulk, they steer off the road and into the dirt field that surrounds the walls, and though the wheels leave deep, wide furrows behind them, they don't sink far enough to become stuck. Their names are painted into the steel - Alriksson, Magnus, Kriestov, Alexis, Volans. The High King, Emperor, Ar-Ulric, Tzar, and Magister Patriarch that won the Great War Against Chaos. The only odd one out is the largest one which is named Urmskaladrak, presumably after the legendary 'Father of Dragons' that was slain by Grimnir. You suspect this was intended to be a warning for their unusual ally, but one that may have missed the mark. From what you've read and heard, Ulthuan Dragons and Wind-aligned Dragons consider themselves entirely different, and the ultimate ancestor of the former is Draugnir, rather than Urmskaladrak. Or it may have just been meant as tribute to Grimnir, but they didn't want to outright call it Grimnir since a dragon would be perched atop it most of the way. You consider your options as you climb down from the wall to make your way to the gate to greet the Dwarves. Since Karak Kadrin, the leadership of the Expedition has consisted of Borek, Gotrek, and Snorri. That council is about to expand since none of the above are particularly suited to leading non-Dwarven forces, but it's not yet determined how much it will expand. You're the natural choice for leading the Wizards, but it might be best to expand your authority. The Knights had their own representative on the Karak Eight Peaks Expedition's council, but Borek is definitely no Belegar, and it might be better for you to take responsibility for all human forces instead of having someone who you're pretty sure doesn't speak Reikspiel deal with the Knights directly. There's also the question of Asarnil - he represented himself during the Sylvanian campaign, but it might be better if he's one step removed from the Dwarves. Given your reputation amongst the Dwarves, your titles in the Empire, and your relationship with Asarnil, there's likely to be little problem with any of those possibilities, the only question is whether it would be better to limit your focus. [ ] Lead only the Wizards [ ] Lead the Wizards and Knightly Orders [ ] Lead the Wizards and Asarnil [ ] Lead the Wizards, Knightly Orders, and Asarnil - There will be a one hour moratorium. - The Dramatis Personae threadmark has been updated for the Expedition's characters.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Lead the Wizards and Asarnil There is no question in your mind that you'll push for being responsible for Asarnil, but the Knightly Orders were a trickier question. You've gone back and forth on it several times, and it breaks down to two separate questions: whether it's better to have more human voices on the council or your own voice be more powerful, and whether it's better to have more overall control over battles or more opportunity to personally intervene. In the end, more voices and more personal freedom won out, but only just. As you approach, the steam-wagons sprout rope ladders and a steady stream of disembarking Dwarves starts to pour out, some clustering concernedly around the bases of the wagons and others heading determinedly towards the town. As you get closer a head pops up from the former and Gotrek gives you a wave. You take the opportunity to examine the nearest steam-wagon as he approaches. Up close, the scope of the modifications that have been made to the River Monitor designs to build the steam-wagons becomes clear. Eight larger wheels in two clusters seem to provide locomotive force, with large steel rods connecting the rods on the outside, presumably to transfer motion from the boiler. To the fore and aft of each are additional, smaller wheels that presumably are there to further distribute the weight of the behemoths, and from the furrows they left in their wake it seems like there's additional wheels underneath. "Morgrim weeps," Gotrek says as he reaches you, "but in the service of recovering the last places He saw His father, I hope it can be forgiven. We just couldn't make the four-wheel design work, not if we ever wanted to cross anything but solid stone. Didn't even have enough time to cover up the coupling rods, could feel the eyes of manling tinkerers on them all the way here." "Any trouble on the way?" "We mostly stuck to roads built by our ancestors. Only tricky part was crossing rivers, since our bridges are long gone and the manling ones weren't built for anything like this sort of traffic, so to be safe we shut off the engines, caulked them up, and pulled them across by hand. Much easier said than done. But nobody tried to block our path, the beasties and bandits that haunt the roads wanted no part of us and the few Roadwardens with the stones to try to stop us relaxed when they saw beards pop over the parapets. Could have used a test to the weapons, but I'm sure there'll be opportunity aplenty." You look further up the body of the monitors to another new addition: just about where the waterline would be is a series of large hatches, eight in all. "Those for the shotcannon?" "He's trouble on two legs, that Gotri, but he knows what he's about. I'd rather have a good broadside of Organ Guns, but nobody's giving those away, are they? We've got eight on each, and we've been working on drills to unmount and remount them in a hurry. When we're just trundling along we'll have two pointing each way and the other hatches will be for firing crossbows and handguns out of, and if we come under sustained attack we'll form a ring around the Urmskaladrak and shift them all onto the outer side." You turn your eyes to the largest of the steam-wagons. "It's unarmed?" "Between the added wheels and the gun-decks we lost a lot of storage space compared to the original designs, so we went with one larger mother-ship dedicated to storage to make up the difference. Was going to have a gyrocopter pad on top, but that became a bit redundant with the Drakkelgi so it's where the beast perches and the Elgi has set up that silken tent of his. We've also got all the Slayers aboard it, they've built a Shrine to Grimnir in their level and they rarely venture out so there's no trouble so far." "The Slayers are sticking to the vessel you're trying to keep from combat?" "We've got a plan for that," he says with a grin. "But yes, more guns means more gun crews means less room for Slayers on each. Borek's been grumbling that the shotcannon were more trouble than they were worth, but he'll change his tune the first time they see action." "How tight is storage space, exactly?" Gotrek shrugs. "Thorek's lads did some amazing work on the boilers, setting up runes to shunt heat out of one compartment into the boilers so we've got a freeze-room for meat and need much less coked peat to keep the boilers going at full steam, but we only broke even trading peat storage for meat storage, and then we needed powder and shot for the cannon. We went heavy on the former at the expense of the latter because if we've got powder but no shot we can still fire gravel or scrap metal or what-have-you. The mother-ship helped, but if we rely only on stores we'll be down to stonebread by halfway." "You're telling me we've got enough food to get there, but nothing for the return trip?" "That's one way to put it. I've been trying to convince myself that it just means Borek has faith in this deal you struck with the horsemanlings, and in the ability for these Knights to hunt and gather." You grimace, but then shake your head. "Whether he does or not, it should work out. Either the Dolgan stick to their side of the bargain and supply food, or they keep their distance and then the Knights are more than capable of rustling a herd or two of cattle, or they decide to attack us, and each of them is sitting atop a lot of meat. Horse isn't exactly tasty, but it'll fill bellies." "Aye, that's what Snorri has been saying. 'Four horses a day' is what he reckons, and that if we can't take on four Kurgan a day we should all shave our heads and join the lads in the Urmskaladrak." "I'm hoping none of the events of the next few months lead anyone down that road." --- Gotrek leads you to the Alriksson, which has become the lead wagon and Borek's seat of power pretty much by default, and you clamber up a rope ladder to join the first prototype meeting of the Expeditionary Council. "Grandmaster," Borek says to you in greeting as you enter, and Snorri gives a nod. "We've been discussing the chain of command for the Expedition. Between your own rank and good name, and the contributions that King Belegar has made, and the..." he pauses just for a moment, "unique capabilities of the Zhufokri, there's no doubt in my mind that you deserve a position of command in this Expedition." "Thank you, Thane Borek." He grimaces at the title, but doesn't comment. He's absolutely entitled to it under Dwarven tradition since he's leading this Expedition, but it might rankle that it was given to him by Karak Kadrin, rather than by his home. "To catch you up, the Engineers and gun crews will be under Gotrek, and the Rangers under Snorri. On paper the Slayers will be under Snorri too, but really they'll sort themselves out. The next matter is less clear. The Drakkelgi. I was hoping that since they have replaced the Gyrocopter..." "Oh no," Gotrek says firmly. "They both fly, but that's where the similarities end. I'd barely know which end of the damn thing to feed, let alone how to command it." "I can take responsibility for communicating with Asarnil and Volrothrai," you say confidently. "We worked together well during the Sylvanian campaign." "Then they're yours, with my gratitude. Second, the matter of the Knights." He looks at Snorri hopefully. "Completely different paradigm. Aye, 'range far, range fast', but not that fast." "Then we'll have to elevate one of them, I suppose. Which group has seniority?" You shake your head. "I'd strongly advise against that. The Knights of Taal's Fury are dedicated to Taal, and the Winter Wolves to Ulric. It would be like if you picked one out of Morgrim and Smednir to give superiority over the other." You leave unmentioned the political troubles, since you'd rather not air the Empire's dirty laundry in front of its allies unless you really have to. The Winter Wolves are no longer part of the Empire and the Knights of Taal's Fury very much are. There likely won't be trouble if they're simply fighting against a common enemy, but if one is given command over the other it will get political very quickly. But considering the grimaces on the faces of the three Dwarves, your simile has hit its mark. "Point taken," Borek says. "Both it is, then. I take it you're familiar with those organizations?" "Fairly familiar personally, and Masters Esbern and Seija are among the Knights of Taal's Fury, and Journeyman Hubert is King Belegar's Envoy to the Winter Wolves." "Then I'd appreciate if you could find whoever is in command of them and bring them to this meeting." --- It doesn't take you long, since the bases of the steam-wagons have become a milling crowd of curious Knights and Wizards, with the Praag locals gawking from a much more cautious distance. It doesn't take you long to find the respective Wizards and get your introductions to the two new Councillors. Of the Knights of Taal's Fury, Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra is a man whose name tells a story, as the formulation is clearly of the Empire but Zavstra is a Kislevite city, albeit one built on the four-way crossroads between Kislev, Ostland, Talabecland and Ostermark. The man himself is as heavily bearded as he is heavily muscled, and rarely talks much except when the topic is combat or animals. His counterpart of the Winter Wolves is Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger, which is another meaning-laden name. From what you recall, somewhere during the Time of Three Emperors the Cult of Ulric were forced to make vows of celibacy as a condition of their return to Middenheim, and ever since the requirement has been oft ignored by those who feel that petty politics should not bind them. It seems that Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart felt that way at least once in the time before the Winter Wolves left the Cult, and the newfound independence of the Winter Wolves has allowed him to induct his son into the ranks. He's a bit brash but well-liked, and it seems command of the Wolves on this Expedition is his chance to prove that he didn't get in on nepotism alone. You bring the two Knights back to the meeting and the rest of it is dedicated to matters of logistics. Six Councillors and six steam-wagons leads to the natural conclusion that each should take residence in one. Borek has already claimed the Alriksson and Gotrek claims the Urmskaladrak for logistical reasons, and it's extremely straightforward to give Sir Ruprecht the Kriestov and yourself the Volans. Given the choice between the remaining two Preceptor Joerg takes the Magnus, perhaps because taking the other would raise eyebrows in combination with his Kislevite birthtown, and that leaves Snorri with the Alexis. "We'll take on supplies here and at Uskovic and Volksgrad," Gotrek says in near-perfect Reikspiel. "So the clock will only really start once we reach the Dukhlys Forest, though I'm hoping we'll be able to hunt and forage and fell trees to stretch that further." Confident nods from Preceptor Joerg and Sir Ruprecht. "We should close out the first week about the time we reach High Pass, where this weather-witch should be waiting." "She'll ride aboard the Volans," Borek says, his own Reikspiel heavily accented but passable. "The second week will take us through High Pass, the third across the plateau, the fourth up the Skull Road and skirting along Iron Wolf territory, and the fifth is the final sprint through Dolgan and Yusak territory to Karag Dum, which is also the point where we'll be leaving anything resembling a road." "Slower than the estimates," you comment. "If you find an Engineer who can go from blueprint to battlefield without a hiccup, it's Morgrim paying us a visit. We can do higher speeds, but as we learned on the way here, it's hell on the axles if we keep it up long-term. Four miles an hour, ten hours a day. That's what we can do and still have steam-wagons for the trip back." "That gives us more room to work," Joerg says. "If the steam-wagons were going eighty miles a day, our Demigryphs would not be able to do much more than keep up. But half that? We can range ahead, scout an encampment position, then scout and hunt in the area." "Our wolves can keep pace with the steam-wagons, keep the flanks secure and be a moving picket around the convoy," Ruprecht says. "Then when camp is made, do our own hunting. The twilight hours belong to wolves." "I'll set you up with some signal rockets," Gotrek says. "For communication from the convoy, there are flags and signal drums," Snorri says. "Do you know our flags?" Ruprecht nods, Joerg shakes his head. "I'll assign a Ranger to instruct you in the evenings. The drums are simpler, and if I recall correctly there are common Empire tunes that match most of them. Send a musician each to the Alexis and I'll have our drummers pass them on." --- Once the Council meeting ends, you make your way over to your own steam-wagon and make yourself familiar with it. You'd only need to give orders if for whatever reason the Volans becomes separated from the rest of the convoy, so for now your command simply means that you get a cabin to yourself while the other Wizards have to decide between bunks or setting up tents each night. Truth be told, you might have trouble filling the days for at least the first couple of weeks, as the journey has little chance to become eventful until you emerge from High Pass into the Zorn Uzkul. The temptation is there to dip into your reading materials and let the days slip by, but though you're only really obligated to start doing things once enemies or problems start appearing, you suppose it would be best to either make yourself useful or get to know those you will be journeying with in the weeks to come. The four with the most votes will be chosen. Spend time getting to know: [ ] Thane Borek Forkbeard [ ] Head Engineer Gotrek Gurnisson [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves [ ] Hunting - With both the Knights and the Wolves [ ] Foraging - With the Rangers - There will be a one hour moratorium. - If there's another way you think Mathilde could usefully apply her time, let me know. - Each of these 'actions' represents at most a couple of days of time, so training or teaching would not yield significant results. - Extremely rough sketch of the steam-wagons, for visualization purposes: Spoiler: Steam-Wagon

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 3: Eastern Oblast

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Asarnil the Dragonlord [*] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [*] Thane Borek Forkbeard [*] Deathfang From atop the Volans, you watch supplies stream out of Praag by the cartload to be winched aboard each of the steam-wagons in what seems like a well-practiced process. You suppose the same must have happened at every town since Karak Kadrin, and it raises your hopes for the coming weeks. The most obvious reason is that that the supply situation is being taken seriously, but also in that Gotrek is in charge of the logistics but the Rangers are the ones performing the actual purchases, which indicates good coordination between him and Snorri. Food is the primary component of the supplies but a surprising amount of firewood is taken aboard as well, which makes sense after you give it some thought. Engineers would certainly prefer to stick to a single supply of fuel, but the coked peat favoured by the Dwarves is effectively irreplaceable this far from the Karaz Ankor, so every day they burn wood instead is a day more of the much lighter, hotter, cleaner-burning fuel to be used in much less friendly territory. As the single funnel atop the steam-wagons as opposed to the dual funnels of River Monitors attests, water is not thrown away through steam, but instead recaptured and cycled back through the boilers once it has reverted to water. Not only does this greatly reduce the amount of water the Expedition will need to store or source, it also means that the boiled water can be diverted for consumption by the beings of the Expedition, which is a great convenience compared to setting up fires and cauldrons next to every river the Expedition comes across. The Rangers still go to the far side of the city to draw water from the Lynsk upstream of Praag, because even if nobody's going to be directly drinking it, the Engineers are very keen that they don't want various city-produced residues fouling up the Engines. The next morning, the taverns of Praag are scoured to extract the last handful of hung-over Knights and Dwarves, and with a inexorably building rumble the great engines are restarted. The convoy circles the city with agonizing slowness, leaving deep furrows in the empty fields surrounding the walls, but once it reaches the solid stone of the road on the other side it accelerates to a quick march or a slow jog. The Winter Wolves fan out to scout the flank not covered by the Lynsk, and the Knights of Taal's Fury bound ahead - normally it would be to scout out an encampment position some forty miles ahead, but today they make for Uskovic to make sure that another day's supplies will be ready to be brought aboard when the steam-wagons arrive. The Expedition is underway. --- As it turns out, transferring between the steam-wagons when they're underway is not a matter of disembarking one and boarding another, presumably by grabbing onto a rope ladder while jogging. A series of ropes are set up between them once they're in the day's formation, and when supplies or people need to travel from one to the other they're pulled taut, the sender is elevated above the receiver and baskets on pulley-wheels are allowed to follow the call of gravity and slide from one to the next. That's the theory, anyway. In practice, the Dwarves of the steam-wagons have attached handles to pulleys and slide back and forth with nothing but their own grip to keep them suspended, a practice that Rangers apparently use to get around mountains quickly. You'd call it pointlessly dangerous, but you suppose it's a matter of perspective as you pull in the rebellious energies spewed from the Warp and force them to translocate you from one point to another in the space between instants. You make your way to the Alriksson at the head of the convoy, determined to spend some time with the Expedition leader and try to gauge his mental state. It's easy to assume the worst of him based on what you've seen of him, but you suppose it might not be entirely fair to him. The past sixteen years of your life has been in service to two great leaders: Abelhelm van Hal and Belegar Ironhammer. In comparison, very few would do anything but fall short. So you will give him a proper chance to prove himself merely average, rather than dangerously inept. You find him at the fore of the foremost vessel, gazing over the railing at the road ahead. "Grandmaster," he says as you approach. "Actually, that reminds me. By which of your titles would you prefer to be referred?" "Loremaster would seem most appropriate, as I am here as Belegar's delegate. But for informal occasions, I would not object to you calling me by name." "Mathilde Weber," he says thoughtfully. "The battle-mighty weaver. I'd call the name rather on-the-nose, had you not been born with it. The games destiny plays, eh?" You give a nod, more at acknowledgement at the shot across your bows than the commentary on your name. "Indeed," is all you say, wondering where he found the time to look into your origins while preparing for the Expedition. "What brings you aboard the Alriksson so soon after your joining us? Everything to your satisfaction?" Well, if he wants to get right to it. "Truth be told, I am concerned with the food situation," you say. "From what I've been told, we'll have very little left by the time we reach Karag Dum." He turns to consider you, rubbing the forked beard that gives him his name. "Ah, you've been speaking to Gotrek. He has the soul of an Engineer, he wants everything in place before his device leaves the workshop, and considers everything short of that a failure. Three years ago, we had planned food enough for the entire Expedition to get from Karak Kadrin to Karag Dum and back again and he was happy as can be. Two pounds of flour and salt meat times fifty Dwarves per steam-wagon times two hundred days, that's eminently portable for vehicles of this size. I'm sure you know what changed." "The Knights." "And their beasts. Twenty-five pounds of meat per day to keep them in optimal condition. Ten of them would equal the amount of food-weight required by the original Expedition, and we have two hundred. We did what we could with the Urmskaladrak and the cold-rooms, but those Knights increased the food requirements of the Expedition by a factor of about twelve. Then we have the storage space lost to the axle-decks and the gun-decks, so now, yes. Five weeks of food storage. But since you already produced a very welcome solution to part of that problem, I know you do not think that amounts to five weeks of food, as Gotrek tends to imagine." "Bartering and hunting." "And stockpiling. Tonight, Uskovic. Tomorrow, Volksgrad. Two nights later, a caravan from Sepukzy. Two nights after that, one from Novchozy. Dotted throughout High Pass, carefully-hidden stockpiles that the Redbeards have been preparing for half a decade. The clock did not begin to tick at Praag, it begins at Zorn Uzkul. Three weeks to Karag Dum, three weeks back, five weeks of stored food. Zorn Uzkul will be barren of supplies, of that I have no doubt, but after that we spend a few days winding through the northernmost expanse of the Mountains of Mourn, which by all accounts - including ones written by gyrocopter scouts this very year - have game to hunt. No Mammoth that far north, but Rhinoxen herds have been confirmed. The Knights should prove capable of preying upon them, and if not, Asarnil's charges for hunting services are preferable to starvation. After that, a few days along the Skull Road through the territory of the Kurgan known as Iron Wolves, who have horses and sheep and goats and cows who should be easy prey for Demigryphs and giant wolves. And then we turn north, and encounter the Dolgan and find out if they are as good as their word. And if they are not, then they too can be preyed upon." He smiles, only visible as a twitch of the beard, which makes Dwarves seem so taciturn to those unfamiliar with them. "Consider it a test of our readiness. If we cannot muster enough might and competence to find a single week of food from hunting, bartering, and rustling cattle, we're certainly not in a position to be delvers of the Chaos Wastes. Does that put your mind at ease?" "More so than it was," you admit. "I am glad. Yes, food is a problem. Yes, none of those sources are certain. Yes, it would be far more preferable to be beholden to nothing but our own stores for the entire journey. But as comforting as that notion is, it is nowhere near as comforting as two hundred mounted warriors atop terrible beasts at my side as we ride into the Chaos Wastes. That is why you recruited them, is it not?" "Something like that." "Food is a known problem, and one it is easy to fixate upon now. The problems of the Chaos Wastes, and whatever evils will be besieging Karag Dum, we cannot know what they will be and so it is much easier to worry about the food. But I am quite certain that those unknown problems will be more likely to be solved with force than with food." He turns his gaze back to the path ahead. "Making this journey has been my only purpose for five times longer than you have been alive. If I fail, it will not be because I forgot to pack a lunch." --- The compartment Egrimm shares with his Journeymanlings is in a state of barely-controlled chaos, with half-unpacked crates scattered around and the straw that was cushioning their contents inevitably escaping and finding every available nook and cranny to slip into. The Journeymanlings are apparently elsewhere, and Egrimm sits at a table bolted onto the ground, tinkering with some sort of crystal array. "Lady Magister, come on in" he says, and you duck through the ovular door into the compartment. "What can I do for you?" "I wanted to get to know you a little better," you say as you cast around the room for something to sit on, eventually settling on one of the already-emptied crates. "Should things get particularly Chaos-y, you and yours will be our best weapon against it." "Our Wind is particularly suited to banishing the beings of the Aethyr," he says with a smile. "Which is quite interesting, considering it originates there. Some see it as proof of the self-defeating nature of Chaos." "Do you?" you ask curiously. "I think it's a dangerous mindset. It might be true on a large enough timescale, but I doubt it comforted Praag that Asavar Kul was knifed by a lieutenant after the Battle at the Gates of Kislev. Personally, I wonder if might be as simple as self-interest. Hysh would stop existing if the world was swallowed by the Aethyr, after all." "I know a Light Wizard who told me a theory that the Eight directly oppose the Four," you say, nodding. "Which could even go so far as to conclude that the Eights are Gods in their own right. They observed that their own behaviour is as strongly influenced by Hysh as a zealot is by their God." He looks at you curiously. "Intriguing. What was the name of this Wizard? I've yet to encounter that view among my Order." "They go by the name 'Cython', they're an associate of Karak Eight Peaks. They're not from the Empire so I suppose it's natural they have a different paradigm." He nods. "We swim in a dammed lake, I sometimes feel. Tempelwijk being hostile to us over petty politics, Arabyans guarding their own magics as military assets, the Damsels and Ice Witches considering their own knowledge holy secrets... and, of course, we just passed by the charred shell of the Fire Spire. So much hovering just outside our grasp." You nod at the crystal device. "Is that what this is for?" He looks down at it and smiles. "The Chaos Wastes are usually a fair bit further than 'just outside our grasp', so with the opportunity knocking we've got quite a backlog of experiments that have been dreamed up over the years. Usually they just get dusted off for however long it takes for an over-enthusiastic researcher to be reminded that Norscans exist." The smile fades a bit. "The foremost of those experiments will be, of course, our own good selves. We underwent extremely thorough examination before we departed, and when we get back we'll do so again, and it'll be compared to our own readings of ambient Dhar levels. That should give us some hard data on whether the 'exterior radiant' or 'ingested taint' camps are correct." "That's a big sacrifice in the name of knowledge," you say, frowning. He shrugs. "We all became tainted the first time we gazed upon Morrsleib or lived through Hexensnacht. We'll be monitoring our food and water carefully the whole way, so unless the most alarmist of the 'exterior radiant' camps are correct the actual long-term effect should be negligible." You remember your own experiences during the Sylvanian campaign, and how you still don't know whether some of the temptations you experienced then were due to the environment or the circumstances. "Well, keep an eye on your thoughts. Dhar taint has a habit of trying to nudge those afflicted into becoming more so." "Hysh demands a centred mind even when circumstances don't. Don't worry about us, Lady Magister. Personally, my concerns are on Alexandra and Cyrston, and to a lesser extent the Ambers." "It won't be the first time the Ambers, or the rest of the Knights, have ventured into tainted land. But I agree with you about the other two." "I'll keep an eye on them when it's not on my three. Being watched from both the light and the shadow should keep them on the right path." "I'd appreciate your insight." You consider him for a long moment. "Did you choose to come on this Expedition?" He raises an eyebrow at the sudden change of subject, then shakes his head. "My decision was not whether or not to venture into the Chaos Wastes, or whether or not to assist the Dwarves. My choice was whether to serve my Magister Patriarch and former Master, or not. And I made that decision quite some time ago." "And now, here you are." "Here I am." "What do you think we'll find when we get there?" He takes a moment to consider that. "The cynical side of me thinks it will share the fate of Karak Vlag, and we'll find an unmarked mountain when we finally get there. But discounting that possibility... I do think the Dwarves are stubborn enough to have survived. But I have my doubts as to whether they're stubborn enough to have remained unchanged." --- Asarnil's lavish tent is erected atop the Urmskaladrak, and he and Deathfang can usually be seen in various forms of repose as they watch the terrain flow by. There's something of a cat to their natures: the claws are never more than a thought away, but for now they choose to doze in the warmth of the sun. Asarnil looks up as you approach. "Ho, Avaulgu," he says, smiling as you wince at the pun. "It's a good day to get paid for doing nothing." You try to think of a suitable counter, but all that comes to mind is Horinasarnil which might be a bit much. "Dragonlord. Getting along with the Dwarves?" "Enough that I decided to ride with them from Ostermark. They leave me alone, I don't have to rebuild my tent each night, everyone's happy." "Well, don't get too comfortable. I half-expect Clan Moulder to pop out of the ground once they realize there's a Great Dragon rolling through their territory." Deathfang gives a contemptuous snort at that, lifting an eye to look at you. "Deathfang speaks Eltharin?" Asarnil smiles. "When he chooses to." "Which is rarely," Deathfang rumbles. "Asarnil is young, and better able to remember the fleeting beings that pay tribute to us in exchange for the violence we have mastered." He blinks, and he lifts his head as his scrutiny becomes intense. "There is a change in your demeanor, Silver Savage. Have you bested one of the rogue wyrmlings?" "No," you say, and then realize where Deathfang's gaze is. "My staff was carved from one that was slain long ago. But I have spoken to a dragon. An Ice Dragon, by the name of Cython." "Cython," he says with a snort. "Such a name. A Serpent of Wisdom and Knowledge, given in the tongue of the people it has no right to. What does it know of either? The rebels turn their backs on the heavens to play in the dust, and crow and strut when they build a filthy mound that will be blown away in the wind." "Not all dragons followed Draugnir when He joined the courts of the Cadai," Asarnil explains. "There's little love lost between those that did and those that did not." "Their devolved forms are their reward for treachery," Deathfang continues. "They have bound themselves to this world and will die with it. I do not blame the younger races for embracing the Winds, they are no more or less than what they have been made to be. But dragons should know better. They should be better." "It's a sensitive subject," Asarnil says solemnly. "Sensitive subject," Deathfang echoes. "Human, have you met any Druchii? Would you like to boast of it to Asarnil?" "Once, actually," you say, and two heads turn towards you. "I mean, he was only conscious for a few seconds after I met him. Then I put him under Mockery of Death and delivered him to a Nagarythian." "A proper response," Asarnil says with a grin. "Would that you did the same to this Cython," Deathfang grumbles. "Is the Expedition feeding the two of you?" you ask, partly curious after your conversation with Borek and partly to change the subject. "We procure our own provisions," Asarnil says with a sniff, "and I have enough with me to last the journey. When we arrived in the Old World, we very quickly learned not to rely on our employers for sustenance. I have seen feasts thrown by human kings that would make an Asur pauper weep with shame if they fed them to their beasts." "If necessary, it will be little hardship to fast from here to there and back," Deathfang says. "But I've found there are very few places on this continent where you cannot find something to kill and eat." "Fresh meat roasted in dragonfire is one of the world's greatest delicacies," Asarnil says with a nod. "We've discussed the possibility of hunting food for the rest of the Expedition with Borek." He looks ahead musingly. "I might offer a discount if it's in the eastern mountains. It's been quite some time since we fought a Rhinox." "Have you ever been into the Chaos Wastes?" Asarnil shakes his head. "I was chasing Yhetees in Troll Country not long ago, and I've fought in Sylvania and Mousillon and Norsca. And I've been to the Blighted Isle, which I understand to be the Chaos Wastes in miniature. But no, not this deep. I'm quite looking forward to a new fight." "IX, 189. The collapse of the Great Bastion," Deathfang says with a yawn. "Cathay?" Asarnil says with a frown. "Surely not. The reign of Morvael the Impetuous was spent in war with the Witch King. We played no part in Cathay's affairs." "Asur played no part," Deathfang corrects, carefully pulling a very large pillow over to him with his huge claws and resting his head on it. Asarnil shakes his head fondly. "Dragons and their secrets." You refrain from commenting. --- As the day draws to an end and the convoy approaches the final encampment position before entering High Pass itself, there's a new figure amongst the normal handful of Knights and Demigryphs standing watch over it and the expected caravan of supplies from Sepukzy. Sitting on a rock in the middle of the clearing is the Ice Witch Ljiljana, the eldest of the four you met in the city of Kislev. When the Alriksson comes to a halt, you're happy to see that Borek has reached the right conclusion and is the first to be disembarking the steam-wagon, and thanks to some quick translocation you're the second. "Greetings," Borek says as he approaches her. "I am Borek Forkbeard, Thane of this Expedition. This is Loremaster Mathilde Weber of Karak Eight Peaks." "Dzień dobry. I am Ljiljana of the Hromada Ledyanoy Ved'ma. I have been the one writing to you in letters." She nods to you. "And you, I met in person previously." She waves a hand at the entrance to the mountain pass. "Belyevobota, clear as the Goromadny Prospekt, as promised." "Indeed. Karag Dum is in your debt." "Karak Kadrin is in our debt," she replies. "Our agreement?" "Gyrocopter scouts will be monitoring the pass. The first part of the payment will be sent if it is still open in one week, the second if it is still open in two months." She nods. "The Krasnoludy are always reliable. Then we go into the Za." She glares up at the nearest steam-wagon. "You may have your pick of the steam-wagons to travel upon. Loremaster Weber is staying aboard the Volans if you wish to be amongst Wizards." "With the Bachór Charodei? Nie. I will stay with the," she waves a hand at the nearby Knights, "leshiye towarzysz. Kovnik Joerg is sensible." She nods as if that settles everything and walks away. "Do widzenia," Borek says to her departing back, and then he turns to give the Pass a thoughtful look. "There's an odd match," you say as you watch Ljiljana make her way over to the Magnus. "Though I suppose Taal could be seen as a forested equivalent to the Ancient Widow. What was that she called them? Leshi..." "Leshiye towarzysz." He considers it for a moment. "Forest Knights, sort of." "She's definitely got seniority, so I suppose it shows that the Ice Witches are taking this seriously." He shrugs. "It was always Karak Vlag that dealt with them. I can get by in Gospodarinyi, but I don't know their people and culture much. We just focused on staying connected with the Karaz Ankor. Hopefully the Knights can keep her out of trouble." "Hopefully," you echo. --- The four with the most votes will be chosen. Spend time getting to know: [ ] Thane Borek Forkbeard [ ] Head Engineer Gotrek Gurnisson [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves [ ] Hunting - With both the Knights and the Wolves [ ] Foraging - With the Rangers Other: [ ] Visit the former site of Karak Vlag - There will be a one hour moratorium. - If there's another way you think Mathilde could usefully apply her time, let me know. - Extremely rough sketch of the steam-wagons, for visualization purposes: Spoiler: Steam-Wagon

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 4: High Pass

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Ice Crone Ljiljana [*] Visit the former site of Karak Vlag [*] Magister Michel Solmann [*] Head Engineer Gotrek Gurnisson The Ice Witch Ljiljana gives every indication that she'll be hard to get along with and even harder to get to know, but considering you're promised to a steppe heist alongside her at some point in the coming weeks, it's at least worth a try. So one evening as the armed steam-wagons circle protectively around the Urmskaladrak and a meal of steamed goat and Ungol-style dumplings is distributed, you make your way over to the part of the clearing dominated by lounging Demigryphs, pausing to give a scratch to the back of the head of Esbern's. Ljiljana sits at the fore of the Magnus, unperturbed by the biting wind that still has some of the nip of winter left in it and munching on a dumpling. "Mathilde," she finally says as she finishes off the dumpling and takes a swig from a leather flask. "Come to feel the wind in your hair?" "I was hoping you could tell me more of my obligation for this thawed pass." "Will tell you what I know, when I know," she says with a wave of her hand. "Must taste the wind, feel the dirt, speak to the stones." "You don't know who has whatever it is?" She clicks her tongue. "If I cannot find it, your debt is clear. That is how sure I am that I will know." "Can you tell me what it is, at least?" She looks up and down the pass. "The Widow is strong here. Very well. We seek the Za-Goblet." You frown, thinking. "Can't say I've heard of it." "Yha, Imperinyi have luxury of not knowing. Kurgan drink from goblet, become stronger, sometimes become daemons. Goblet breaks. Goblet found elsewhere. More Kurgan drink, and on and on. So we take goblet, Ved'ma guard goblet, nobody drinks, never breaks, never found again." You frown. "Sounds like a dangerous artefact to be transporting." "My problem. The Ancient Widow may protect, and if not," she shrugs. "I am old. Soon I join the winter." It's a ruthless point of view, but you can see the sense to it. Taking an endless supply of daemonic transformations from the Kurgan would be worth a lot more than a single life to their future enemies. "Are you getting along with the Knights?" She grins. "Like those of Ursun, but with better manners and metal skin. And Joerg remembers enough of the proper ways to be welcoming." That could be a concern. If she manages to get hooks into the leader of the Knights of Taal's Fury, she could influence him in favour of pushing on if matters devolve to the point that the Expedition should be turning around. Still, you've got Esbern and Seija to keep an eye on him, and you've still got the Winter Wolves who will side with you if push comes to shove. And that reminds you: "will you fight alongside the Expedition between here and the Steppes?" She tuts. "Would rather not. Save as much strength for the Za-Goblet as possible. But if I must, I must. No goblet if Expedition is destroyed." She tilts her head and looks at you thoughtfully. "A question for you, since you have so many for me. You serve the Trickster, yha?" Apparently not very well if she already knows that. "I do." "A message, then. Tell Him that the Widow may be willing to forgive, and that He should send a representative to discuss." You feel a sliver of wary attention turn your way. "I take it He'll know how to go about that?" "Yha. Friends in common, you could say." "I'll pass it along." No need to tell her that He already heard. You've received answers to the most pressing questions you had, and you get the impression you're unlikely to make much further headway with her, so you thank her for your time and make your way back to the Volans before the dumplings get cold. --- You find Magister Michel playing card games with the trio of Light Journeymanlings, and lurk nearby until the game concludes. Michel jumps quite gratifyingly as you slide into the chair opposite him, almost dropping the cards he had been regathering. "Good evening, Magister Solmann." "Good evening, Lady Magister," he says, rallying. "Care to join me for a hand or two?" "Gamble against a Celestial?" you say dubiously. "Yes, that's the usual reaction," he says with a sigh. "Haven't had a good game of Trionfi or Reversin in months. What can I do for you?" "For starters, keep the stakes low with the others. I don't want bad blood amongst the Wizards of this Expedition." "Won't go beyond coppers." "I also wanted to know if you could shed any more light on what Magister Matriarch Stossel is concerned about." He shrugs. "Even if I knew anything more - and I don't - I probably wouldn't be able to tell you. The future isn't set in stone, so if you get a glimpse of it and act too dramatically to try to alter it, you could change the future too much for the glimpse you got to be any help to you. You can stack the deck," he says with a smile as he ruffles the cards in his hand, "but you can't change the game." You frown thoughtfully at that. A bit like having a spy inside the enemy camp, you suppose. If you act too obviously on their information, you could give away that you have that information. "That makes sense. I don't like it, but it makes sense." "And I suppose while I'm putting my cards on the table..." You sigh. "Must you?" He grins unrepentantly. "It's hoped that I'll have an opportunity to see the Ice Witch in action. Weather is part of Azyr, but it's underutilized compared to our study of the future and the stars. We're not looking to steal secrets, just to garner a bit of inspiration. It's unlikely any of the inner workings would be directly transferrable, anyway." "Not quite Arcane, not quite Divine," you say with a nod. "Closer to Elementalists than anything else, if I had to guess." "She's said she'll contribute if we come under major attack, so you might have your chance. Is that why it's you that's here, instead of anyone else?" "If all goes well, I'll have enough goodwill banked that I'll be able to try to develop some new applications for Azyr. I hope to give the Jades some competition for the agrarian sector - they can only bring forth water on a very small scale, whereas an induced storm might be able to water an entire barony's worth of farmland." "That's a useful ambition," you say with a nod. "Have you had a chance to talk to Hubert?" "I have. He's... somewhat single-minded, but his skill with Lightning Bolt surpasses my own. I've been giving him a few tips on Wind Blast in the evenings, considering how well he's taken to Wings of Heaven he should be able to wield it quite well by any standard, let alone that of a Journeyman." "I'm glad. Thank you." You look at Solmann thoughtfully. "What did you do for your journeying?" "I fought alongside the Drakwald Patrols in Hochland, mostly minor skirmishes with Forest Goblins and Beastmen. Waaagh and Peace was a great help in the last year of my Journeying, by the way. I also assisted with the administration of the College of Sorcery in Hergig." "Oh? My former Master was up there a few years back, pursuing a Tzaangor through the Middle Mountains." "Would this be Magister Regimand?" You nod. "I met him a time or two. Never got to fight alongside him personally, but the information he left us when he was done kept us busy for a year." "Small world," you say with a smile. "I'm glad we were able to talk, and I'm looking forward to seeing what you learned in Hochland." You slide four aces across the table towards him, and he frowns at them and starts rifling through the deck in his hands. When he looks up again, you're gone. "Greys," you hear him say with a sigh, and you smile as you slip away. --- As the Expedition approaches the halfway point of High Pass, you join Snorri and a group of his Rangers who are making a detour to check on Karak Vlag - not in the expectation that they'll find anything, but out of the obligation to try anyway while they're here. The road is surprisingly rough for one leading to the former site of a Dwarfhold, and you're told by the Rangers that there had been a proper road that joined the one through High Pass, but it had disappeared with the Hold. "What about nearby mines?" you ask. "Gone too," Snorri says grimly. "But we've dug some exploratory shafts. The veins that Karak Vlag mined have not returned, but instead been replaced with solid rock." "Solid," you echo. "So not simply caved in." He nods. "So that would mean that..." "Whatever did it isn't playing silly buggers with time, it's playing silly buggers with us," Snorri finishes, to a rumble of anger from the other Rangers. "Have any Wizards taken a look at it?" "That Elgi Zhufi and some of his Umgi students, shortly after it disappeared." You blink. "Teclis?" "Aye. Said there wasn't a trace of whatever had caused it." "Ah," you say, somewhat disappointed. You're rather proud of your Magesight and part of you was hoping you'd be able to spot what others had missed, but if Teclis and the founders of the College had given it their scrutiny and found nothing, that's a pretty clear indication that there's nothing to find. Unless... well, when they visited it, the Great War Against Chaos had only just ended. This area would have been saturated in magical energy from the recent expansion of the Chaos Wastes. Almost two centuries later, perhaps things would be clear enough that you could see what even Volans couldn't. When you finally reach your destination, you can see why the Dwarves would have chosen this place for one of their original Holds. The peaks that frame the approach would have been trivial to carve watchtowers into and the sheer cliff-face that the path terminates at would have been the natural place to carve an entrance and, eventually, to place its famous outer gates, which had been inscribed with scenes of the founding Dwarves exterminating the terrible beasts that made their homes in nearby caves. Instead of that great entrance, there's a single sad excavation barely tall enough to admit a Dwarf that gives up barely a few meters in. You wonder if this was an aborted attempt to start from scratch, or someone desperately hoping that Karak Vlag still existed under an external layer of rock. Snorri glares at the cliff-face. "It's not right," he says. "No songs to sing of their doomed defence, no occupied hold to retake. Just removed, with nothing left but fading memories." You put his words out of mind and focus. Stone is an excellent insulator of magic, and normally trying to see magic through this much stone would be a fool's errand, no matter how keen their magical senses. But you're not trying to see a spell or a magical being through stone, you're seeking something much, much larger. You know that the Old Holds of the Karaz Ankor form a Waystone network that funnels magical energy to Karaz-a-Karak, and that includes - or included - Karak Vlag and Karag Dum. If either of those two nodes on the network remain... You vaguely hear one of the Rangers ask something, only for Snorri to hush him. You let your eyes slide out of focus as you turn all your attention to the magic around you. All you can see at first is Azyr high above. You redouble your concentration. You can see birds of prey flying overhead, faint dots of Ghur among the Azyr. Patches of Ghyran in the hardy shrubs and mosses dotting the stone around you. The extremely faint hint of something alien yet familiar that emanates from Dwarves. Below you is blank, but it's blankness that's deepening as you focus your concentration down, blocking out everything but the stone. And finally, you see it. Like a faint star you can only see when you're not looking directly at it, a tiny string of energy far below, one end frayed as the magical energy reaches its destination and finds nothing there to redirect it further south, and instead spills into the stone. At the point where those magics are being grounded the ambient energies must be so high that any creature there would be wracked by terrible mutation, but stone is hardier than that, and it simply radiates the energies until they're so diffused that they're harmless by the time they reach anything that could react to it. Stone is an excellent insulator of magic. You frown, peering at the faint tendril. Sure, stone is an excellent insulator of magic, but- That's the third time you've thought that exact phrase. "How does stone interact with magic?" you ask, as if thinking aloud. "I don't know much about it, but I do know stone is an excellent insulator of magic," Snorri says. "That's why we build our Holds underground." Dwarves wouldn't normally say that. 'Insulator' puts the focus on the magic, not the stone. Dwarves consider themselves to have the nature of stone, and they'd say stone resists or repels or endures magic. It's a defensive phrase, a weaponized cliche. A tiny fragment of radiated information meant to mislead. Stone is not that excellent an insulator of magic. After almost two centuries of constant bombardment, even stone would be affected, but it isn't. Ergo that magic isn't being radiated, it's being used. You try to do the mental calculations for what could be done with that amount of power multiplied by one hundred and eighty-five years, and quickly realize that the better question is what couldn't be done, and that's a damn short list. Also short is the list of beings that would be capable of shaping that amount of power, and damn near every entry on it is Chaos-aligned. The word 'portal' comes uncomfortably to mind. And then you realize that whatever original objective this gambit might have had, the Ice Witches going to the trouble of scouring High Pass clean of snow would have announced that some sort of very important target of opportunity would be approaching. So in summary, someone is doing something with a lot of magic, and the 'someone' is almost certainly Chaos, and the 'something' is almost certainly bad, and the Ancient Widow has announced that there's an excellent target for that badness trundling down the pass this season. You hold your pose of concentration and consider what your next move should be. [ ] Act normal - There might be unfriendly eyes on you. Pretend you didn't see anything and return to the Expedition as normal, and decide what to do from there. [ ] Run like hell - Every second could count. Return to the Expedition as fast as magic will allow and raise the alarm. [ ] Stand your ground - Snorri has a horn, you have Illusion to make the same sound except louder. Asarnil can be here within a couple of minutes, and the Knights soon after that. Stand your ground and if it does anything, you might be able to disrupt it. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a one hour moratorium. - As this occurred just over halfway along High Pass, Mathilde has not spoken to Gotrek yet. - The conversation with Ljiljana was originally posted here.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 5: Karak Vlag

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Stand your ground For a moment you're torn between bluffing and standing, but in the end you decide against ceding the initiative to whatever it is you're facing. The clearing of the pass announced loud and clear that a juicy target of opportunity would be coming, and right now that target is about a mile away. Either it's winding up to strike, in which case facing it down here and now is preferable to giving it space to work whatever evil it has in store, or it's got another target in mind, in which case it needs careful study so you know who to send a warning to. "Snorri, call for reinforcements." To his credit, it only takes him a moment to reach for the horn on his hip and after a moment to inhale, he blows a long, deep note out of it. You listen carefully to the tone, and weave an Illusion to duplicate and amplify the note, until it's loud enough that pebbles on the path below you start to rattle. "Why do we need them?" he asks as the last echoes of it die away, hefting his war-hammer and looking around warily. "There's some powerful magic occurring deep in the mountain," you say. "And there's very few possible scenarios I can think of where that's not very bad." "You think it's targeted at the Expedition?" "I think it's likely. The Ice Witches rang the dinner bell when they cleared the pass. Whatever's doing it, it knows that something major is happening." "And we just told it that you know that it knows." You smile grimly. "We did." [Rolling...] You heft your staff warily, trying to watch the entire mountain at once while Snorri barks out quick orders to the Rangers, who spread out to different firing positions, crossbows at the ready. In the back of your mind you're trying to make guesses as to what's going on back at the steam-wagons. How long would it take someone to tell Asarnil the significance of the horn? How long would it take him to don his armour, for Deathfang to get aloft? Seconds pass in silence while you wait for something to happen, either to your fore or your rear. [Rolling...] [Observation: Learning, 4+28=32.] In your defence, stone is an excellent insulator of magic. By the time you spot the delicate flow of energies running down hidden channels they've almost reached the surface, and you barely have time to yell a warning and level your staff before the ripple of changing reality comes into sight. In an instant the bare stone face is gone, replaced with the massive entrance to the dwarfhold of Karak Vlag, only scraps of steel hanging from hinges showing where the great gates once were. You have to catch yourself as the ground beneath you falls away, replaced with Dwarven roadworks several inches lower than the bare rock was, and behind you Rangers shout and swear as the boulders and outcroppings they were taking cover behind move or disappear. You take your eyes away from the open gates for just a moment to glance behind you, and sure enough, the watchtowers carved into the mountaintops have been restored. [Temptation: Piety, 89+26+10(Avatar)=125.] Though you almost missed the first wave, the second wave is one you notice immediately, roiling out of the darkness inside the gates. You brace yourself as it crashes over you, and for just a moment a bewildering array of sense-memories leave you reeling. But you know exactly where you are and what you are doing, so you shrug off the sound of a crackling fire and the sensation of cold water on bare skin and focus on the stone beneath your feet, the staff in your hand, and the gates before your eyes. There's movement inside the gate, and as soon as you register the height of the nearest figure and the litheness of its movements you begin to fold Ulgu into familiar patterns. When the first figure emerges it has only a moment in the sunlight before a barrage of Shadow Knives catch it in the chest, but the purple-pink tinge of the humanoid figure's flesh - and there's very little concealing that flesh - tells you all that you need to know. Karak Vlag is in the grip of the Tempter. [Pistol: Martial, 45+23=68.] [Magic: Learning, 45+28=73.] [Rangers: Martial, 10+20=30.] "Daemons!" you yell as you draw your pistol and form another volley of Shadow Knives, but only a single bolt joins your first shot and though the second Daemonette out of the gates falls, the four alongside her continue advancing on legs with too many joints, screaming in anger and anticipation, raising whips and knives and talons and claws as they charge. [Mathilde receives charge: Martial, 10+23+10(Master Swordswoman)=43 vs 7+30=37.] [Snorri receives charge: Martial, 90+20=110 vs 48+30=78.] The first catches a pistol shot in her chest as she leaps, but the moment it takes to release the gun and summon Branulhune is enough for the second to be on you, your sight filling with her empty eyes and needle teeth as her talons sink into your supernaturally hardened robes before you send her sprawling with a strike from the pommel. Beside you Snorri has already struck down one and is pummeling the reeling figure of another as he shouts orders at his Rangers. But the one you struck is already recovering, a long, sinuous tongue licking at the demonic blood spilling down her chin, and still more are moving inside the Karak. [Rangers: 46+20-20(entranced)=46.] [Mathilde countercharge: 93+23+10(Master Swordswoman)=126 vs 67+30=97.] [Snorri countercharge: 65+20=85 vs 16+30=46.] The twang of a crossbow indicates that the Rangers are not completely out of the fight, but you don't have time to gauge how much as you're already swinging Branulhune at the recovering Daemonette, and her attempt to catch the blade with her clawed hands does not go as she probably planned, as it passes straight through the hand and then straight through her torso as well, sending two halves and several fragments splattering across the ground. With Snorri beside you you meet the next wave of daemons right at the gates, and in the close confines it should be impossible for them to evade your blade. That proves correct, but only just - the daemons are unnaturally fast and flexible, and one tries to leap over your blade as another bends backwards in a way that shouldn't be possible for any being with a spine. More daemonic blood spills, and for a moment the survivors are pushed back, reassessing their odds against these foes. You don't like that. You'd much rather they keep mindlessly charging into your blade, instead of thinking and planning and allowing more of their number to emerge from the depths of the lost Karak. But time is much more your ally as theirs, as somewhere behind you there is a thunderous roar and a cry of "Wahnil!" [Disengage: 46+23+10(Master Swordswoman)=79 vs 24+30=54.] It takes the daemons a fraction of a second to react when you and Snorri withdraw from the entrance, but it's a fraction of a second too long, because with an earth-shaking crunch of shattering stone, Deathfang lands between the two of you. A dagger bounces off one of the dragon's horns with a soft tink, and then all becomes fire. --- In the time it takes for the rest of the Expedition's notables to make their way to you, Snorri does a lot of shouting at his Rangers, Asarnil does a lot of pouting that Deathfang didn't even try to save any of them for him, and you do a lot of glaring at the bare cliff-face that has once more replaced the entranceway. You might wonder if it had been some sort of hallucination if it weren't for a couple of things: the road and the watchtowers are still where they're supposed to be, and in the magic-thick aftermath of an entire Karak appearing and disappearing again, the bodies of the Daemonettes remain where they lie, their blood slowly boiling away into free-floating magic. With several lines of on-edge Knights and a thick firing line of Dwarves watching where the entrance should be like hawks, you confer with the rest of the Council. "Not an assault force," is your conclusion to them. "It took them time to emerge, and they did so in dribs and drabs. Whatever power is in control here, it was trying to swat me after it realized I had seen enough to be suspicious. When it realized the scale of the response, it pulled back again - and hastily too, because the exterior parts of it are still here. I'd bet the mines are restored, too." "It answers a lot of questions," Snorri says. "Karak Vlag was taken into the realm of daemons." You nod. "And they retain the power to return it, with whatever cargo they desire. A back door into reality." Borek nods. "Very well. This changes little. We move with caution and keep all forces close to the steam-wagons, as we planned to in Zorn Uzkul." "Changes little? A lost Hold is right there!" Snorri says, pointing at the cliff face. Borek shrugs. "Okay. Go reclaim it." Snorri looks at it, then to you questioningly. You shake your head. "If I had my equipment, and my books, and a few other Wizard Lords, and preferably Kragg or Thorek, I might be able to try to yank it back out after a few months of study. But with what I have here and now? No." "And we're too few for a reclamation," Gotrek says. "Same argument as the one we've been having over Karag Dum. If it's been taken by the enemy, we do not have the strength to retake it." "And for once I agree," Borek says. "We'll send word to Kislev for them to keep a wary eye on High Pass, and a letter to the Dwarven ambassador there to tell Karaz-a-Karak what we have learned. That's all we can do." "Is there a chance Karak Vlag still holds?" Ruprecht asks. "The gates have fallen, but I know enough of Dwarfholds to know that would not have been the only line of defence." "What I know of Karak Vlag says aye," Snorri says, "but I know too little of the tainted realm to speculate." All eyes turn to you, and you consider it. "It's impossible to speculate," you eventually decide. "We know very little of the Aethyr, but what we do know suggests that what we consider to be constants of reality are very variable there. Their defences could have held, or they could have been soft as snow and melted just as easily. It could have been two centuries for them, or two years, or two millennia. They could have all turned to stone as soon as they were drawn into the Aethyr, or their Hold's Runes against Chaos could still be holding." "Daemonettes are the soldiers of She Who Thirsts," Joerg says thoughtfully. "If they had occupied it, there would be guards at the gate. If they had taken it and exhausted what entertainment they could, it would be empty. They weren't guarding, but they were ready for battle. That could indicate a besieging force surprised by a foe to the rear." "Or squatters in a fallen Hold, no different than the rats or greenskins," Borek says. "Is there anything that can be done, here and now?" Ruprecht asks you. [ ] Waystone Clog - Deliberately block the next Waystone upstream to prevent the energy from Karag Dum reaching Karak Vlag, hopefully interrupting the effect keeping it in the Warp. [ ] Waystone Interruption - Have Cyrston channel as much magic out of the leyline feeding Karak Vlag as possible, hopefully interrupting the effect keeping it in the Warp. [ ] Light Chorus - Have the Light Wizards work together to try to reach and interfere with the magic keeping Karak Vlag in the Warp. [ ] Other (write in) [ ] No - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Yes, you rolled 45 twice in a row, that wasn't an error. - There is no obvious way to do anything about Karak Vlag here and now, which is why there's no default 'Yes' answer. But I'm open to the thread exploring non-obvious ways. - Any answer but 'no' will result in the Expedition remaining here until the Karak Vlag situation is resolved.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 6

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Waystone Clog You give it some thought, and spot another way you could come at it. "There's a lot of magical power being sucked up into where the Karak was," you say, avoiding any explicit mention of the Waystones. "That would be how they're able to move it back and forth. If they'd just swallowed it up they wouldn't be able to do that, but this way they can use it as a backdoor into reality." "It's the sort of thing they do," Ruprecht says. "The beginning of the Great War Against Chaos was marked by a daemonic assault from within Nuln." "And a lost Dwarfhold returning as a daemonic stronghold is the sort of sick joke they enjoy," Joerg agrees, to scowls from the Dwarves. "If I interrupt that power supply," you continue, "it would cut short the effect. I believe that would result in Karak Vlag returning permanently to reality." "You believe," Borek echoes. "The other possibility being that it is lost permanently?" "That's possible too," you admit, "but it's the less likely of the possibilities. From what little I understand of the Aethyr, for it to still be able to move back and forth after so long an absence would indicate that the Hold itself is acting as an anchor." "Even in the worst case scenario, we rob Chaos of a major avenue of attack," Snorri says. "And any survivors are doomed to Chaos," Gotrek points out. "They're already lost. I'm sure they'd rather their Hold be snatched back from the realm of daemons than it be lost with them." "How long would it take to return?" Borek asks. "Depends on the exact nature of the magic at work. It could be instant, or it could take some time - hours or days. But no longer than that. If they maintained their grip on it with magic from the Aethyr, it would have eroded its ability to return long ago," you reply. "Can they reverse whatever it is you're doing that would cut off the power?" Joerg asks. "I'd be doing so at a point to the north, they would need to reverse it at the same place. And with the magic cut off, it would no longer be pointing the way - it would take me months of scouring the mountains to find the correct point if I didn't have it to guide me." "Once they're returned, any daemons within it would not have long before they begin to decay," Joerg says thoughtfully. "No storm of magic, and the Chaos Wastes are not currently waxing. And there's no population centers nearby for them to capture for sacrifices. Two days, three if Morrsleib is full." Snorri thinks for a moment. "About a hundred miles to Novchozy, but that's in a direct line over mountains. A hundred and fifty to Sepukzy if they follow the Pass and then cut through the Dukhlys Forest. Two hundred to Volksgrad if they follow the road." "If unimpeded, they may be able to make it to Volksgrad," Joerg admits. "They'd have enough cunning to know if they follow the road, they'll find people eventually." "How large a force are we talking about?" Borek asks warily. Eyes turn to you, and you shrug. "If they are still besieging inhabitants, they could react to what has just happened by redoubling their assault, or they could pull back while they consider what just happened. If it's fully taken and waiting for use as a new access point to reality, there might only be a few daemons standing guard over it, or using it as a home while it's not in use - the forces of the Tempter would be focused on defending it from the other Chaos Gods, the forces for which would be on the outside. If it's the work of a single ambitious Daemon rather than the orders of the Tempter, then they and their followers would likely be calling it home." "Could we barricade the entrance before it returns?" Ruprecht asks. "Trap them inside and wait for them to decay?" Snorri shakes his head. "Dwarfholds have many hidden entrances to prevent that tactic from being used against us, and they are not hidden from the inside. The Daemons would be able to find them, and we would not." "Them spilling out of the main entrance rather than slipping out some hidden exit would be to our advantage," Gotrek says thoughtfully. "We could bring up the steam-wagons and build an enfillade of broadsides." "We can't risk the steam-wagons," Borek says instantly. "If all goes wrong, they will be our only method of withdrawal. If this is to be done, we can shift the guns to positions around the entrance." "If they cannot reverse the blockage of magical energies, their only other alternative is to find people to sacrifice," Joerg says. "If we fortify a chokepoint to the west of here, we have almost as advantageous a position as if we besieged the entrance, with the added possibility of them heading east or deeper into the mountains and dissipating harmlessly." "Could your Knights not harass them to slow them down enough that they cannot reach the people of Kislev?" Borek asks. "It would mean much less risk to the future of the Expedition." "We could, though there would be a chance that a fraction of them will slip through. If it happens it would be a small enough force that Kislevite authorities would likely be able to deal with it before too much damage is done." "Any slipping through would be a failure," Ruprecht disagrees. "We would have the blood of their victims on our hands." "Could Kislev not deal with it?" Borek asks. "Mathilde, you are able to move swiftly when necessary, are you not?" "I am," you say. "So we have her take a message west to warn Kislevite authorities, then she goes to perform her magic, then catches up to us partway through the Zorn Uzkul. Is this a possibility?" You consider it. It would mean having to observe the Karak until the magic dissipates and the Waystone can be safely unclogged, but you're mobile enough on your Shadowsteed to be able to easily catch up after doing so. "It is." "Hardly the stuff of songs," Ruprecht says. "Leaving an empty Dwarfhold in our wake does not sit well with me," Snorri says. "If we can snatch two Dwarfholds instead of one from the forces of Chaos, it is our responsibility to do so," Ruprecht says. As the debate goes on, it becomes clear that things are split fairly evenly between the different possibilities. Snorri wants to meet the Daemons head-on, Gotrek wants to fight from a fortified position or not at all, Borek wants to minimize risk to the steam-wagons, Joerg is drawn to the more pragmatic ideas, and Ruprecht favours going all-in on wiping out the daemons. Though Borek is in command of the Expedition, you're fairly sure he's too canny to dictate a response that the majority of his council is against. It looks like you're in a position to tip the scales, once you decide which way you want them to tip. Argue in favour of: [ ] Fortify the Karak entrance with the steam-wagons. Ruprecht, Snorri, and Gotrek are in favour of this idea. [ ] Fortify the Karak entrance, but keep the steam-wagons disengaged. Joerg, Gotrek and Borek are in favour of this idea. [ ] Fortify the road to Kislev to keep the Daemons isolated from population centers. Joerg, Ruprecht, and Snorri are in favour of this idea. [ ] Harass the Daemons with cavalry to slow them down enough that they cannot reach population centers in time. Joerg, Gotrek, and Borek are in favour of this idea. [ ] Send a warning west, clog the Waystone, and move on. Joerg, Gotrek, and Borek are in favour of this idea. [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Any of the fortify plans will take about a day to set up. - Writing in an idea may or may not succeed; consider the positions supported by the other Councillors to decide whether they're likely to be in favour of a new idea.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 7

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Fortify the road to Kislev to keep the Daemons isolated from population centers. "We don't know what the daemons will know," you say, interrupting the circular conversation. "If the intention of whatever power we're opposing here is opportunistic, it's possible they spill out of there with a map, a packed lunch and a chapbook, and will beeline straight for civilization. But if they're still besieging the Dwarves of Karak Vlag, or if the intention was to join the next Everchosen, it could be that they will be completely ignorant of what part of reality they will find themselves in. If we fortify the entrance, that doesn't matter as they'll run into us anyway, but if we fortify a ways to the west, there's a not inconsiderable chance that some or possibly even all will head east, or scatter into the mountains." "I thought daemons were supposed to be a fragment of the greater power," Ruprecht says doubtfully. "Surely they would not lack for knowledge." "Connection does not necessarily imply pooled knowledge," you say. "For instance, take my familiar, Wolf, back at the Karak. He is as much a part of me as daemons are a part of their God. But even if he were here, I would not know what he had for breakfast unless I made an effort to find out, and at this distance I have no way of knowing at all. The Dark Gods would be much more able to talk to their servants, but the deciding factor here is whether they would bother. Distraction or whim could have the Tempter's attention elsewhere." "Not all prayers are answered," Joerg says with a nod. "It surrenders the initiative," Gotrek says, "and our flanks would be much more exposed than if we kept them bottled up." "Against the forces of the Violent, I would agree, but the Tempter is much more likely to try alternate methods when the obvious fails. Watching the main gates is no guarantee that they would not seek egress elsewhere." There's a lull in the conversation as glances begin to go sideways at Borek, who is frowning, lost in his thought. "So many have put so much towards the attempt to reclaim my own home," he says at last, "that I cannot justify not doing the same for Karak Vlag. Karag Dum would rather be lost than inherit the shame I would bring them if I did not try." "Well said," Snorri says, to nods from around the room. Then a map is unrolled and the Expedition begins to plan the defence of High Pass. --- "As the rumour mill has probably informed you all by now," you say to the Wizards under your command upon the deck of the Volans, "Karak Vlag made a brief reappearance earlier today, expelling several lesser daemons of the Tempter. Before we go on, does anyone not know what I mean by that?" You get silence in response, thankfully. You'd have very stern words to pass along to their College if any of the Wizards here had not had at least a basic briefing in the Chaos Gods. "This would suggest that the Karak was being kept with ties to both realms to act as a go-between, either for targets of opportunity or to wait for the next Asavar Kul. They saw me having a poke at it, and took a swipe at me without realizing there was a dragon within hornblowing distance. Having seen the mechanism in action, I believe I have a way to interfere with it." Thoughtful looks appear on the faces of those present, as they should when someone suggests they can put a spoke in the wheel of the Chaos Gods. "Couldn't that result in the Karak being stuck forever in the Aethyr?" Max asks. "It could, and if that happens, then it's no worse off than it was yesterday and the entire Old World is better off with one less avenue of daemonic reinforcement for the next Great War. But my theory is that it would be anchored here in reality, and the magical energy it's absorbing is maintaining that anchor. Otherwise it would require less passive power, but much, much more power to move it back and forth." Egrimm nods. "Direct translation from the Aethyr to reality requires either the borders between the two to be extremely thin, or a huge amount of power to be expended. The forces of Chaos greatly prize ways around this. That's why they spend so much effort creating and spreading Cults, to act as relays for their will and anchors for their true servants, and why it's so important for them to be hunted and destroyed." "So if all goes to plan, tomorrow I will travel to interrupt their power supply-" you see several mouths opening, "-the details of which lie in both College and Dwarven secrets, so don't even ask. If all goes to plan, Karak Vlag will be severed from the Aethyr and return to reality, and the daemons caught in it will spill forth and either dash themselves to pieces upon our defences," you gesture at the already-formidable stone barricades blocking the road below, "or head east and spill out into the Zorn Uzkul. They won't have long before reality erodes them, and their only hope of extending that timer is finding some easy targets to capture and sacrifice, so we'll be keeping them from Kislev." "And the only targets for that in the Zorn Uzkul are the you-know-whos or, uh, the other you-know-whos," Cyrston says. "Which is a win for us, as far as I'm concerned. For those of you who can't fill in the second blank, I'll tell you if it becomes important. Now, the tricky part between us and the reclamation of a Dwarfhold is that it means withstanding daemonic assault for up to three days. The Tempter is..." You consider your words for a moment. "Well, each of the Four is horrible in their own special ways, but the Tempter is called that for a reason. If at any time you doubt in your ability to withstand what you might be offered, there will be no dishonour and no censure in withdrawing at the first opportunity. Better to fight only half a battle than to go against the Tempter with a chink in your armour." You can see resolution on the faces of the Wizards to not need to accept this offer, and you can only hope they change their mind if they find themselves tempted. "Has anyone here faced Daemons before?" Nods from Esbern and Seija, which makes sense - the Knights of Taal's Fury oppose Chaos in all its forms, not just Beastmen. Egrimm nods too, and Citharus and Timpania raise hesitant hands. "Do Apparitions count?" Michel asks. "That's a complicated question, but for the purposes of this conversation, no," you say. "Very well. The bulk of the enemy forces will be what is usually known as Daemonettes. Physically they appear largely humanoid, with pinkish-purple skin, hooved or taloned feet, and sometimes horns. They're typically armed with short blades, whips, and sometimes have claws instead of hands. They're no more durable than human opponents but they are superhumanly fast, so I wouldn't recommend locking blades with them if you can avoid it. They're also..." you mentally reword the coming sentence a few times, "distracting in appearance, and dressed in little or no clothing. In this context they're more likely to try to kill than lure, but it's still something to be aware of. Even if you don't think you'd be tempted by that sort of being, their nature makes it very easy to overlook what doesn't interest you and focus on what might. "Some of them may be Seekers, which are Daemonettes mounted on daemonic Steeds that resemble a sort of featherless bird the size of a horse, but are faster than any mortal steed and have a long, whip-like tongue with poisoned saliva. And they may be accompanied by beings known as Fiends, which are said to be akin to a centaur, except they blend Daemonette and Steeds in the same way centaurs do a man and a horse. Their tails have a barb that delivers an extremely powerful sedative, and they're said to release an odour that numbs the body and slows reactions. Finally, there may be one or more Greater Daemons or Daemon Princes on the field. Their forms vary greatly, but they're almost always significantly larger than anything else that would be amongst the opposition. I would recommend extreme caution with these, and where possible, leave them to the big guns. Any questions?" "Enemy spellcasters?" Michel asks. "Some Daemonettes may be capable of wielding Chaos magic or Ulgu, as will any Daemon Princes or Greater Daemons. Anything else?" There appears to be nothing, and you nod. "Remember, this is Chaos we're dealing with. There might be unexpected or even previously unrecorded beings amongst them. Be ready and be flexible." And with that last warning, you unroll a copy of the plan the Council eventually reached and begin to explain it and hand out assignments. The battlefield will be a flat plain about forty meters wide with steep edges to either side. There will be a line of hastily-built stone fortifications which will be held by the Rangers, who will fire at the first wave before falling back behind the Winter Wolves and the Slayers to hold the line behind them. Behind the fortifications will be the steam-wagons, which will be firing platforms for the cannon, shotcannon, Engineers, and Wizards. The Knights of Taal's Fury will be in the mountains to either side, ready to counter any flanking attempts or to flank the attackers if there are none; the Demigryphs are nimble enough to navigate this extremely rough terrain. Code: \ | / \ | / Enemies, presumably \ v / \ / \ / \-----------/ \ SSSSSSSSS / Slayers \ RRRRRRRRR / Rangers \ WWWWWWWWW / Winter Wolves \ / \ | | | | | / \ | | | | | / \ | | | | | / Steam-wagons \ | | | | | / \ | | | | | / \ / \ / E | N-+-S | W Lady Magister Mathilde: [ ] MATHILDE: Counterspelling [ ] MATHILDE: Fire support [ ] MATHILDE: Fighting alongside the Winter Wolves [ ] MATHILDE: Fighting alongside the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] MATHILDE: Seeking to attack the flanks of already-engaged enemies [ ] MATHILDE: Seeking to physically attack enemy spellcasters and leaders [ ] MATHILDE: Seeking to physically attack Greater Daemons and Daemon Princes [ ] MATHILDE: Other (write in) Asarnil and Deathfang: [ ] ASARNIL: Use your best judgement [ ] ASARNIL: Other (write in) Magister Johann: [ ] JOHANN: Use your best judgement [ ] JOHANN: Fire support [ ] JOHANN: Fighting alongside you [ ] JOHANN: Other (write in) Magister Max: [ ] MAX: Counterspelling [ ] MAX: Fire support [ ] MAX: Other (write in) Magister Esbern and Seija: [ ] AMBERS: With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] AMBERS: Fighting alongside you [ ] AMBERS: Other (write in) Journeyman Hubert: [ ] HUBERT: With the Winter Wolves [ ] HUBERT: Fighting alongside you [ ] HUBERT: Other (write in) Magister Egrimm and Journeymanlings Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania: [ ] LIGHTS: Counterspelling as a choir [ ] LIGHTS: Counterspelling individually [ ] LIGHTS: Fire support as a choir [ ] LIGHTS: Fire support individually [ ] LIGHTS: Other (write in) Magister Michel [ ] CELESTIAL: Counterspelling [ ] CELESTIAL: Fire support [ ] CELESTIAL: Other (write in) Journeyman Cyrston [ ] JADE: Counterspelling [ ] JADE: Fire support [ ] JADE: Other (write in) Journeywoman Alexandra [ ] BRIGHT: Counterspelling [ ] BRIGHT: Fire support [ ] BRIGHT: Other (write in) - There will be a three hour moratorium. Voting for the Wizard assignments will be in plan format, while voting for Mathilde's place in the coming battle will not be in plan format. This means most votes will have two parts: the vote for Mathilde's part in the Expedition, and the vote for the plan they support for the rest of the Wizards. - Assuming that the Karak returns immediately and the Daemons immediately head towards the Expedition at full speed, Mathilde will be returning to the Expedition from blocking the Waystone at about the same time as the Daemons will reach them. - 'Fire support' means they will seek to do as much damage to the enemy as possible with their spells, while 'counterspelling' means they will try to disrupt enemy magics and attack any identified spellcasters. If no enemy spellcasters are seen to be present, they will default to cautious fire support. - 'Use your best judgement' is only available to those who have proven their combat skills to Mathilde, or have been sufficiently vouched for. It's not available for Esbern and Seija since it would have the same result as placing them with the Knights of Taal's Fury. - Only those Wizards who have ways to keep up with Mathilde on a Shadowsteed are able to accompany Mathilde in battle. They will engage in whatever fights Mathilde engages in.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 8: The Battle of High Pass

Spoiler: Voting results [X] MATHILDE: Fire support [X] Plan: Playing to Strengths, Heavy on the Counterspells -[X] ASARNIL: Use your best judgement -[X] JOHANN: Use your best judgement -[X] MAX: Counterspelling -[X] AMBERS: With the Knights of Taal's Fury -[X] HUBERT: Fighting alongside you -[X] LIGHTS: Fire support as a choir -[X] CELESTIAL: Counterspelling -[X] JADE: Counterspelling -[X] BRIGHT: Fire support Even though you have an exact compass heading to work with, finding the Waystone is still easier said than done. Most Waystones are either Elven monoliths or stone menhirs jutting out of the ground and are therefore very easy to spot even to those that can't see the magical suction siphoning the Winds from the air, but the Dwarven ones aren't quite so obvious to mundane or mystical senses. As far as you can tell they do not absorb Winds themselves, existing only to funnel the Winds absorbed by the great Karak-Waystones towards Karaz-a-Karak, and that power runs deep underground which makes it even harder to spot. It takes you, Johann and Hubert several hours to find your way to the Waystone, much of it spent with you in meditation as you try to catch a glimpse of the river of magical power far below you to confirm that you're still on course. At last you come to a small mountain that at first glance seems no different to those surrounding it, but deep below the magical energies break from the perfectly straight line to turn more to the east. Close examination of the mountain itself reveals nothing; it's not until you move away and examine it from afar that the natural-seeming crags, cracks and gullies combine to form a massive Rune you don't recognize. The next step is to make your way to the peak, which would be no mean feat to those not capable of teleportation or flight, where the nature of the stone is somehow altered to allow for energy to pass through it without any loss of clarity or intensity. You place your hands upon it and recall the lessons you were taught of the ways the Colleges know to interact with them, and speak unfamiliar phrases while you form a construct you do not understand in your mind to funnel Ulgu into. When complete, the construct is accepted by the stone and sinks into the mountain, and after a minute a sickening lurch threatens to topple you off the mountain as you instinctively try to adjust for a movement that did not occur in the physical realm. Deep below, energy begins to pool like water behind a dam, except much more dangerous. Everything you know about magic screams at you to undo what you've just done, but better it gather threateningly here than to fuel the ambitions of the Chaos Gods. With that done you descend from the mountain to return to Hubert and Johann and make your way back towards where the Expedition has fortified as quickly as possible, fretting over the number of variables in play and hoping everything goes according to plan. --- [Rolling...] Your return to the fortified position finds it just as you left it, except slightly more so because there's no such thing as an idle Dwarf when there are fortifications that can be improved. You check in on the Wizards, who are spread throughout the steam-wagons to prevent them from getting in each others' way when battle begins, make sure that everyone's still ready for battle, and settle down to wait. Which lasts for about a couple of hours of nothing happening before you're asking Asarnil and Deathfang to provide overwatch while you pay a visit to the site of the Karak to double-check that power has been cut off. The trip there is uneventful and careful observation reveals that the flow of magical energy has indeed halted, but that's all the conclusion you can draw. Whatever result your actions will have are occurring in the Warp, not here. So you once more return to the fortifications to wait and fret. Dusk comes, and night passes, and the next morning still nothing has happened, but there's a tension to the air, something akin to the sense of a thunderstorm about to break. Your Wizards feel it too, as does Asarnil, but the Dwarves don't, confirming this is on the mystical side of things. You pass on the information to the other Councilors, which at least keeps Borek from nudging for the Expedition to resume, and retake your position at the fore of the Volans, staring east along a stubbornly empty road and drumming your fingers on the rail. The third day takes a while to register what has changed about it, but finally you notice what it is that's bothering you - the Winds are blowing west to east, instead of north to south. Or to be more exact, they're being drawn slightly south of eastwards. A jaunt on your Shadowsteed confirms that the center of this phenomenon is the site of the Karak, as whatever is controlling the magic tries to draw in enough ambient magic to replace the torrent from Karag Dum. A handful of pages of calculations later reveal that it's an effort destined to fall far short, and you smile in anticipation. The fortifications have grown truly formidable at this point, and you're starting to feel sorry for any daemonic force that tries to head west. Finally, in the late morning of the third day, twelve Wizards, an Elf and a dragon wince in unison as a chunk of absent reality tears itself free from the Warp and sends aethyric shockwaves in all directions as it forcibly reasserts itself. Despite the waning throbbing in your temples, you smile. For something to be uncomfortable tens of miles away would have to have been agonizing to anyone with Magesight at the epicenter, and to a being made of Warpstuff... you could only speculate. You pass word along, a flag goes up the Volans' mast, and a steady drumbeat begins to emanate from the Urmskaladrak. The activity below you shifts - not a sudden scrambling to stand ready, as the Dwarves and men are too seasoned for that, but they do start to finish off whatever they are doing, finishing up card games and downing the last of their drinks, and behind you you hear the surprisingly soft noise of a dragon taking flight. "It's starting then," Hubert says at your side. "Seems that way," you say. "We've stacked the deck as best we can, all there is to do now is see what the daemons decide to do." [Rolling...] A few minutes later Deathfang returns to sight and beelines towards you, raising your anticipation a notch. You'd worked out a system of signals for Asarnil for the most expected scenarios, so him coming in to deliver something in person indicates something unexpected or complicated. Deathfang alights atop the cockpit, his landing light enough and the steam-wagon sturdy enough that there's barely a creak of protesting metal, and Asarnil clambers down gracefully. "Three factions," he reports, "Khornate, Slaaneshi and Tzeentchian, busily tearing chunks out of each other. There's a Bloodthirster down and being torn apart by Daemonettes, and a Lord of Change leading a troupe of Horrors east." You take a moment to digest that. "Okay, then... so we're still facing Slaanesh daemons, if anything. Do they have a Greater Daemon?" "Perhaps. Something like an overgrown Fiend. Could be just that, could be a Keeper of Secrets or a Daemon Prince of some sort." "Composition?" "Almost all Daemonettes, some mounted. Though there's some sort of sorcery at play that could be concealing something, I couldn't count them without the numbers getting jumbled. But by appearance it seems to be in the low hundreds." "Thank you. I'll pass that along." He nods and lifts himself back atop Deathfang while you tell Hubert a much more concise version to pass on to the other leaders. As he flits away, your grip tightens on your staff and you smile down the road. Won't be long now. --- The Daemons make slower progress than you expected, but you first catch sight of them as the sun begins to dip in the sky, an oncoming horde of bared flesh and sharp edges led by something that looks like a giant woman from the waist up and a giant snake from the waist down. But just as Asarnil said, attempting to count them causes your mind to tie in knots. With some reluctance you focus on your Magesight to observe the oncomers; reluctant not because what you'll see would be terrible, but because it won't be. Sure enough the beings under your Magesight are transformed into a shifting tapestry of impressions as they somehow communicate with sight that everything you could wish is as close as acquiescence. Without changing from their physical appearance the beings manage to give impressions of everything that might be found alluring, from certain individuals to giant grimoires overflowing with lost knowledge to pleasures as simple as a warm bath and a hot fire, and as soon as your attention lingers on one for more than a moment it balloons into an all-consuming obsession; the grimoires stack to the ceiling and resist any attempts at ever categorizing the knowledge they might offer, the baths become oceans, the fires spread into your very soul, and the individuals, well, the less said about them, the better. [Magesight: Learning, 53+28+10(Windsage)=91.] But underneath all that is magic, only some of which is dedicated to the bevy of temptations that bombard you, and it's shockingly familiar. A tapestry of Ulgu dedicated to misdirection and illusion, too much for the only effect to be a difficulty in counting their numbers. You try to focus, unpick the tangled web of familiar magics woven by alien minds, but it's then that the first of the cannon opens fire, shattering your concentration and, a moment later, a Daemonette. From there the constant drum-beat of cannonfire as the cannonballs chase the sinuous figure of the snake-woman as she weaves back and forth makes any close examination impossible, and you put the matter from your mind as you grip your dragonbone staff and prepare to unleash your magics upon the enemy as it closes. This will be the first time you have cast Melkoth's Mystifying Miasma in anger, and you're intent on giving it your all. As you start to weave the first Miasma, the being that must be a higher Daemon of some kind begins to do something similar without interrupting its dance, and you choke down the impulse to jump in and combat it directly; your part in this battle is already decided, and all you can do is count on the Wizards around you to play their part. Just as you conclude that thought it's rewarded as three Winds leap forth to bombard, entangle, and engulf the half-formed spell, and the spell scatters across the soon-to-be battlefield as the first crossbow bolts and rifle bullets fly. [Casting the Miasma: Req 50, Learning, 6+28=34.] [Miscast management: Learning, 91+28=119.] Your grand battlefield debut of the Miasma does not go according to plan. Perhaps your own anticipation of it was the chink in your armour, as you find yourself hurrying through the incantation, and by the time you notice there's too much inertia to slow or stop. All you can do is try not to trip over your own tongue as the magic hitches, snarls and tries to tear itself free of your grip. But at that point you're more than happy to be rid of it, so when it thrashes you throw your own impetus behind the motion and the spell flies forward like the crossbow bolts it's amidst, and the ball of rebelling magic strikes the weave of illusion like a cannonball against a palisade, and with much the same effect. Magic shatters and the illusion drops away, and the front line of advancing Daemonettes shimmers and transforms into... Dwarves? Not just any Dwarves, Slayers. But with their crests dyed pink rather than red, and with their tattoos dedicated not to Grimnir, but to a different God entirely. For a moment the battlefield seems to fall silent as every Dwarf gawks over the fortifications or through their sights. But the advancing Slaaneshi Slayers have no such compunctions, advancing at a Dwarven run, screaming warbling battlecries as they go. As the echoes of cannonfire fade, a second roar replaces it. Though the Engineers and Rangers stand aghast and the Winter Wolves falter in confusion, the Slayers that joined the Expedition to find their doom scream in outrage at this mockery of them and throw themselves from the fortifications to meet the advancing foe. [Casting the Miasma, take two: Req 50, Learning, 50+28=78.] [Slayer vs Slaaneshi Slayer: 2+20+20(Enraged)=42 vs 93+30-20(Miasma)=103.] This time you're able to control the pace of your spellcasting so that when the two lines of Slayers meet, it is with time eddying unpredictably around the enemy. You'd like to think it makes a difference in the next few seconds, but even through the unnatural burden of rippling time the Slaaneshi Slayers move with more grace and speed than you've ever seen from a Dwarf, their axes slicing through limbs and necks with scornful ease and delivering the death in battle that their counterparts sought. That might have been the beginning of the end as the remaining Slayers throw themselves at the fortifications while the Rangers and Wolves remain paralyzed with shock and confusion, but possibly because of their greater distance from what has been happening, the Engineers have recovered and resumed firing, and bullets and grapeshot alike tear through flesh, splattering much of the Slayers across the advancing Daemonettes. With the Slayers dead, the Winter Wolves should be on the fortifications, but as the Daemonettes charge it's the axes of the Rangers that stand ready to meet them. You take a second to turn your attention back to the suspected higher Daemon and find it struggling to take in the swirl of conflicting energies around it and bend it to its will; perhaps it is reeling from the shattering of its illusion, perhaps it's still dazed from its abrupt transition into reality, but in any case it's definitely struggling to take ahold of the energies that you discarded in its direction. It would probably be able to wrestle it into submission in time, but time it definitely does not have, because that's the moment that Deathfang leaps upon it from behind. When you'd told Asarnil to use his own judgement, you'd imagined something quite different to a perfectly-timed airborne ambush, but you suppose one doesn't last long enough to become the Old World's most expensive mercenary by charging into every battle like a Norscan berserker. You turn your attention back to the Daemonettes, confident that their leader is more than occupied between a miscast and a dragon, and envelop them in a fog of temporal instability as they try to leap atop the makeshift parapets, causing many to misjudge their jumps and slam face-first into the stone and one to overshoot the fortifications entirely and land amidst the still-reeling Winter Wolves. If there was ever a call-to-arms, it was that, but the spooked Winter Wolves scatter from the surprise impact amidst them, and that might have been the beginning of a rout if Ruprecht didn't step forward to pin the Daemonette to the ground with his sword, hurling abuse at the Ulricans all the while. Finally they seem to be shaken back to reality and begin to climb up the fortifications to stand side-by-side with the Rangers as they lock axes against claws. You turn your attention back up to the higher Daemon, but to your shock it's not being torn asunder, but instead has wrapped itself around Deathfang's neck and is slowly sinking the claws of one hand into a gap between the hard scales and fending off Asarnil's sword with the other. Then the Daemon shrieks in pain and anger as a Silver Bolt lodges in its back, and that moment of distraction settles it for you: it's time to act. [Instant reinforcements: Req 50, Learning, 45+28=73.] [Swing: Martial, 4+23=27 vs 39+40-30(Unaware)-10(Wounded)=39.] You could picture it so perfectly in your mind: you appear standing on Deathfang's neck, sword already mid-swing, and you take the Daemon's head neatly off its shoulders. You save Deathfang, Asarnil pledges eternal friendship, Deathfang shares some juicy dragon secrets, happy ending for everyone but the Tempter. The Daemon has other ideas. In an instant its talons are out of Deathfang's neck and catching Branulhune in mid-air, and though daemonic ichor spills forth, it manages to arrest the swing of the runic blade. It catches your gaze in its own, and in a moment you know that it was capable of offering you any pleasure imaginable and some that weren't, but all it was willing to grant you was pain. With one talon clutching Branulhune, a second fending off Asarnil's Ithilmar blade, and its body writhing to avoid Deathfang's massive talons, it somehow manages to spare enough attention to craft a spell. With a scornful glare and a flick of its wrist silvery shards shoot out at you and you're barely able to sway backwards in time to avoid whatever they are, though you manage to wrest Branulhune from its grip as you do so. This gives it the opportunity to turn its full attention on Asarnil and it takes it with savage glee, and an outraged howl echoes across the battlefield as its claws close on nothing but air as Asarnil's silhouette blurs. That's when a ball of pure-white energy strikes the Daemon's back right where Max's spell-bolt had struck previously, blowing a massive hole through its torso. The Daemon sways in place for a moment, blinking and frowning in confusion, before melting away into rapidly-evaporating ichor. You lower Branulhune, torn between being impressed, grateful, and upset at the sudden intervention of Hysh, before you remember that the rest of the battle is still ongoing. You turn your attention to the fortifications and see that Ruprecht's exhortations has spurred the Winter Wolves into a full-blown countercharge, and the Daemonettes are falling back from the wall of stone as battlecries and shouted prayers to Ulric rise above the din. Then the Daemons follow their leader's example and begin to dissolve one by one, and in moments all that remains is Dwarven bodies and Daemonic ichor. You exhale and dismiss Branulhune with a thought, and step shakily down off Deathfang's neck as he carefully lowers himself to the ground for you to do so. Your first battle against the forces of Chaos is over. To be continued. - Though only Mathilde's rolls were shown, I was rolling for everyone, and those were possibly the most swing-y dice I've ever encountered. Almost everyone had one roll below 10 and another above 90.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 9

As the lay-clerics of Gazul amongst the Rangers give the Expedition's Slayers the proper rites and debate what is to be done with those from Karak Vlag, you check in on your Wizards to make sure everyone got through the battle unscathed. Johann and Hubert were by your side right up until you teleported over to Deathfang so you just double-check that they didn't manage to get themselves into strife in the moments between that and the end of the battle. Everyone else, however, requires a bit more time and attention. You know that Cyrston pulled at least some weight because you saw three shades of magic shoving the higher Daemon's attempt at spellcasting off-kilter, and his own description of the battle lines up with that: he watched it for any attempts at spellcasting and jumped in when it happened, as well as keeping an eye on the Daemonettes in case any of them turned out to have a concealed talent for magic. Perhaps one could criticize and say that he should have had an opportunity or two to deploy Summer Heat or Winter Frost, but it's just as valid to say that his job was to counterspell and he did that, and if he had started slinging magic he might have missed any other enemy spellcasters that could have been present. In any case, he seems in good spirits after this blooding and you leave him to his meditation. Alexandra is the other unaccompanied Journeymanling and thus your second stop on the circuit, and in contrast to Cyrston's calmness she's very clearly still riding an adrenaline high. As she enthusiastically gives you a blow-by-blow account of the various forms of fire she threw at Daemonettes, you carefully examine her under your Magesight to make sure it's nothing untoward, and you can't see anything but roiling Aqshy. Just high spirits, then, probably reinforced by the influence of her Wind. All in all it's probably a good thing that her first taste for battle made her eager for more instead of the opposite, considering it's very unlikely to be the last time the Expedition encounters hostile forces. You congratulate her and have a quiet word with the Rangers that would have been nearby, and confirm that while her recollections of mowing down waves of Daemonettes with fire don't quite match reality, she definitely accounted for some of them. Michel isn't immediately visible, but even with so much Daemonic energy in the air it's not hard for you to find a Wizard who isn't actively hiding, and you clamber atop one of the steam-wagons to find him grumbling and massaging his arm, which spasms every few seconds. A backlash from locking magics with the higher Daemon apparently, but while a piece of stray lightning going rogue and rendering an arm useless for a few hours is alarming to your perspective, it's apparently something that's relatively common and usually harmless for Celestial Wizards. While he's not happy, he doesn't seem disturbed or permanently injured, so you thank him for his role in the battle and leave him to his moping. Max is the third and final of those that were on counterspell duty, and he's just as out-of-sight and subsequently easy to find as Michel, and for much the same reason; he's tucked himself away in his room and at your enquiry says to leave him be unless it's dinner time or another attack is happening. A few soft questions pries out of him that his own participation earned him a splitting headache, though it can't be too bad since it doesn't stop him from describing it at length to you once he gets going. You're quite used to Max and his foibles, and nodding along while he complains is a small price to pay for his able assistance, so you allow him to exhaust his grumbling before you excuse yourself and move on. The Light Wizard quartet played quite a dramatic role in the battle, one that you'd attempted and failed to claim for yourself. You put aside any bitterness and check in on the Lights, which is a study in contrasts. Egrimm is calm and collected and watching his charges with a concerned eye, and while Citharus and Timpania leap at the chance to tell the story of their part in the battle (much of which flies right past you, and you make a note to read up on Hysh choir-magic), Barbitus remains silent and lost in his own thoughts. Egrimm notices you watching the quiet Journeyman and catches your eye, and you take him aside to have a word away from the others. "Is it serious?" you ask, noting the worry on Egrimm's face. "I hope not," he replies, rubbing at his temples. "But it's hard to say. Hysh requires a concentrated introspection, and one downside to that is that when one of our own faces troubles, they turn inwards instead of doing anything that might indicate where their mind is at. It could just be shaken nerves, maybe Barbitus just isn't suited for the battlefield. But Barbitus - all three of them, really - have had cloistered lives since they were little more than children. And the Dark Prince has a great many hooks on its line." You recall the barrage of temptations that you were met by, each tailored to target a different aspect of who you are. "You think he might have been tempted?" Egrimm sighs. "Facing the forces of Chaos is the purpose of the Order of Light, and as such we try to prepare our initiates as best we can. But there is always attrition, and those that stare into the eye of the Great Enemy and balk are the least of those. It can be impossible to tell from the outside whether someone has recovered from their encounter with Chaos and are ready to face it again, or whether they have found in themselves a desire to seek it out for the wrong reasons." You nod soberly. Every Order prefers to deal with such things in-house, but when all else fails it is to the Grey Order that the unenviable task of eliminating so-called Black Magisters falls. You've heard stories of how bad it can get when someone with a full College education decides to misuse it, and few of them ended cleanly. "You'll keep an eye on him?" He nods. "Of course, and I'll give him what guidance I can. And if some suspicious accident ends my vigil prematurely, I trust you'll do what must be done." "You have my word." "Thank you. I don't think it will come to that, but better to be sure in such matters." He claps your arm and heads back towards his charges, and you watch him go thoughtfully. It speaks well of him that his concern over his hopefully demoralized and possibly corrupted Journeyman takes precedence over the pride he must feel from having scored the killing blow on a higher Daemon. The final Wizards to check up on are Esbern and Seija, and your being done with the others neatly coincides with some of the Knights of Taal's Fury returning to the Expedition. Their vigil over the Expedition's flanks had them clash with the mounted Daemonettes, and over a series of inconclusive skirmishes and cat-and-mouse chases through the mountains the Seekers were thoroughly scattered. Most of the Knights are still out hunting them down one by one, but the threat they pose to the Expedition is likely neutralized, as it would take too long for them to reunite in sufficient numbers to pose a significant threat. They are now reduced to one more lurking threat amongst the dozens that are already assumed to be hiding amongst the mountains, and one that the Expedition is already well guarded against. You have a word with the Knights to check for any news about the Ambers, and you're told that apart from Seija sporting a minor wound that should heal cleanly, they're fine and enthusiastically participating in the hunt. Your final charges, and ones that would likely not consider themselves such, are Asarnil and Deathfang who have once more made themselves comfortable aboard the Urmskaladrak. Deathfang is grumbling but otherwise lying still as Asarnil tends to the punctures on his neck, rubbing some sort of poultice into them. "Are you okay?" you ask in Eltharin. "I should be asking you that question," Asarnil says with a laugh. "If that had worked, the poets would be fighting each other for the honour of putting that maneuver of yours into verse." You grimace. "I'm aware. But my ego will heal." "As will Deathfang's," he says, slapping the side of the dragon's neck companionably. "That's the Slaaneshi for you, no matter how quick you expect them to be, they'll be quicker. He had her completely by surprise and she was still around his neck in a trice." "So, what do you think? Greater Daemon? Daemon Prince?" "That's the other thing about them, you can never tell just by looking. The other three stick to a theme for Greater Daemons, but Slaanesh likes variety. Unless you can work out that one's name and track her history, you might never know whether she was always a part of the whole or an elevated pawn." "I suppose if I had got the kill, I'd probably never be able to properly categorize it," you say with a smile. "Might be for the best." "It'd be underappreciated too. Everyone thinks Bloodthirsters are the pinnacle of Daemonic opponent, they don't appreciate how fast a Keeper of Secrets is, or how tough a Great Unclean One is, or how hard it is to get a Lord of Change into actual battle." Asarnil shakes his head. "There's an elegance to getting your appreciation in coins and ingots and gemstones. If someone doesn't pay what you're owed, it's a lot easier to burn their house down and loot the ruins than it is to pin them down and demand accolades." You laugh, and thank Asarnil for his time and his insight. --- Once the Expedition has finished licking its wounds and loading the dead and wounded aboard the Urmskaladrak, the next priority is Karak Vlag itself. Every question you have about what Karag Dum might have endured and experienced in the almost two centuries it has been absent applies even more so to Karak Vlag, which was in the actual Aethyr instead of merely the Chaos Wastes. You know the front doors have been blown off their hinges but beyond that you know next to nothing, though it's probably a good sign that the stone is still stone rather than anything more exotic. It could be completely overrun by Daemons, it could be the site of an active siege, its population could have converted to Chaos entirely, or the Karak could still be holding strong just past the entrance. Even the Slaaneshi Slayers are hard to read much out of, because as terrible a blasphemy against Grimnir that they are, there weren't that many of them and could be the result of illusion and trickery, rather than the Karak falling to Chaos entirely. After a cautious investigation of the path leading into the Karak confirms that it's still there and that nothing remains of the Daemons that fought amongst themselves there but decaying ichor, a quick discussion amongst the Council determines Plan A: yelling into the Karak and seeing if anyone (or anything) answers. What it lacks in style it makes up for in that it risks nothing, but a few noisy minutes later yields nothing but echoes. Plan B it is, then: reconnaissance in force, with a line of shotcannon and rifles in defilade to retreat to. You're the natural choice for such a project, but your recommendation that you go in alone and invisible is rejected for Dwarven reasons. First contact with the lost Hold must be made by a Dwarf, so that they can either be welcomed back properly or the Grudge for whatever has happened to them can be properly witnessed and later recorded. You grumble, but by now know which battles can be won and can't be when it comes to Dwarves, so you simply add Johann. If the group can't have stealth, it should have firepower. Snorri is almost as natural a pick as you as this is almost as well-suited to Rangers as it is to Grey Wizards. Ruprecht volunteers, and is thanked for doing so but of the many fine qualities of the Winter Wolves, ability to navigate in total darkness is not among them. Snorri fills out the group with the most seasoned and reliable of his Rangers, and to your surprise and grudging respect Borek decides to come along as well, grumbling that he might as well see what the endangerment of the Expedition has been in aid of. You're not happy with so many eggs in one basket, but even in the worst case scenario the Expedition could still continue in fairly good shape should all of you be lost. "Right," Snorri says, "we go in quiet and we go in dark. If we see anything without a beard," he pauses, "that isn't one of these two, that is, shoot it. And if it's still alive after that, leg it. If you lose track of the path back to the entrance, say so immediately." You have to wonder if that bit is directed at the humans in the party, or at the only non-Ranger Dwarf. "If the Wizards tell you to do something, do it, even if it's weird. Ancestors be with you." And Ranald, you think. The descent into Karak Vlag is painfully slow, marked by scouting ahead for any trace of enemies, then backtracking to examine the area with the dimmest of lights and whispered conversation in reasonable confidence that it won't immediately invite an ambush. There's two recurring themes: signs of battle, and what might be described as Slaaneshi decoration. And not always the latter atop the former, telling a story of a long, grinding siege where the defenders gave as good as they got, making the attackers pay for every inch of ground and taking every opportunity to push them back. "We've seen marks left by rifles and cannon at every step," you say in one murmured conversation after a descent that feels like it lasted forever but according to Snorri has penetrated at most a fifth of the way into the Karak. "Of course," Borek says. "They weren't lost in the Golden Age, they would have all the modern weapons." You pass on commenting on the fact that two century old weapons would still be considered modern. "In the Aethyr, constants aren't. For blackpowder to have worked this entire time, chemistry and thermodynamics must have remained unchanged this entire time. That's unlikely, unless it was kept in a sort of 'bubble' of reality." "Why would that be the case?" Snorri asks. You consider that. "It might have had to be to maintain the anchor, to keep the Karak bound to this position for it to be able to move back and forth. That would fit the energy drain. Keeping a bubble of reality in the Aethyr would be as energy-intensive as keeping a bubble of unreality here was to the Daemons." "It'd explain why the Daemons had to fight for every step, instead of the sheer weight of Chaos driving the Dwarves insane or turning them to stone, as it did to our lost cousins," Borek says gravely. "But the Slayers..." one of the Rangers says doubtfully. "A few score of them," you reply. "What was Karak Vlag's population?" "About thirty thousand," Borek says. "They weren't in a hurry. There's no Everchosen right now, no Storm of Magic. Slain Daemons could be trivially reformed or replaced. They could take it room by room, hall by hall. Take captives. Both to torment them, and to use them to torment those that still hold out." "It fits," Borek says after a moment's thought. "These ones value entertainment over efficiency. Holding an entire Karak in their domain to be toyed with at a whim is the sort of thing they'd do." "Like a child's toy soldiers, complete with a model castle," you say with a nod. "Until a Wizard comes along and yanks it right out of the Aethyr," Johann chuckles. "That's horrifying," Snorri says, "but here and now, hopeful." --- It takes several more eternities of painstaking delving until things change. The decoration gives way to bare stone and Dwarven carvings, and the air hangs heavy with magic from still-dissolving ichor, and patches of mundane blood splatters the stone here and there, still sticky to the touch. No bodies, though drag marks leading deeper into the Karak show where they're likely to have gone. Johann also finds shards of metal that seem very much like fragments of shattered weapons that were mostly, but not entirely, retrieved. "Their energy flow becomes dammed," you theorize when the group next falls back to confer. "Suddenly their toy Karak has a very tight time limit. They strike deals with two other higher Daemons for them to lend their forces to an all-out assault. And then when they're returned to reality so abruptly the forces of the Fighter and the Tempter fall to infighting and those of the Plotter strikes out on their own." "And leaves our lads still kicking?" Snorri says, hope in his voice. "More than kicking by the looks of things," Johann says, running his fingers through a chunk smashed out of a wall. "Well then," he says, and slaps his knee determinedly. The rest of you follow him as he delves back into the depths. "Ahoy!" he shouts, and you're barely able to grab him by the collar and yank him out of the path of an incoming crossbow bolt. "Hold fire, damn it," he bellows, and you sigh and give him another yank as a crossbow bolt tinks off the stone behind where he was. "You're back in the mountains! You're safe!" "Oh aye?" comes a voice from the darkness. "Well, we'll just let our guard down then, shall we? Parades and feasts and the High King here to shake our hand and tug our beard too, I expect. Wives and gold for everyone. Got that about right?" There's a chorus of chuckles echoing from the darkness. You can see realization hit Snorri. "But it's real," he says to the darkness, and scornful laughter is all he gets in response. Well, that and a third bolt, but he's already stepping out of the path of that on his own. A few minutes later at a much safer distance from what appears to be the front lines, Borek is nodding to a crestfallen Snorri. "One of my cousins spent three days camping outside the gates because he forgot the pass-phrases and the Winds were blowing too hard for the Runemasters to confirm his identity," He says. "Daresay these lads have learned even harsher lessons than the Chaos Wastes taught us. Probably had a dozen rescues, and much grander than this one." "But it's real, they're safe now," Snorri says. "Shouldn't that count for something?" "Reality is never as convincing as something designed to be convincing," you say. "Could get Thorgrim here and they'd probably think that his beard should be longer and his Throne bigger." "They'd be expecting Alriksson anyway," Borek says. "Doubt they've heard of Thorgrim." "Exactly, so-" you pause as you consider that. "That's it." "What's it?" Snorri asks, but you're already heading back down. --- "Hi," you say as a Marsh Light illuminates the darkness, and then you step out of the way of the inevitable crossbow bolt. Or at least the Illusion of yourself does. You're bold, but you're not stupid. "Got sick of the act?" the voice says. "Bit overdressed, aren't you?" "Oh, I'm not a Daemonette," you say. "Mathilde Weber, Dalmhornzhufokrul." There's a moment of silence as they consider that. "Night water crafter? You make commodes?" You're too busy grimacing at the mistranslation to react fast enough, and two crossbow bolts punch through the empty air that your Illusion occupies. "Grey Wizard of the Empire," you say, as voices mutter in the darkness at your apparent intangibility. "Pull the other one," says the voice after a moment. "Empire's not like Kislev, they burn their Zhufi." "Not since the Great War Against Chaos," you say. "That's what we call the battle against the forces of Asavar Kul, the Everchosen during the Chaos invasion you lot disappeared in. The Empire legalized Wizards because we joined in the fight against Chaos." "Well, at least this one's original," says the voice. "Go on, then. The next part is where the High King showed up and saved the day and everyone starts respecting us properly. That last bit is the least believable part of the entire spiel, if you ask me." "He died," you say. "His sons, too. His nephew Thorgrim's on the Throne of Power now." "Think I preferred the other ones. What sort of temptation do you call this?" You shrug, and your Illusion does too. "None at all, it's pretty grim. After the losses were tallied, some Dwarfholds were talking about sealing their entrances and dwindling. But Thorgrim declared that the Silver Age was over, and that the Age of Reckoning has begun. The Karaz Ankor will repay every Grudge before it fades from the world." Mutters answer that. "This isn't the sort of thing they say," you can just hear someone saying. "Maybe Tudnak's right." "It will take more than one earthquake only the Rune-pokers can feel before I stick my neck out." "Here, I think I've got an idea. Budge over." A moment later, a much louder voice asks, "what about the Elgi? They turn up for this Great War of yours?" You smile. "They sent three people and they still act smug about it." Silence answers that. "I think it might be real," someone finally says. "Look, I'm not saying you should strip off your chainmail and come dancing through the mountains with me," you say to the darkness. "Reclaim the hold, and I don't have to tell Dwarves to do it slowly and carefully and properly, but I will anyway because the Daemons are gone but the Grobi and Raki probably won't take long to notice you're back. Start peeking out the front doors once you've properly rehung them. Karak Kadrin's a bit far for a jaunt, but if you're feeling bold Volksgrad is up the road and they've rebuilt Praag. We're about to head off to see what's going on with Karag Dum, but we'll send word south and the High King will send someone to answer your questions." There's a while before an answer comes. "We'll take that under advisement," the voice says doubtfully, which is probably the best you're going to get. --- "Let's go," you say to the group as you rejoin them. "What, all that talk and then you're giving up?" Snorri asks. "I'm not giving up, I'm changing the engagement. They're not going to trust anything we say. You know how you befriend a paranoid stray? You don't grab it by the scruff of the neck, you just leave some food out and leave it to it. Eventually it realizes that you're not out to hurt it." "So we leave?" "We leave. Send word to Praag for them to send word to Karaz-a-Karak, and they'll have a gyrocopter full of Longbeards trying to coax them out by the time we get back. Best we can do. Look, I won't pretend that I know the inside of a Dwarven head better than you, but I do know how to manage paranoia. I grew up in a College dedicated to it." "She's right," Johann says. "Like long-tailed cats in a room full of rocking chairs, the lot of them." --- When you return to the surface, you're forced to repeat your argument several more times before everyone reluctantly accepts it, but Snorri brought one of the crossbow bolts up with him and keeps showing it to people who think they'd be able to do better. The mood is mixed as the Expedition prepares to set off once more, as those who want to stay and try their hand are harangued by Borek into submission. The clock is ticking, and there's no hope of getting anything other than munitions from Karak Vlag for the foreseeable future. So you leave in your wake one Hold of thoroughly traumatized Dwarves, which is at least better than the bare mountain where a Hold should be. You turn your mind to the future, and to Zorn Uzkul: the Great Skull Land, the vast plateau where the Chaos Dwarves were born and the site of an eternal underground battle between them and Clan Moulder. The landscape is as desolate as the rest of the Darklands but at least less bare, as for unknown reasons giant beasts from the Mountains of Mourn travel here to die, leaving their skeletons to be stripped by scavengers and the wind. Every step will likely be watched by at least two sets of eyes, watching for any moment of weakness to attack and turn the Expedition's resources into their own. But despite how bare it is, this region sees much more traffic than one would expect, as the Road of Skulls is walked by many. Trade convoys from the Old World to Cathay and back, of course, but there's another mark on a trader's map here: Uzkulak, the founding city of the Chaos Dwarves, open to anyone willing to pay the Chaos Dwarves their cut and give them first refusal on any goods or beings sold there. Pirates of every stripe and species make their way through the channels carved through the pack ice of the Frozen Sea to sell and trade their stolen cargoes and captured slaves, as do Kurgan, Hong, and Hobgoblin tribes from the Great Steppes, Ogres from the Mountains of Mourn, Orcs from the World's Edge Mountains, and unscrupulous traders from the Old World. It's a terrible place, and the world would be far better if it was torn to the ground. But it's also a place where a fistful of gold could turn into just about anything, including ancient tomes, forgotten scrolls, Elven steles, and golden plaques from the New World. The part of you that wants to see it destroyed is matched by another part of you that wants a chance to peruse the treasures from across the world that would be available to purchase there. And it could also answer questions of supply, as even if you don't trust the food farmed and gathered by Chaos Dwarves, food cargoes from piracy and herd animals from the Steppes could also be available for purchase there. The Dwarves wouldn't like it, but they'd probably like starving to death and failing Karag Dum even less. The five with the most votes will be chosen, as you still have some time before the Expedition emerges into Zorn Uzkul. Spend time getting to know: [ ] Thane Borek Forkbeard [ ] Head Engineer Gotrek Gurnisson [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Visit Uzkulak, the Chaos Dwarf equivalent to Barak Varr [ ] Visit the combes that Qrech told you about - There will be a two hour moratorium. - I didn't have a vote for what approach to take with Karak Vlag because none would have achieved better than this, and Mathilde has a lifetime of knowing how to manage paranoia. Any approach that might work would have been tried by Daemonettes under glamours at some point in the past two centuries; that there are still Dwarves here indicates that they didn't believe it then, and so they won't believe it now - at least not in any hurry. The best approach is to leave the Dwarves in peace to glare suspiciously out the front doors for a while. - Mathilde will restore the flow from the Waystone at the beginning of the next update.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 10: Uzkulak

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Head Engineer Gotrek Gurnisson [*] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [*] Visit Uzkulak, the Chaos Dwarf equivalent to Barak Varr [*] Visit the combes that Qrech told you about [*] Thane Borek Forkbeard When you part from the already-moving Expedition to reopen the flow of magic from the Waystone north of Karak Vlag, you feel the eyes of Borek on you as you leave, which isn't unusual - your Shadowsteed has that effect sometimes. But upon your return some time later, they're on you once more. You'd already resolved to find the time to have a talk with him, and this feels like more than window enough, so you ride alongside the Alriksson and clamber up a rope ladder that's thrown down for you. "Thane," you say as you approach the figure that's rarely to be found away from the bow of the lead steam-wagon. "Mathilde," he replies, not turning from the horizon. "The flow re-established, then?" "It has been," you say cautiously. "I'd believed from the High King's reticence that the flow had stopped. It's hard not to feel hope in that it was redirected at Karak Vlag, rather than ended at Karag Dum. But I am curious how you came to know of it. Did Ulthuan tell your Order, or did King Belegar inherit secrets?" "Neither," you say after you regain your mental balance. "It was a new discovery." "You manlings are full of surprises," he says, turning to look at you. "Something my home has been long aware of, but perhaps too used to thinking of as a curse, as the only manlings we see much of are the Marauder tribes." "I wasn't aware that Karag Dum would know of the network," you venture. He smiles bleakly. "Karag Dum remembers much that others have forgotten, even when some might prefer we didn't. Even when we might prefer we didn't." "You're in an unusual mood for someone who's found reason for hope." "My hope for Karag Dum is undimmed. My attention remains on the road ahead." He turns his head back to the road ahead. "The Knights have already confirmed that the final supply cache has been burned by tainted fire, almost certainly from the Daemons that departed east. Between that and the three days of waiting for Karak Vlag's return, we've lost a week's worth of supplies." "You seemed confident when last we spoke on the subject of food." He waves a hand at the Winter Wolves riding ahead of the Alriksson. "I fret because others fret. The beasts consume the bulk of the food, and their riders will not have them starve. Our current schedule has us reaching the Great Steppes with two weeks of food remaining, while being three weeks away from friendly territory. Those are numbers guaranteed to seed doubt in their minds. If we had three weeks of food remaining, as we originally should have, that would have given them at least enough confidence to try their luck at bartering or raiding, at least for a day or two. But now I see things coming to a head at the eastern end of Zorn Uzkul." "I suppose few would make room in their plans for the recovery of a second Dwarfhold on the way, or a warband of Plotter-daemons able to sniff out a resource cache." He snorts. "I could predict that something could happen to delay us and cost us supplies. I was just hoping that if it happened, it would be closer to the Steppes." You consider the matter. "What if there was a source of food closer to hand?" "That plant Wizard?" You shake your head. "Then- oh." He looks over his shoulder to check for listeners. "I'd considered it long ago, but no Dwarven force would reach it intact - anything small would be enslaved by raiding parties long before they reached the supposed safety of Uzkulak, anything large assumed to be an invasion force and opened fire upon. But I suppose you have both the mobility and the required flexibility." You nod. "It's not uncommon for my Order to be faced with two evils and forced to choose. We're adept at weighing them up and finding the lesser." "To be caught between Theralind and a Kharibdyss, as I once heard said. Failure to reach my home will always be the greater evil, and some more riches locked in a Zharr-Naggrund vault does not strike me as being much worse than them being in the hands of whichever Marauder loots my corpse after I try and fail to return alone." With some difficulty, he gradually extracts a small pouch that was hanging around his neck and does not seem to want to part ways with his beard, weighs it in his hand, and then tosses it to you. "Diamonds and Fire Agates. I had a sack as large as my head when I left Karag Dum, and this is all that remains. The least of them is worth enough to feed us from here to Cathay, but I've no doubt that our fallen kin will do their best to rob you." You nod, weighing the substantial handful of precious stones. The Expedition has a large amount of silver tucked away that had been intended to pay for the purchase of cattle from the Kurgan, and then a fair bit more in case there were any other problems that precious metals could solve. While your reputation is good among the Dwarves that you could definitely draw upon that and have the money reimbursed from your personal vault in Karak Eight Peaks, you've had previous experience in how unwieldy large quantities of silver could be, and were still working on a solution that wouldn't sacrifice your mobility in hostile territory. Borek had just neatly solved that problem. "I'll see what can be done at Uzkulak. Would you prefer I stay vague when I deliver anything I was able to procure?" He shrugs. "If you think it would be best. It would be hard to say if Dwarves would be more reluctant to eat food sourced from Uzkulak, or to eat food that came from a Wizard riding off into the wastes and returning with it mysteriously, but I suppose the Knights might think differently." "They've grown accustomed to working with Wizards." "As are many Dwarves of late." He shakes his head and gives a sad chuckle. "Was a time we were making our own miracles. Now the Karaz Ankor is so fallen that an Umgi who by our standards would be barely old enough to begin an Apprenticeship is doing what we apparently cannot. I'm sure arrivals in the Underearth must be greeted with the overwhelming disappointment of our Ancestors, if we're even considered worthy to be admitted at all." It's a troubling thought that you consider in the back of your mind as you hold a clear stone up to the sun. Dwarvish ego is very easy to laugh off as a foible of their race, but just like the Elves it's something they take deadly seriously. Of the fifty dead Slayers being watched over in the Urmskaladrak, you've no doubt that at least several shaved their heads over failing to meet an unreasonable standard they had imposed upon themselves. And you're just as sure that should the Expedition turn back, Borek will make good on his implied promise to continue alone and on foot. He would rather die pointlessly than live with failure. --- With shocking abruptness, High Pass falls away into the plateau of Zorn Uzkul and the landscape turns grey. Though it is largely free from the volcanic ash that dominates much of the Dark Lands south of the plateau, Zorn Uzkul is just as inhospitable, with gritty sand that fills your mouth with the taste of iron every time the wind picks up. And most striking of all are the skeletons that litter the landscape in every direction, ranging from the small humanoid skeletons that you hope were Goblins to the enormous carcasses of massive beasts come down from the mountains to die. With Uzkulak to the north and Clan Moulder below, it's likely that there'll be hostile eyes on you for every step of your journey, watching for any weakness. It's the hope of the Expedition that you'll reach the other side before they spot one. After an hour or so of covering a map with notes and measurements, you determine that the best time to part ways with the Expedition to minimize return time while weighed down with cargo is still a little away, so the next time you find yourself burdened with spare time you make your way to the Alexis. Snorri Farstrider was the one that argued most passionately and pushed to risk the most for the sake of Karak Vlag, and you're curious why that is, and a little concerned that it means his mind won't be on the road ahead. Like many others - including yourself at times - he's taken to spending a fair bit of time at the foremost part of the deck, but unlike the others he's practical enough to have set up a chair and a sunshade there. You find him gazing to the steam-wagon's right, or possibly starboard, at the vast expanse of emptiness to the south. "There's lakes out there," he says, waving a hand at the landscape. "Four vast freshwater lakes, linked by rivers, springing up from the ground and then plunging back into it at a ravine on the southern edge of the plateau. Biggest is the size of the Bay of Wrecks, I've heard." "Oh?" you ask neutrally. You've actually heard of this, or at least the end of them - the waterfall supplying drinking water is what makes Qrech's Seventh-and-Final-Combe such an ideal position for Clan Moulder's forward base. But that's not something to mention too freely. "The greatest accomplishment of Karak Vlag's Rangers. For millennia the east was considered lost to us because you can't follow the mountains without hitting Uzkulak, and you can't cross the Dark Lands without encountering traitor patrols. But this was the Golden Age and we never gave up back then. Karak Vlag's Rangers eventually managed to chart a path through the Zorn Uzkul from lake to lake and reached the Mountains of Mourn without the traitors ever catching on. The mountains were rich and had never seen a pick, and Karak Vrag, Karak Azorn and Karak Krakaten rivalled the riches of the Old Holds for a time. The range seemed wide enough that we could expand into it for a thousand generations and still have room aplenty. But then the Golden Age came to an end." "The War of Vengeance?" you prompt. "That certainly didn't help, but more relevantly in the east, Ogres arrived after having eaten their way through the Giant Lands. The holds of the east held out for a long, long time before falling, but the only contact that was possible with them was by dashing across the Dark Lands, not winding their way through mountains now filled with Ogre tribes to reach Zorn Uzkul. That was the end of Karak Vlag's geopolitical prominence. Even the Silver Age largely passed it by, since there were Norscans and Kurgan between them and the Empire. It wasn't until the founding of Kislev that it began to recover." "Are you from Karak Vlag?" you ask. He'd been introduced to you as if he was Clanless, but you subsequently learned he was part of Clan Redbeard, who you thought were from Karak Kadrin. Now his apparent familiarity with Karak Vlag has you wondering again. He barks a humourless laugh. "That's a question I've been asking myself a lot lately. Clan Redbeard of Karak Kadrin watched the mountains to their north, and Clan Grimsteel of Karak Vlag watched them to their south. They saw a lot of each other and had good relations, and three of my eight great-grandparents were from Grimsteel. After Karak Vlag vanished Clan Redbeard scoured the pass for them for years, and then it was decided they were to hold it on behalf of the Karaz Ankor, as Karak Vlag no longer could. But that put us in a tricky spot. A Clan is part of a Karak, a Karak is part of the Karaz Ankor. So in the eyes of many, a Clan that has no Karak is no Clan at all. You'll find many these days that refer to us as the Redbeards, rather than Clan Redbeard. We see Karak Kadrin maybe once a decade, and there's Longbeards twice my age that have never walked Peak Pass. So until everything that happened back there, I would have said that we were more a part of Karak Vlag than we were anywhere else, and I'd have never given it much more thought than that if you'd never plucked it out of the clutches of Chaos." You nod solemnly. This was just one of many ripples that will be spreading after the events in High Pass. "So it comes down to... does your loyalty lie with the Hold few of you have any real ties to, or does it lie with the Hold that has returned to the Pass that is your home?" "That about sums it up. Though, would they even want our loyalty? You saw them. Well, heard them. Utterly convinced that this was just the latest daemonic trick." "I think they would," you reply sincerely. "Once enough time passes that they realize there isn't a barb in the tail waiting to hook them. I think it will be a long, long time before any of them feel comfortable walking under the open sky, and they'll need Rangers now more than ever." "That's a nice thought," he says, and the quiet - or at least, as close to quiet as it gets with the massive engines thrumming away below you - stretches as he considers that. "Well, whatever the future holds there, it doesn't really matter until after we're done with this Expedition. And it's only going to get more dangerous from here on out." "You think this is less dangerous than what we'll face in the future?" "Definitely. The Skaven will think this is a Chaos Dwarf trick, the Chaos Dwarves will think this is a Skaven trick. By the time they stop chasing their own shades and realize we're a third party we'll be halfway to Cathay." "What if the Plotter-Daemons change the equation for them?" Three is peace, you remember Qrech saying, but four is feed. "The Chaos Dwarves are straightforward - if there's Daemons roaming around, they'll hunker down or try to capture them. If the Daemons attack the Skaven, they'll watch the Skaven for any weakness to take advantage of. They'll take a guaranteed kick at a distracted enemy over rolling the dice on attacking a heavily-armed convoy. At most they might send a group of Hobgoblins that are out of favour at us to see if our show of strength is genuine, and it very much is." "What do you think of the food situation?" He shrugs. "Where there's horses, there's grass. Where there's grass, there's seeds. If all else fails, stonebread will get us there and back. And Borek worries about the Umgi because he doesn't know Umgi, he thinks they're not Rangers so they're Warriors and they need a supply train. But they're both from Cults that are close enough to being Ursenist that I'd put money on us coming out of the Steppes with more food than we went in with." You nod along to that, resisting the urge to conceal a frown as you contrast that with what Borek said. Maybe all would work out if you left everything alone, but you'd rather not leave things to chance if you don't have to, especially if that just happens to mean you can satisfy your curiosity while doing so. You thank Snorri for his insight and begin to make your way back to the Volans. --- As the Expedition's steam-wagons circle protectively around the Urmskaladrak, you let your Wizards know you're off to do unspecified Grey Wizard things and slip into the night atop a Shadowsteed. You'd considered travelling incognito, but the only way to get there and back in a timely manner is with you atop a horse of Ulgu so there's not a lot of options for other guises. The Grey Order goes to great lengths to prevent knowledge of Shadowmancy from falling into the wrong hands, so the only non-Grey Wizard possibilities that come to mind are Vampires, Beastmen, and Daemons, none of which you're that confident in coming across as for what could be prolonged interactions. So all you've done is left your hat behind and wrapped your staff in cloth to hopefully make you less distinctive. It's not hard to find your way to Uzkulak, as there's a great fire at the peak of the mountain it is carved into to guide both travellers and Chaos Dwarf patrols to it. You'd half-expected a giant skull to have been carved into the face of the mountain with the mouth as the entrance, but as you approach you find it difficult to spot anything that would be out of place on the Karaks you've become familiar with. An odd glow flickering around some of the gun emplacements, perhaps, or the empty plinths that you assume once must have bore statues of the ancestors. For whatever reason the Chaos Dwarves haven't decorated their birthplace in the same megalomanic style as the pictures you've seen of Zharr-Naggrund; most sources assumed that the operative parts of the Hold are below the ground level that guests are allowed in, but a few pass on rumours that the lower levels are sealed, and only opened to throw in someone that has particularly annoyed or displeased them. You wonder if it's true, and wonder what it would mean of a people that have such a desire to put distance between them and the place where they found their God. The gates are closed, but a small door in the base of them is open, and a handful of what must be Hobgoblins shiver and bicker as they crowd around a cooking fire. Physically they look little different from 'normal' Goblins except perhaps a bit taller, but their nature is said to be entirely different, as these are the Goblins that have turned their backs on Gork and Mork, either in favour of Hashut or pure self-interest. East of Kurgan land they're said to control a vast stretch known as the Khanates, and here in the Dark Lands they're possibly the craftiest of those in the service of the Chaos Dwarves. When one spots you it leaps to its feet and starts haranguing the others, distributing kicks and blows like he's just caught them skiving off instead of being one of them a moment ago, and when a figure emerges from the door they fight each other to be the first to speak to it, shouting accusations of inattention in a babble of overlapping not-quite-Khazalid. The figure picks one to backhand and barks orders at the others and before long the Hobgoblins are standing sullenly at attention, one bleeding from a cut lip, and the figure turns his attention to you. At first glance he's a Dwarf, but at second glance the protruding tusks disagree, and at third you notice the tall, pointed hat and the scaled armour extending down to his ankles. This Dwarf is from a culture that diverged from the one you know over six thousand years ago. He looks at you, snorts, and produces a clipboard from behind his beard. "Name, alias, or pseudonym?" he asks, sounding as bored as any gate guard you've ever met. You scramble for anything that's not your actual name or 'Grey'. "Gabriella," you land on. "Gabriella von, er, Nachthafen." "Gabriella von Ernachthafen," he repeats, carefully scrawling runes with a quill. He looks you up and down. "Grey, Black, Thrall, or incognito?" You blink at him. "Incognito," you say. "Buying, selling, or both?" "Buying." "Have you brought any of the following goods to Uzkulak: bound Daemons, precious stones or metals from Nehekhara, any seed, bud, fruit, or cutting from Athel Loren, unshielded warpstone, spherical devices made of brass, Vampire body parts, any item created or possessed by the Skaven Clan Pestilens, gilded skulls made of black bone, anything from the Temple-City of Zlatlan, any mummified bodies of large, frog-like beings, unshielded wyrdstone, any kind of projectile capable of moving on its own, any of Kadon's Scrolls of Binding, golden whistles, instruments stringed with unicorn hair, keys made of crystal, or any sort of stone that glows with a green light?" "No." "Have you brought any slaves with you with any of the following qualities," he looks up at you, "well, do you have any slaves at all?" "No." The Dwarf scans down the page to the next section, and sighs before looking back up. "Gabriella von Ernachthafen from no organization in particular, welcome to Uzkulak," he says, his tone droning and his gaze boring into yours and making it clear he resents you very much for being here and making him do this. "This place is a place of trade and profit. As long as you follow our rules, you may trade and you may profit. Rule One: All exchanges are to be witnessed by an Officiant, and a percentage of the price is to be paid to the Officiant. The percentages for each type of goods can be found on display in the Trade Hall. Rule Two: Do not attack other visitors within Uzkulak, nor within sight of the flames of Uzkulak, under any circumstances. Rule Three: If you stay for more than one day and night, you must rent accommodation. The list of available accommodations is available in the Trade Hall. Breach of any of these rules will result in your death or enslavement, and the forfeiture of all your property. Do you understand these rules?" "Yes," is all you can say. "You have entered at night. Dusk tomorrow is the limit of your stay without renting accommodation. When you exit Uzkulak, ensure that you are recorded by the attendent at that exit, or you may be incorrectly marked for death. Glory to Hashut." "Glory to Hashut," echo the Hobgoblins. You're not sure what to say to that, as you're not going to repeat the glory thing and you're pretty sure thanking him wouldn't be appropriate, so you simply nod and step through the door. A long, wide, and well-lit stone corridor extends deeper into the mountain. Your footsteps echo down the long corridor and you're watching carefully through your magical senses for any sign this might be an extremely long con on you in particular. But as you approach the end of the corridor a growing babble of voices indicates that it might not be a trick, and you step through a final set of doors into what must be the Trade Hall. By noise alone, the hubbub of traders and merchants and mercenaries plying their trade is quite familiar, and the only immediately noticeable difference is that the Khazalid is deeper and more guttural. But with your eyes open it's a series of shocks, one after another. The Marauders you expected, the Ogres and Hobgoblins you theorized. Mutants and zombies, Skaven and Goblins, the Vampire and the group of Dark Elves each capture your attention for a time. But what really surprises you is that a lot of the crowd are people you would not look at twice if you passed them in Barak Varr. Tileans and Estalians, Kislevites and Imperials, even what looks like a group of Bretonnian yeomen squabbling with an unimpressed-looking Dwarf about an axe made of jade. Stalls extend in all directions, many occupied and many not, and it seems like all one needs to do is pick an empty one and unload their goods onto a table to begin trying to convince someone to buy them. Every stall has a bell on one corner, and every so often the ring of a bell sounds and the crowd parts for what must be an Officiant with an abacus and a sack. You weave your way through the crowd, slightly unnerved at how little attention you're getting. Actually, how much everyone goes out of their way to avoid paying too much attention to you, or to anyone else. Everyone seems to pretend not to notice anything about anyone else, their eyes carefully fixed just above or below eye-level unless they have a reason to interact with someone. This isn't the easy comfort of a functioning society, you realize. This is deadly enemies at arm's length and unable to do anything about it under threat of death. The more you look at the crowd, the more you spot the signs - the groups of similar-looking raiders who very carefully circle around each other, the Skaven with scraps of cloths tied around their identifying insignia, the Vampire openly grinning at a band of angry Tileans who are trying their best not to look in his direction. This room is perpetually moments away from violence, and no place here is far from a set of double-doors that you're sure are perpetually ready to spill forth a band of Chaos Dwarf warriors, or perhaps something more exotic, to beat down the offenders and claim their riches and lives. The Chaos Dwarves may always get their percentage, but they're watching for any opportunity to claim the entirety without threatening Uzkulak's reputation of neutrality, and faded bloodstains here and there on the floors and table tell of when they found those opportunities. You also spot signs and doorways leading to ancillary halls dedicated to specialty goods that, for various reasons, aren't suitable for sale in the trade hall. There's a Hall of Livestock, which you visit very briefly as you find an empty room that will likely smell of dung for the rest of time; an extremely weary-seeming Officiant tells you there's nothing currently in, as an Ogre tribe pushed out of their hunting grounds bought everything there was. There's a Hall of Slaves, which you spend some time looking at with a churning gut. Slavery in the abstract is a detestable practice, but actually seeing slaves, chained and suffering and waiting to be bought, is something you're not sure you can witness up close without breaking the restrictions you're currently under. Sure, maybe it would be all greenskins or Chaos Marauders enslaved and sold by their rivals, but it's very possible that they'd be innocents taken in raids on the Old World's coastlines and sailed to Uzkulak to be sold. What do you do then? Beggar the Expedition and then burden it with a swarm of hungry noncombatants? Do something drastic and bold that gets you killed for nothing? Try to match your skills at thievery and deception against the greed and paranoia of the worshippers of Hashut, who have spent millennia at Uzkulak honing and practicing their skills and procedures to prevent that exact occurrence? You turn away, at least for now, putting the matter out of your mind with the discipline that the Grey Order taught you. There's still another chance for your stated goal here to find success: the Hall of Bulk Goods. Not every ship taken at sea carries gold and jewels, not every caravan carries ivory and silks. Sometimes the sort of cargo that's heavier than it is valuable is burned or sunk, but the more disciplined, or more desperate, of raiders takes those goods here to try to find a buyer, because Zharr-Naggrund always hungers for raw materials. You make your way through the hall where a handful of bored Officiants sit behind tables covered with samples; apparently the goods are left in the care of the Officiants for a fee, and if the goods remain here for long enough and the fee consumes enough of the value of the goods, Zharr-Naggrund buys them. There's little that won't be taken if the price gets low enough, because there's little that can't be burned, smelted, or fed to slaves. You find ingots, furniture, bolts of various cloths, weapons, armour, wooden boards, even chunks of ore, most of low quality and much of it water-damaged. Finally you find what you're looking for in a corner stacked high with ropes and sails: a slimy chunk of brined meat that has long since oozed out its moisture into a growing stain on the table. You ask the price, and it'd be slightly high if the barrel had just been sealed, let alone for something that was shipped for an unknown time, stolen in an unknown location, shipped an unknown distance to Uzkulak, and has been sitting in storage for an unknown period. But it's meat, and the quantity the Officiant says is available would feed the Expedition for about one and a half weeks, leaving you slightly better off than the original schedule. After making your decision about the meat, you return to the main hall and do another circuit, this time with an eye for the goods rather than the crowd. There's a huge array of weaponry, including some extremely fine pieces made and sold by Chaos Dwarves, from the traditional swords, axes and maces, to exotic weapons from distant countries you couldn't put a name to, to firearms of every type, including a tarnished bronze cannon with barnacles growing over one side. These are the goods that get the most attention from the crowd. But you're not here to trade your stolen goods for a better weapon to steal even more goods, you're here, at least partially, in the hopes of finding something unexpected and exotic. So you turn away from the crowds and delve into the odd little corners, looking for the esoteric, the unusual, the unique. What you mostly find is the counterfeit. There are 'power stones' that are clearly sea-polished rocks. There's a gaudy scimitar said to be made from Ithilmar, but you can leave a mark in the metal with your fingernail. There's books of magic aplenty, including a 'Book of Nagash' that has a very intimidating skull on the cover, but radiates so little taint you doubt it's seen Morrsleib, let alone the hand of the Great Necromancer. 'Dragon eggs' that contain not the barest flicker of life, a 'magic scroll from the fabled land of Albion' that is plainly in Eltharin and consists of a complaint about an apparently insufficient set of repairs made to the writer's roof, a map to 'Elven treasure' that would, if your memories of geography are correct, land the treasure-seeker near the foot of the Dragon Spine Mountains, which you're sure Caledorians would disapprove of quite strongly and almost certainly violently. But it's not all fake. Or at the very least, some of it is faked well enough to fool even your scrutiny. The first piece that causes your eyebrows to rise is a four-fingered arm made of solid gold and covered in sigils you don't recognize. You can sense dormant power within it, and a lot of it - but too tightly contained to tell what sort, except that it's not Dhar. The fingers are razor-sharp talons and the palm has a raised circle you're sure is where that power you sense is output. But though the Norscan selling it does not seem to know anything about its magical properties, he does know solid gold when he sees it, and that puts a solid floor on the price. Eight hundred gold coins is a shockingly exorbitant price for a complete mystery and it's not like you're short of strange things to prod at, but you suppose if all else fails you could resell it for melt value. The second is from a Naggarothi Corsair that won't stop smirking at you, and among the goods scattered haphazardly across the table is some sort of nut that glows so brightly with Ghyran that it gives you a headache in your soul to focus on it. Your questions uncover that the Corsair got it from 'somewhere', where it belonged to 'someone', and was stolen 'a while ago'. You're starting to understand why the Ulthuani don't get along with these people. The price is a jaw-dropping one thousand gold coins, and your shock and outrage at that only seems to make the Corsair more delighted, which leads you to suspect that's why they gave you that price. But you must admit you've never seen so much magic concentrated in so small a form. The third and final curiosity is a set of books and papers apparently taken from an Ulthuani explorer who ventured into Lustria and the Southlands to investigate the strange lizard-folk that are said to reside there. That she took rubbings and sketches instead of the golden plaques themselves might be why she survived so long while engaged in such a dangerous endeavour, but it was no protection from the other hazards of the world, and apparently a Chaos Dwarf ship caught her vessel off the Shifting Mangrove Coastline on the eastern side of the Southlands. Her fate is unknown and probably tragic, but her rather extensive writings have been sent here to see if they can find a buyer. If they don't, they're likely destined to feed a forge somewhere. --- Does Mathilde visit the Hall of Slaves? [ ] HALL: Yes [ ] HALL: No Does Mathilde buy the barrels of salted meat using Borek's money? [ ] MEAT: Yes [ ] MEAT: No Does Mathilde purchase the golden arm for 800 gold coins? [ ] ARM: Yes [ ] ARM: No Does Mathilde purchase the Ghyran nut for 1000 gold coins? [ ] NUT: Yes [ ] NUT: No Does Mathilde purchase the explorer's writings for 200 gold coins? [ ] PAPERS: Yes [ ] PAPERS: No - There will be a two hour moratorium. - For reference, Mathilde's current wealth weighs in at about 2800 gold coins. That is not the money the Expedition has, that is the money she has back at K8P and so can reimburse the Expedition with upon their return. - The phrase 'no harm in looking' should be avoided when debating the Hall of Slaves. Mathilde is a strongly moral person in her own way, and she follows the God of freedom from tyranny. What she sees could leave her unbalanced for some time. It could leave a permanent mark on her. It could put her in a position where she has to choose between choosing to do something risky and/or expensive and/or strategically unsound, or being unable to look at herself in a mirror. - The remaining interaction and exploration will continue after business here is concluded. - If bought, transporting the food will not be a problem - it would only take a few gold coins to hire some of the visiting traders to haul the cargo a few hours southwards.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 11: Seventh-and-Final-Combe

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] MEAT: Yes [*] PAPERS: Yes [*] HALL: No [*] NUT: Yes [*] ARM: Yes In the end, you turn your gaze away from the Hall of Slaves. There will always be more evils in the world than you are capable of addressing, and a half-baked attempt to fix this one would just make it less likely that you're able to fix the one you've invested years of planning towards. That logic isn't very effective at quelling the part of you calling it cowardice as you literally walk away from the enslaved and the suffering, though. --- The meat is an easy purchase. It looks horrific to you, but you're accustomed to being able to go for a leisurely ride to an inn, restaurant, or bakery when hunger makes itself known. Those at sea are not so fortunate, and it's largely upon barreled salt meat like this that they feed themselves for months or sometimes even years at a time. Between the Light and Amber magic at the Expedition's disposal there's little harm in testing it on the wolves and Demigryphs, and at worst it won't be any more inedible than the few precious stones you trade it for. The books and papers are almost as easy, as between their uniqueness, rare subject matter, and their fate if they aren't purchased, it takes very little thought for you to decide to add it to your haul. The golden arm and the Ghyran seed are less convincing, but in the end you decide to purchase both, your curiousity outweighing your financial prudence and your dislike of the Druchii's smirk. Even if you're never able to puzzle out the arm you'll still be able to get a significant amount of the cost back by selling it for its gold content, and even if the seed is some sort of trick, figuring out how that much magic was crammed into so small a container would still have value. Transporting your purchases is simple enough, as you simply claim a stall, write 'seeking caravan for one-day transportation contract' in the air with Aethyric Projection, give a price that's double the usual rate, and put your feet up for the few minutes it takes for someone to approach you. You wouldn't trust the Tilean in question as far as you could throw him since he's here in Uzkulak, but then he could say the same for you, so you ring the bell, hand over a portion of the fee to an Officiant, and see about getting the barrels and books loaded up into the caravan that you're sure he'll claim has been to Cathay and back when it returns to Kislev. With the golden arm in one of those barrels so none of them have to wrestle with temptation. You make sure to confirm with the watchdwarf that Gabriella von Ernachthafen has departed Uzkulak and travel in the wake of the caravan, keeping enough of an eye on them to keep them from getting any clever ideas. Shortly after dawn, the Expedition trundling along the Skull Road comes across you sitting atop a stack of barrels in the middle of the empty wasteland as you skim through the books. You project an air of aloof smugness as you ignore the many bewildered questions directed your way, which redouble after someone finds the markings on one of the barrels confirming that they came from a Marienburg trade ship. The Dwarves are familiar enough with their vessels at this point that it only takes them a few moments to swing out the davits and start hoisting the barrels aboard and it doesn't take long before the Expedition is underway once more, and you find a moment away from prying eyes to return the remaining precious stones to Borek, and pass word to him that there's apparently a displaced and hungry Ogre tribe somewhere in the area. --- Aboard the Urmskaladrak, Gotrek is supervising the efforts to mount a boiling contraption onto the engines so that most of the salt can be boiled out of the meat. "Won't ask how you did it, but I'm glad you did," he says to you. "You were worried about the food situation?" "Worried?" He harrumphs. "I've worked with Snorri before, I know Rangers can find food anywhere there's food to be found, and the manling Knights seem poured from the same crucible. But I'm more comfortable the less variables there are. It wouldn't have taken very many delays to start raising questions about whether we can even reach somewhere where food can be foraged." "Three weeks from Dukhlys to the Steppes," you say with a nod. "It should have been two at most," he grumbles. "The four-wheel design would have had us halfway back to Karak Kadrin by now, as long as every road on the way was solid and perfectly maintained stone at no more than a three degree incline. I should have pushed back more against the sort of Grandmasters that haven't seen the sun since they were Apprentices, but there was trouble enough with me being appointed Head Engineer and having to relocate the project would have ended it there and then. Even though the only reason it was me and not one of them was because none of them would do it." "I've heard Karag Dum has a lot of detractors among traditionalists," you prompt. "Folks are always ready to believe the worst of those they've failed," he says with a shrug. "If Karag Dum wasn't worth protecting, there's no shame in failing to have protected it. And it's not like they're able to level a Grudge in defence of their good name." You nod silently. It's a reasonable conclusion and possibly even a correct one, and it doesn't require the degree of culpability that Thorek's theory requires. "So, this will get the salt out of the meat?" "Most of it," he grumbles, but in a less morose tone; a Dwarf grumbling about how much better they could do something with more time or better resources is always a happier Dwarf than a Dwarf grumbling about the decline of the Karaz Ankor. "There are cauldrons and ovens that feed off the heat of the boiler already of course, but we're going to need to boil these a lot to get them edible. At sea they'd steep them first, but that means changing the water every few hours and we don't have an endless supply of water with lower salinity than the meat, so that's out. And we can't just toss it into the main boiler, that's designed to be damn near a closed system, and introducing salt and meat fragments would go wrong very quickly. So we build a secondary boiler and condenser and run them off the firebox, boiling off most of the water and draining off the brine and refilling it from the reclaimed fresh water. Before long we'll be left with boiled and only moderately salted meat and a tub of saturated brine that would be maybe eight times saltier than seawater. We can use that to preserve any new meat that comes in that's in excess of what can be eaten, or if nothing else, sell it to a saltern or a pickler on the way back home." You nod, impressed at such an efficient solution at such short notice. "Very efficient. Nothing's wasted." He snorts and folds his arms. "Of course. We aren't making it home if we get in the habit of wasting." "What do you think we'll find at Karag Dum?" "I don't. Never been, never met anyone who has apart from Borek, so not enough data. Though it does bother me that Borek is becoming more nervous, rather than less, as we get closer. I wonder if he would prefer them to have been destroyed than to have found an unconventional way of surviving." "The counterfeit Slayers from Karak Vlag do highlight some ugly possibilities. Speaking of, any thoughts on the return of Karak Vlag?" "Not really," he says with a shrug. "Don't get me wrong, it was the right thing to do and I'm glad we did it, but the Karaz Ankor and I have parted ways. My Ankor is my family now, and they're no better or worse off than before with a Dwarfhold on the other side of Kislev back in existence." "Ah." Gotrek apparently takes this as an unvoiced question. "My wife is Clanless. My Clan wouldn't allow her to join it in marriage, so I left it." You consider the offer that Gotri said he's willing to extend. "Do you regret it?" He shakes his head firmly. "I regret that they made it necessary. Never my response." --- The Expedition has had less than a week away from copiously available snowmelt, so there's no need for water at this time. That doesn't stop Snorri from deciding to send a team to investigate the northernmost of the Zorn Uzkul lakes so you'll know for the return trip whether it can be relied upon as a source of water. It comes as a surprise to you that wholesome water supplies can exist in the middle of Chaos Dwarf territory, but you suppose that even Dwarves would think twice before taking on an aquifer. Either that, or Zharr-Naggrund is reliant on this water downstream. You travel with them to the lake, more for the company than out of safety concerns, though it's likely that if you asked there'd be a significant disagreement over who's protecting who. Once you arrive, the eldest of the Rangers takes a very cautious sip, swishes it around in his mouth cautiously, then nods and swallows. The Rangers all fill up the waterskins they've brought with them for this purpose, apparently intending to create a type of ale that the Rangers of Karak Vlag would only make from the waters of these lakes. What you know of brewing says that if the Expedition suffers no further delays, it will be about ready to drink by the time you're almost back at High Pass, and you wonder if the plan is to drink it or to leave it for Karak Vlag in the hopes that they'd take it as further evidence they're back in reality. Perhaps both. You part ways with them as they head back to the Expedition and follow the trickle of an outflow as it carves a deep furrow through the empty landscape, galloping along its winding length for a couple of hours until it and you reach the river flowing from the largest of the four, and then three more hours following that until it reaches the second largest of the lakes, which is large enough that you can't see the opposite shore and it takes you two hours to circle around it until you reach the outflow. From there it's another hour until you reach the unnamed falls that disappear into a ravine carved in the southern edge of the Zorn Uzkul plateau, plummeting downwards in a great waterfall taller than most mountains. Somewhere on the western side of that ravine is Clan Moulder's Sixth-Combe, and somewhere on the eastern is the Seventh-and-Final-Combe. This is Clan Moulder's front line against the Chaos Dwarves, from where they raid and are in turn raided by Zharr-Naggrund to the southeast, which is visible as a great column of smoke on the horizon. Actually reaching Seventh-and-Final-Combe from up here would be much easier said than done for someone that isn't capable of short-range translocation. You shroud yourself in invisibility and hop from niche to recess to tunnel, searching for the one from which unfortunate Skaven do their best to extend a giant funnel into the enormous flow of water every other day to top up the water supplies of the Skaven base. It's not hard to confirm the correct one when you find it, as the Skaven seem to have an impulse to carve their Runes into the walls of every tunnel they occupy, and you follow the three-sided Rune of the Skaven and the overlapping triple diamond of Clan Moulder into the darkness deep underground. You've braced yourself for the smell of a place teeming with Skaven, but what you actually encounter is the overwhelming smell of blood and brimstone, causing you to redouble your guard. When the passage finally opens up into a main chamber, you find yourself looking upon a fresh battlefield being picked over by Hobgoblins and watched over by what must be a Bull Centaur, the giant creatures 'blessed' by Hashut with the torso of a Dwarf and the body of a bull. Far from the drunken idiocy of the Centaurs of the Beastmen, this creature stares over the Hobgoblins with eyes alight with cruel intelligence, occasionally barking out an order that leaves them scurrying to obey. Looking over the field, you note that most of what you see are regular Skaven, and most scrawny enough to suggest a low position within the Clan's pecking order. Either the more exotic bodies have already been dragged away, or they were never a part of this conflict to begin with, which leads you to believe that you might have found a clue as to what happened with the Plotter-Daemons. You can hear Qrech's voice in your memory: two is war, three is peace. The status quo here is war, and it's one that has long since solidified into a stalemate from which both sides can harvest exotic slaves and test subjects. The introduction of the Daemons would normally bring peace, but the Daemons did not arrive somewhere equidistant between Clan Moulder and Zharr-Naggrund, they would have arrived around Second- or Third-Combe, introducing a second set of two. Clan Moulder was beset on a new front and withdrew its strongest troops and most lethal beasts to respond, and though they undoubtedly would have tried to keep up the appearance of strength against the Chaos Dwarves, they managed to see through the deception and attacked while their old foe was weakened. Perhaps the bulk of their forces is further west, carving deeper into the chain of bases until they reach the Plotter-Daemons, or perhaps this is the extent of their ambition and they are already returning home to count the spoils. Considering the Hobgoblins are down to dragging away the bodies for what little meat there is on their bones, you doubt there's much left to find here - but there's no harm in trying. Piecing together a mental map from what Qrech's stories have revealed about his old home, you skirt your way around the gore and deeper into the base. [Rolling] [Rolling] Your explorations quickly reveal that the base has already been quite thoroughly looted, including the vaults, cells, laboratories and armouries, but there's one place that you're hoping they wouldn't have been able to find yet: the hidden safe in the Warlord's personal quarters that featured prominently in his story of how he replaced the Warlord before him. The room has already been torn apart, with the wall hangings and carpets Qrech described already disappeared and probably destined for either a Chaos Dwarf's own quarters or Uzkulak for resale, and the vast aquarium that takes up one wall has been broken and the gilled rats that called it home are gone. You reach through the broken glass and pull up the tiny sword lodged in the ribcage of an upset-looking model skeleton, and with a few clicks that make their way through the walls, part of the wall swings noiselessly out, revealing a safe dial. 13-13-13 gets you in, because the way to change the code had been lost with Qrech's predecessor when he was entombed alive in this very safe. Thankfully, Qrech was practical enough to have said predecessor removed after he had cemented his new position instead of leaving him in as a trophy, and there's only a faint whiff of decay as you reach in to pull out several heavy sacks. Inside you find golden Kislevite Ducats, most bearing the face of Tzar Vladimir Bokha on one side and all the Winter Palace on the reverse, likely either stolen in raids on Kislev or from Kislevite traders bound for Cathay. The quality of the minting is very good as Kislev has always sourced its dies from Dwarfholds rather than making their own, but their purity is very slightly less than Imperial coins. Your rough estimation from their weight says that they're not quite enough to make up for your recent purchases, but at least you won't have to tithe any of it. With your newfound wealth you make your way back out of the warren, and just in time too, because the Bull Centaur has apparently called a break and his Hobgoblins are busy building a cookfire that's soon to fill the tunnels with the smell of burning rat-flesh. --- The few careful tests indicate that though the wolves and Demigryphs aren't exactly enthused by the salt meat, they'll eat it, and after they show no signs of side-effects worse than a certain amount of grouchiness it is distributed to the rest of the beasts and to anyone else willing to try it. You give it a shot yourself, and though it's still hellishly salty, you have to admit you've eaten worse, mostly from Altdorf street vendors. This leaves the Expedition with approximately four weeks of provisions remaining while two weeks away from Karag Dum. That gives a fair bit of wriggle-room should anything go wrong. The Expedition has reached the eastern end of Zorn Uzkul, and faces what might be the most laborious part: the switchbacking ascent to the Great Steppes. This is the leg of the Expedition where the speed of the steam-wagons will reduce to a crawl and the convoy might be most vulnerable to attack, and the quality of the road is likely to be extremely variable. At the top of the ascent is the land of the Iron Wolves, the Kurgan tribe who are said to serve a Dragon Ogre and who spend much of their time watching and raiding the Skull Road. By the end of the week you should hopefully be at the edge of Dolgan territory, ready to begin your final sprint northwards to Karag Dum. The four with the most votes will be chosen. Spend time getting to know: [ ] Thane Borek Forkbeard [ ] Head Engineer Gotrek Gurnisson [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Use Rite of Way to ease the ascent - Will only be necessary during the roughest patches [ ] Scout the lands of the Iron Wolves [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Iron Wolves [ ] Investigate the 'Windfall' with the Light Wizards - Where the Winds blowing from the north descend to ground level, which is only know to happen in mountainous terrain: here, the Mountains of Mourne, the Goromadny Mountains, and northern Norsca. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - If you have any other ideas for useful ways for Mathilde to spend her time, let me know. - Mathilde's debt to Borek is to be settled with solid Dwarven coinage after she returns to K8P. - There were 1,350 ducats in the bags. The Kislevite ducat is worth about 95% of an Imperial crown. Spoiler: Expedition map

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 12: The Ascent

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Use Rite of Way to ease the ascent [*] Investigate the 'Windfall' with the Light Wizards [*] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [*] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger The road winding up from the Zorn Uzkul plateau to the Great Steppes is no more treacherous than anywhere else along the path except for one aspect: the incline. Conventional wagons can manage it more or less fine, albeit sometimes through double-teaming the wagons or having Ogre mercenaries help push, but those strategies aren't really viable for the behemoths that are the steam-wagons. All that can be done mechanically is to stoke the fire up and hope for the best, but the loss of traction from a pothole or fresh gully here could meaningfully slow the steam-wagon down where on level terrain it would simply coast over it. So this is an ideal place to first deploy your Rite of Way: where the terrain is troubling enough that it would help, but not so rough that it's vital. You displace Borek from the prow position on the Alriksson, mentally prepare yourself, and as the wagon begins to climb and the engine redoubles in volume you let Ulgu flow through you into your staff and pour onto the road ahead. [Casting Rite of Way: Learning, 21+28=49.] After the first shift, you're glad you decided to get the practice in here. The steam-wagons need to be fairly well spaced out to give each of them time to adjust to any change in speed from the wagon in front of them, and maintaining the trail for the full convoy turns out to be a lot more mentally taxing than you had expected. Until you get into the proper rhythm there's several times where the tailing wagon isn't covered and starts to fall behind and needs to catch up at the next bend, where being able to see the road to make the turn means the spell can't be applied. But there's an unexpected benefit to this in that having the final wagon act as an inadvertent control subject demonstrates the better traction that the hidden path provides, which mollifies concerns and reduces grumbling to background levels. The wagons themselves turn out to exceed expectations when it comes to managing the slopes, the sixteen driving wheels and twelve carrying wheels turning out to maintain traction much better than the Engineers had expected from their tests with the four-wheel designs. By the second day they've accepted the use of the Rite of Way and are updating their projections to show at least a day saved on the ascent, possibly more. The scouts bring in detailed information on the incline and the condition of the path ahead, and you're able to work out a schedule where you'll be assisting with the trickiest parts without having to completely exhaust yourself by dedicating all your daylight hours to the task. --- Esbern and Seija had been able to identify an area of Windfall while out scouting with the Knights of Taal's Fury, so on a day when the Winds are blowing and you're not needed for a suitable stretch you and the Light Wizards fill rucksacks with esoteric equipment and a lunch and make your way east-southeast to where the phenomenon was spotted. You might be able to cautiously make your way across this terrain atop a Shadowsteed but you doubt the Light Wizards would be able to, so there's nothing for it but a good long hike with Skywalk to bridge some of the trickier gaps. "So," Egrimm says curiously as the five of you walk around the mountain in your way. "That spell, the Rite of Way. Is it a ritual?" "No, despite the name, it's a sustained spell. Low-level Battle Magic." "Are you consciously controlling the whole thing?" "No, Ulgu is able to detect breaks in uniformity, so I have individual instances of a stripped-down Skywalk that get placed wherever there's a break in that. I just have to control where the fog is to act as a constraint on the spell and supply a steady stream of new instances." "I've seen how far you have to extend it to cover the convoy, that must be a difficult visualization." "Not as much as you might think, when it's a straight road at a relatively low speed. Then the tough part is output and consistency. It would be a different story for something faster moving that could need to change direction suddenly." "But it would still be possible?" "In theory. It's yet to be tested on a battlefield." "It's new?" "Put the finishing touches on it earlier this year." There's silence in response to that, and you glance up from the path ahead to see Egrimm looking at you in surprise. "Well," he eventually says, "I suppose that's why I haven't encountered it before. That's an impressive spell to have made from scratch." You shrug. "It's yet to have a proper field-testing. This stretch is just a warm-up, it's the steppes that will really put it through its paces." When you finally reach the spot that Esbern and Seija had found, the Light Wizards trailing behind and in various stages of exhaustion, you take a moment to appreciate the sight that would be invisible to anyone without Magesight. This is where seven of the eight Winds blowing from the north descend from overhead to reach ground level and begin to follow the preferences and patterns you're familiar with, and though a waterfall would be the closest comparison, water's descent is extremely straightforward compared to streams of the Winds trying to keep their distance from other Winds and merging with streams of the same Wind in a chaotic twirling descent, and then scattering as they hit ground level and break apart from the sudden impact. The impact point is thick with Dhar from the times when velocity overcame natural repulsion, but the same velocity that causes the Dhar prevents most of the Winds from being drawn into the morass of blended Winds lurking at the bottom of the cliff like a sinkhole of dark magic. "It's always mountains," Egrimm says as he begins to unpack his rucksack. "All across the upper hemisphere, there's always mountains to interrupt the flow of magic overhead. Here, the Mountains of Mourn, Norsca... I've read that even Naggaroth has a chain of mountains to its north that performs the same function. There's only two exceptions I know of: where the Northern Wastes meet the Great Ocean, and the Great Bastion of Cathay. Neither of which we know much about." "So are mountains actually required for magic to descend, or is it an accident of geography?" you ask. "That's the question. Those that believe the world was made with purpose tend towards the former, those that don't often also believe that there's similar Winds coming from the Southern Wastes that don't have a chain of mountains to interrupt them. Needless to say, there's not many expeditions to try to map the geography of the Southern Wastes, though apparently the High Elves have an outpost on a spur near Khuresh." He removes a large crystal wrapped in wire from his pack, and begins to examine it carefully. "How does your Magesight manifest?" you ask curiously. "Visual, which is actually not that common in the Light Order - we initiate early so most don't have a chance to develop their own before they're shaped by the Choruses. Citharus has auditory like most, Timpania has olfactory, and Barbitus has... what was it?" "Visceral, Magister," he says, not looking up from rooting through his rucksack. "And how is all this manifesting for you?" Barbitus frowns. "Hard to say, but it's doing a lot of it. I think I'll be skipping lunch." "Remember to take notes, we don't get many chances to accumulate data on this phenomenon." Egrimm looks downwards at where the plummeting Winds terminate. "And to prove it, that's a much-debated phenomenon we can confirm the existence of. Natural Dhar. There's plenty that argue that it only comes about as a result of unnatural influences or ill intent." "Why do the Winds fall here, though?" you ask, looking upwards. "That's the question, isn't it? Everywhere else we know of, it's easy to say that it's the mountains interrupting the flow of magic, and that's the most popular theory. But this peak is below the ground level of the Great Steppes and it's still happening here. Even the Azyr is dipping before splitting off from the other seven to remain higher." "Something metaphysical, then? The nature of mountains weighing down the Winds?" "Could be. But that's a problem with the Colleges, they're so centralized in Altdorf that most of the Wizards that weave theories never go further afield than the Grey Mountains, and that's a very tame range, comparatively. So they've never really encountered the real thing." "Well, let's gather some data for them," you say, frowning as you consider the coloured wax pencils you've brought with you. You're not much of an artist, but trying to turn what you're seeing into words seems a lot more daunting than trying to sketch it out. A few industrious hours pass as copious notes are taken, esoteric instruments consulted, and one crystal shard is very carefully dipped into a Wind stream with Move cast by the miniature choir. To you the choir was more interesting than the results, as between the three of them they managed to keep two instances of the spell on the crystal while the third took a break, rotating so that every minute each of them had rotated in and out once. Getting them in sync enough for that to work must have been a hellishly difficult process, but it seems like it would be extremely useful in all sorts of ways. But once the observations are taken and the lunches have been eaten it's time to head back once more, with the three junior Light Wizards ranging ahead while you hang back to talk to Egrimm. "How's Barbitus doing?" you ask him. "Not well, today isn't the first meal he's missed and I don't think he's sleeping. But it doesn't seem like it's outright festering either. I think as long as the voyage continues to be prosaic, he'll have recovered by the time we arrive at Karag Dum." "I think if we do come under attack here, it will be by more mundane forces than we saw from Karak Vlag. Do you think he'd have trouble engaging normal horsemen?" He shakes his head. "Choir discipline runs deep. Once he gets casting with the others, he'll be fine." You nod thoughtfully, your eyes on Barbitus as he hops from rock to rock. "Glad to hear it." --- Journeyman Cyrston von Danling is the only Journeymanling who seems unmoved by his taste of combat with the Daemons, and that has drawn your curiosity and perhaps a bit of your suspicion. The paranoid part of you wonders if 'seasonal attunement' is perhaps a very convenient excuse for his spells growing in power as he approaches the Chaos Wastes, though you do know from Panoramia that it is an existing phenomenon. So you put aside some time to approach him as he watches the terrain rolling past. "Fascinating plateau," he says, staring down at the Zorn Uzkul that is laid out below. "What could it be that motivates the great beasts of the mountains to come here to die?" "No idea," you say. "I've heard of something similar far to the south for dragons, but that seems more cultural than instinctual, since they stopped doing it after the Coming of Chaos." "An ancient migratory path that was once survivable, but no longer is? A herding instinct that has them trying to follow the same path as the great caravans, unaware that the caravans carry food and water with them? Some sort of curse or ambient energies?" He shakes his head. "Such a fascinating mystery, and one so dangerous to even reach and look upon." "There's a lot of those in the world," you say with a nod. "I hope so. Travelling would get boring if you only ever encountered things you already understood." He smiles and turns his eyes away from the plateau. "What can I do for you, Lady Magister?" "Just wanted to check in with you. I'm juggling a lot of hats right now, but one of them is being head of the Wizards on this Expedition." He nods and smiles. "I suppose it can't be easy to manage Journeymen while also somehow looting a Marienburg ship. Nothing to worry about with me, I couldn't be happier to have seen the famous Zorn Uzkul, and soon the Great Steppes. I'm told they look something like northern Kislev, but on a much vaster scale." "No lingering effects from the battle? The effects of a Higher Daemon of the Tempter can be rather subtle..." He shakes his head firmly. "Not that I've noticed. If anything, well, not to get too graphic, but that sort of thing is trending downwards as spring gives way to summer, as it always does." You decide against pursuing that line of enquiry too closely. "Do the seasons still have such an effect, even this far north?" He nods. "We've never encountered a place where it didn't. I once read an account of a Jade Wizard that travelled to Sudenburg and was still subject to seasonal variations in mood and magic even though the weather there didn't reflect it. The current atheological theory is that the rhythm of the seasons is constant and powerful enough to keep Wizards in sync with it no matter the distance." You nod, considering his words. Your first interview with him did reveal that he considers himself something of an explorer, so you suppose it's no surprise he'd focus on the landscape rather than the events. And maybe his seasonal attunement keeps him centered in such a way that the periphery of a Tempter aura couldn't get its hooks in. You're not fully convinced, but it's your job to never be fully convinced. "And the theological one?" you ask curiously. He sighs. "The theological one is busy being fought over by the Rhyans and the Shallyans and the Ishernosians," he says with a shrug. "Do you take a side in that?" "Not if I can help it. I think the march of the seasons is powerful enough to venerate it without needing to put a face and a name on it." You nod. You've yet to discuss the matter with a Jade Wizard that didn't keep out of that disagreement, though you suppose it makes sense that those that travel far from their home College would be those that don't want to get involved in the major internal disagreement of their Order. You're glad that the Grey College didn't inherit any major institutional baggage from the pre-Teclisean era, as it seems to be a huge weight on the mind of Jade Wizards. You thank Cyrston for his time and leave him to his study of the landscape. --- Sir Ruprecht the Younger is a hard man to get a hold of, as he seems to spend every waking moment on patrol, giving orders to those about to go on patrol, or receiving information from those that have just come back from patrol. It's good that he's so dedicated to his work, but that it requires so much constant hands-on management from him suggests either internal troubles or a lack of confidence, though you suppose their performance back in High Pass would justify a certain amount of close scrutiny. You finally manage to pull him aside in between patrols and it doesn't take much probing from you before he's voicing his thoughts on the battle. "It was that illusion," he says, shaking his head. "We were ready to charge in there and kill everything that was underdressed and beardless, but suddenly there were those heretic Slayers, and our own Slayers were cut down so quickly by them. That was something nobody could have predicted, but they should still have reacted. But they didn't, not until I all but threw them at the fortifications." "Inability to adapt to changing circumstances?" you ask. He nods. "I think we've grown too used to predictable foes, the Orcs of Iron Rock and the Dragon Ogres of Thunder Mountain. That's why back in the Empire, only half of us would be on guard duty at any one time, and the other half would be out striking down the enemies of man. Beastmen one week, cultists the next, and Forest Goblins after that. But ever since we settled down in Ulrikadrin the only time we've done anything but skirmish with the neighbouring brutes is during the battles at Karak Eight Peaks." You nod. "There's only so much drilling and skirmishes can do. But that might be unavoidable. You don't have an entire province to fight across any more." "We might," he says. "There's been rumblings from Barak Varr about Mad Dog Pass - it's the last of the southern passes that isn't controlled by the Dwarves, so it's the destination of choice for those that would rather take their chances than pay the Dwarves their cut. But that much wealth attracts the wrong sort of attention, and there's rumours of bandit-kingdoms along the Howling River. And it's a very small step from bandit to pirate, and Barak Varr definitely doesn't like that sort of thing. It was just talk when we left, but after Karak Vlag I've been thinking about it a lot." You frown, consulting a mental map. "With Karak Vlag back, Mad Dog Pass would be the only overland route to the east outside of Dwarven control." "And they last had that level of control, I've heard, before the birth of the Empire." "Long before," you say with a nod. "Karak Norn was founded by the Clans that once watched over the Silver Road and Mad Dog Pass." "And that could be where the Winter Wolves fit in. Mad Dog Pass is the only Pass without a major Dwarfhold on it. Seems better suited to being watched over by cavalry than by Dwarves on foot." "That would put you in close proximity with Night Goblins and Forest Goblins. There's your unpredictable foes." "Bloody Spear and Black Spider tribes," he says, nodding. "That way we have a chance to still be Knights in a few generations, rather than monks with puppies or feudal lords with pretensions." "You wouldn't be the only ones to benefit. If the Dwarves took a cut of every caravan from Ind and Cathay... well, even Dwarven vaults would be swelled by that." You consider that for a moment, then turn the conversation back to the original topic. "Have any of the Knights been troubled by the battle? Not so much by their performance, but from the influence of the Daemons?" He shakes his head firmly. "Our martial skills may have slipped, but our faith is stronger than ever now that we're far from the politics of Middenheim. A few are troubled, but they already know the prayers and meditations that will guide them past it, and our more experienced brothers are watching over them." "Glad to hear it. I'm sure they'll have a chance to prove themselves once more soon." You clap him on the back and leave him to it, and it doesn't take long before he's hurrying back to his men. Perhaps a slight inclination to over-management, but you suppose that's only natural after overseeing a failing like that. --- You're resting atop the Alriksson as the caravan negotiates its way around a corner when it happens. By the time it's audible over the engines of the steam-wagons, the clattering of falling stone has escalated into a full-blown avalanche, and there's a roar of draconic disapproval as the ground below the largest of the steam-wagons gives way, dragging it over the edge and out of sight as an extremely disgruntled dragon flaps his way free, carrying an even more disgruntled Elf in his talons. As the silence drags on you become more and more horrified, until at last there's an earth-shaking crash as the Urmskaladrak hits the ground far, far below. It only takes you a moment to collect yourself before you're shaping Ulgu and appear at the edge of the cliff, then several more times as you jump from outcropping to outcropping until you reach the shattered vessel. To your shock there are already a couple of survivors crawling free of the wreckage, but you take just a moment to confirm that none of them are Gotrek before you turn to cast your eyes over the surrounding terrain. You can't see him, nor can you see the speck of Shyish that would probably indicate where he fell if he was atop the steam-wagon at the time, but from so far a drop he could have ended up any distance from the wreck itself. And if he was inside... Time becomes meaningless as you do everything you can to negotiate a nightmarish maze of twisted metal and gore as you try to find survivors, or more accurately one survivor. Gotrek's knowledge of steam-wagons is irreplaceable, and without it there's that much less chance of being able to correct anything that goes wrong with them. But you're keenly aware that if he didn't survive the fall you have only a few minutes before he's beyond the grasp of the Seed of Regrowth, and though you've pulled out two more Dwarves that somehow survived the fall free of the wreckage, neither of them are Gotrek. And none of the recognizable corpses you've found are, either. By the time you emerge once more, the Winter Wolves have wound their way back down the road and are starting to help retrieve and treat the wounded. You wipe the blood from your hands as best you can and start to numbly reassess the chances of the Expedition, because as soon as you and the survivors return to the convoy, there will be a debate over whether this has just ended it. --- - The Urmskaladrak is completely destroyed. - 16 Engineers, including Gotrek Gurnisson, died in the fall. - Five Engineers survived, and will join the crew of the remaining steam-wagons - Asarnil and Deathfang are unharmed. - Most of the Expedition's food requirements are for the mounts, so this has a negligible effect on food consumption. - About one week of food was aboard the Urmskaladrak. None is recoverable. - About two weeks of food remain on the other steam-wagons. This is their maximum capacity. - Karag Dum is approximately one week away. - Kislev is approximately three weeks away. - The scouts have not encountered any Iron Wolves, but if there are any in the area, they would have heard the falling Urmskaladrak. - The Kriestov and Alexis are behind the rockslide area, and will need to negotiate the now narrower road if the Expedition presses on. - The Alriksson, Magnus, and Volans are ahead of the rockslide area, and will need to negotiate the now narrower road if the Expedition turns back. Ergo, the Expedition should... [ ] Press on [ ] Turn back [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Convoy dicerolls: 1 on a d100 for cornering, 8 on a d100 for recovery, got the Urmskaladrak on a d6, rolled another d6 for how far a drop (higher better) and got a 1. Deathfang got an 82 for his reaction. Gotrek's survival roll, everyone else's, Mathilde's S&R.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 13: The Great Steppes

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Press on "To get us all mining the same vein," Borek begins, "with the Urmskaladrak destroyed, we've not only lost our best Engineer, we've lost most of our food storage capacity. We are left with only what the other steam-wagons have room for, which is about nine tons apiece. This equates to about two weeks of food at full rations." "We're three weeks out from the borders of Kislev," Snorri says, his voice distant. "If we turn back now and switch to half rations as we approach High Pass, we should remain battle-ready until we're out of the area where we're likely to encounter enemies." "This quest was perilous in the best of circumstances," Sir Joerg says. "Without food, it cannot continue." Sir Ruprecht reluctantly nods in agreement. "I may have a solution to that," you say, and all eyes turn to you. After properly washing the blood from your hands, you had spent some time considering the problem that the other Councillors are already wrestling with, and had come up with an elegant solution, and then had spent some time atop the Volans with a piece of measured string while trying to keep the words 'Mookery of Death' out of your head. "I have a spell at my disposal that will ensorcell the target into a sort of enchanted sleep. If we can acquire cows from the Kurgan, either by silver or steel, there's room on the top-deck of each of the steam-wagons for about sixty by my measure. They'd still require watering, but apart from that they'd be essentially cargo." There's a long silence as everyone considers those numbers. "These wouldn't be fat Averland steers," Sir Ruprecht says. "Call it two to a ton, and a quarter of that bone." "At least twenty tons of meat per steam-wagon," Borek says, a hint of hope re-entering his voice. "That triples our range. If we can get enough cows, that's more than enough to reach Karag Dum and for the journey back." "The other problem is the missing part of the road," Sir Ruprecht says. "The Engineers have been taking measurements, what did they determine?" You see heads turn towards the empty seat. "It's passable," Borek says in Gotrek's stead, "but barely. The remainder of the road seems stable, but there's stable and then there's a steam-wagon going over it stable. We'll take out the shotcannon and the more portable supplies and as much crew as we can - for such a short stretch we just need a stoker, a driver, and a pilot." "I can have Hubert standing by to grab the pilot if the road goes, but the other two will share the fate of their steam-wagon if anything goes wrong," you say. That's all you can contribute to this problem, unfortunately. You've been trying to figure out a way for the Rite of Way to help in this situation, but it was built with the explicit intention of the caster not having to manually control it, so you're stuck with how the spell's targeting mechanism was built - and it was not built to bridge ravines. Snorri exhales heavily. "We all knew that could be the price when we joined this Expedition. After already having saved one Dwarfhold, I'd be surprised if less than half of the Engineers stepped forward for the job." "How do the numbers change if we lose another steam-wagon? Or, Gods forbid, both?" Sir Joerg says. There's another moment as everyone wrestles with the numbers. Gotrek would have had a slate handy. "With four steam-wagons, five weeks," Borek says eventually. "With three, a little under four." Sir Joerg considers that. "That's still viable." "Then we continue on," Borek says firmly. --- With bated breath, three hundred sets of eyes watch as the freshly-unloaded Kriestov noses its way forward. With its engine struggling to get up to steam on an incline it was always going to be slow, but given the circumstance it seems like very understandable hesitance. The remaining portion of the road seems far too narrow for the steam-wagon to slip past and you find yourself holding your breath as it slowly noses its way forward... [Rolling...] ...and through, allowing you to finally exhale. But the wait for the Alexis to be unloaded and de-crewed allows tension to mount once more and you're just as nervous the second time... [Rolling...] ...though, thankfully, for nothing. With the remaining steam-wagons reunited, the Dwarves scramble to reload the cargo so that the Expedition can finally get moving again and start to make up for lost time. The impact of the Urmskaladrak could have rung the dinner bell for any Kurgans or Ogres or who knows what else might be in the area, and right now your best defence against them is to be elsewhere. --- Thankfully the final leg of the ascent is uneventful and you find yourself on the Great Steppes, the vast rolling landscape with the Winds blowing overhead and the constant feeling of being watched. Sir Joerg has reported that his scouts have spotted individual and small groups of horsemen, which so far have ended uneventfully with the horsemen falling back and the Knights letting them. It would be better for the Expedition if battle can be avoided, so it's better not to start any blood feuds if you can help it. Soon you'll reach the point where the Expedition will veer north off Skull Road and into Dolgan territory. With a trail of smoke pointing to your position at all times it's likely they'll find you before too long, and hopefully they'll be inclined to stick to their end of the deal. You weren't exactly forthright about the band you'd be arriving with, but if the Dwarves stay out of sight then a band of monster-riding warriors surrounding huge, strange metal behemoths doesn't exactly scream 'not Chaos', so your lies by omission have a decent chance of being swallowed whole. The landscape itself isn't too bad, and the dry landscape should hold up fairly well under the steam-wagons, or at least better than they would if it had rained recently. Still, any time spent casting Rite of Way would speed up the Expedition. You could also proactively make contact with the Dolgan instead of making them come to you, or take care of your side of the deal with the Ice Witches now if you think it would be better than doing so on the way home. And there's always value in checking in on others in the Expedition to keep tabs on their mental states. So much to do, so little time... The four with the most votes will be chosen. Spend time getting to know... [ ] Thane Borek Forkbeard [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Use Rite of Way for the worst patches of rough terrain [ ] Use Rite of Way for the moderately difficult ground [ ] Use Rite of Way nearly constantly - For these, vote cumulatively. For example, if you want to use two of Mathilde's four choices on it, vote for both the 'rough terrain' and 'moderately difficult ground' options. [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Dolgan - These are the Kurgans Mathilde met with earlier, who agreed to sell her cattle. [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Yusak - These are the Kurgan that live directly south of Karag Dum, who are said to have lost the favour of the Gods and may be seeking to move further south. [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Kul - These are the most infamous of Kurgan tribes, who gave rise to Asavar Kul. They are said to live to the west of Karag Dum. [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Iron Wolves [ ] Attempt to steal the Chaos artefact with Ljiljana - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Trying to scout ahead to Karag Dum is very strongly recommended against. Even Asarnil and Deathfang would not go that far into the Chaos Wastes without back-up. - For the Rite of Way vote, vote cumulatively. For example, if you want to use two of Mathilde's four choices on it, vote for both the 'rough terrain' and 'moderately difficult ground' options. - My compliments to a particularly creative thread contributor who hit upon the Mockery of Death solution, without which this would have been a very different update. - I am declaring a moratorium on all ideas and discussion about how to get the steam-wagons past the narrow part of the ascent until it's time to embark on the journey home once more.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 14: Karag Dum

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Use Rite of Way for the worst patches of rough terrain [*] Attempt to make contact with the Dolgan [*] Use Rite of Way for the moderately difficult ground [*] Attempt to make contact with the Yusak With the Expedition leaving the road and veering into the seemingly-endless steppes of the Kurgan, you've decided your best contribution to this Expedition would be to use Rite of Way to ease the journey over any difficult terrain, and to make contact with the Kurgan tribes whose territory lies in your path. Hopefully your established deal with the Dolgan will lay the foundation for a peaceful passage through their lands, and hopefully the fact that the Yusak have fallen from the favour of the Chaos Gods will mean they won't be looking for new enemies. Hopefully. As the steam-wagons turn off the road and onto the soil you take up position at the prow of the Alriksson alongside Borek, whose eyes rarely leave the northern horizon. You can feel the steam-wagon slow as the great wheels bite into the turf, but the great engine below grows louder and the many wheels keep turning, biting a deep furrow and leaving a trail of upturned black soil in its wake. Behind you the Magnus does the same, driving slightly to one side to avoid sinking deeper into the trails left by the Alriksson. If the great columns of smoke weren't enough, ten parallel black lines in the landscape will make it trivial for anyone with eyes to follow your trail, but then again stealth was never the plan. Speed and intimidation are how you hope to avoid conflict. With the Expedition still making relatively decent forward progress you refrain from assisting with Rite of Way as the engineers make their assessments, monitoring engine and axle stress, measuring speed with a modified chip log, and conversations being shouted back and forth or had by writing down messages, attaching them to a crossbow bolt, and then firing them at targets attached to the fore and aft of each steam-wagon's funnels. Only once so far had such a message missed the target, and Snorri has said that the bolt will remain embedded in the funnel until the Ranger responsible can knock it off with another. When a consensus is finally reached, the results are sent to Borek, who glances down at them and grunts. "No worse than expected," he says to you. "Barring any dramatic changes in the landscape, we should arrive slightly ahead of schedule." "Well, let's see if we can improve that," you say cheerily. "Might want to take a few steps back." [Rite of Way: Learning, 87+28-10(Winds overhead)+15(Windsage)=120.] You reach your hand upwards and with force of will you snag one of the overhead streams of Ulgu, causing it to break free of the overhead tapestry to swirl downwards towards the Alriksson and spiral around you. You feel giddy as you feel it engulf you, the thrumming energies throbbing in time with your heartbeat and flitting hither and thon in response to your slightest whim. With an effort of will you remind yourself of your purpose and channel the Wind through you and into your Staff, the altered dragonbone almost as permeable to Ulgu as your soul. Fog billows out from your staff and hands and mouth and eyes, pouring forward to embrace the terrain ahead. The first steam-wagon seem to surge as it hits the grey road you've made, and at the same time there's a yank on your soul as the spell demands much more energy to sustain its effects, so much more than they required on the Skull Road. But now more than ever before there is energy aplenty, fresh from the Aethyr and ready to shape the malleable world to your will, and you meet the demands with only a slight effort. Then a second yank as the Magnus reaches the road, then a third and a fourth and a fifth, and now the entire stream flows straight through you and out onto the turf below. If you attempted to hold this much energy it would tear you asunder in seconds, but you simply let it flow through you. The lever moves the world, but the fulcrum remains steady. This is what it is to be a Wizard. The robes, the rituals, the titles, the books, they were just decoration. To be a Wizard is to face the tide of power that would kill the world, and to bend that power to its defence. "Maybe more than slightly," you hear Borek mutter to himself behind you, and your smile widens. --- By the end of the first day the Expedition has grown familiar with the terrain and now knows how steep a hill can be and still be surmountable unassisted, and by dawn tomorrow the Knights will have a map ready for the day's travel that will give a route around the hills and bogs that dot the terrain. After most of a day immersed in Ulgu your thoughts flit about unfamiliarly, but a night's sleep surrounded by steel serves to ground you and you rise ready to face whatever the day will bring. The Knights have also reported regular contact with small groups of Kurgan, but so far both groups seem content with keeping a cautious distance. You hope to hammer that ad hoc ceasefire into a more solid agreement, and get confirmation that the Dolgan will cleave to their side of the deal. As the steam-wagons set off, you ride out with the Knights for a spell and then split off from them to try to encounter some of the locals alone. It doesn't take you long to spot a promising sign - a thin wisp of smoke rising from over the horizon, much smaller than the column at your back. You ride towards it, slowing as you do so; by the time you can see the flicker of light you're only at a trot, and when you can make out the figures around it you slow even further. You want there to be no possibility of mistaking your approach for a charge. By the time you reach them, they've long since spotted you, doused their fire, and mounted up, ready to fight or flee if necessary. Three of them look no different than any number of Gospodarin or Ungol horsemen you saw in Kislev, but the fourth has a strangely elongated head and a silver ring around his neck marking him as the leader. According to the books you've read both are signs of status; the children of prestigious Kurgan have their heads bound as infants to change their shape with the intention that an artificial mutation will attract truer ones from the Gods, and the torc is a display of martial confidence and an open challenge to all, saying that the silver belongs to anyone that can remove his head. "Blood or tea?" you say in Khazalid, an echo of what the Shaman you met first said to you, and the leader eyes you thoughtfully for a moment, his eyes flicking downwards to your Shadowsteed and then over to the column of smoke that marks the Expedition. Then he nods and points upward, to a point higher in the sky than the sun currently is, and you nod and point downwards. There's another exchange of nods, then the leader exchanges a few words with the others and they gallop off. You note the direction. You're sure they'd change direction when out of sight so they didn't point you directly at the nearest encampment, but it does indicate a direction where the encampment isn't. [Rolling...] As the sun nears the indicated point in the sky, you see your response approaching, and one much larger than the previous. You count fifty horsemen, and from their auras can spot three Shamans, one the Ghur Shaman you spoke to previously, the other two aligned to Aqshy and Shyish. The leader of the group is easy to pick out, as he wears metal pauldrons and both arms are ringed with an eclectic collection of silver and gold bands. But most obviously of all the only feature on his face is his mouth, the rest of it smooth, flat skin where eyes and a nose should be. Despite this apparent handicap his face is pointed straight at you as the band approaches, and your hands itch for Branulhune. They stop several meters from you, and the mouth of the leader issues a sibilant order, and the Ghur Shaman approaches, the two of you dismounting to close the final few meters. "Blood or tea, Shadowed Shaman of the Mountain Ring Clans?" he asks in guttural Khazalid. "Today, tea, Untamed Shaman of the Dolgan Tribes," you reply, and as last time he approaches to offer you a flask, and again you flick some north before forcing down the fermented horse milk. "This is Irnik, Slaaksho of the Four, who rules these lands," he says, gesturing behind him at the faceless chieftain. "I shall speak for him, for his tongue only speaks the Blessed Language. I had suspected that the metal longboats that sailed upon a sea of fog was your pilgrimage." You nod. "We have travelled far, and we have further yet to go. Our beasts are always hungry, and our blood is destined to stain other lands." You produce an ingot of unmarked silver from your robes and hand it over to the Shaman, who turns and throws it to the chieftain, who snatches it out of the air and considers it closely. A long, bright pink tongue emerges from the being's mouth, its unnatural length caressing the metal carefully before retracting with an audible snap. It nods. "It is agreed," the Shaman says. "How many beasts do you require?" "We shall buy up to sixty adult cattle now, and up to three hundred on our return journey, or the equivalent weight in other beasts." This, you had decided with the rest of the Council, was the best way forward. It left you with a thin margin of food at Karag Dum, but that was preferable to having exposed cattle atop the steam-wagons when you enter the Chaos Wastes proper. The Shaman nods, and turns and has a prolonged exchange with one of the non-Shaman Kurgan in the crowd. "We can fulfil this," he says when he turns back. "We shall meet you at the Yusak border with the first of the beasts." "We shall be seeking to return through these lands within the next two white-moon-cycles, when we will purchase the remainder." "Very well. We shall bring some of our herds to this area, and watch the border with the Yusak for your return. Your silver is pleasing to Slaaksho Irnik. May we both grow stronger to bring glory to our peoples and enjoyment to our Gods." --- Though the Knights and Winter Wolves remain watchful for any sign of treachery, the Dolgan prove as good as their word and you spend a few hours wielding magic to render lively, nervous cattle into still-breathing cargo, at which point the beasts are hoisted upwards to be tied down on the upper deck. It gives the other Wizards a chance to get used to casting in these conditions as they cast Sleep on the beasts to render them more vulnerable to Mockery of Death. By the time you reach the edge of Dolgan land the beasts have eaten their fill and then some, and at your current pace you'll reach Karag Dum with several days remaining before their return journey - more than enough for the return journey to relatively uncorrupted lands. Now you have only one penultimate unknown: the Yusak. All you know of them is that they, in the words of the Ghur Shaman, 'lost favour with the Four and seek lands further from them'. Perhaps this means they will be weakened and unwilling to seek conflict, perhaps this means they will be all too willing to in an attempt to regain their lost favour. So on the final day through Dolgan lands, the Expedition charts a particularly conservative path as you head north at full gallop. In the Empire, most borders are invisible, ephemeral things, marked on unreliable maps and argued about almost constantly. This border, at least, is quite different. Further north the eight-coloured stream of energies is joined by a ninth, uglier, heavier shade, as Dhar emerges from wherever it is Winds come from and sinks to the ground much sooner than the others, hanging in the air and seeping into the soil. The line where the unnatural arc of dark magic reaches the ground is as visible to mundane senses as it is to Magesight, as the vegetation changes abruptly from near-uniformity to a chaotic patchwork. In some places the vegetation is dying off, poisoned by the unnatural energies, and in others the grasses draw vigour from the Dhar, growing tall and stained with sickly colours. The landscape varies even further as you push deeper, and at points the land is scarred with roads appearing from nowhere and going nowhere. You spend some time considering a stone ziggurat worn almost into a pyramid by the passage of time or some other process, and you spend as little time as possible considering the distant flocks of figures too large to be birds that drift lazily through the sky. Eventually the grasses die out entirely, leaving the lands alternating between dry, dusty soil, unpleasantly sticky mud, and bare stone. Here and there mushrooms as tall as trees grow in clumps, dripping with mucus and emitting an unignorable stench like overripe fruit. It's around one of them that you find the first signs of the Yusak - a band of sheep crowding around the stalk of a mushroom that looked sicklier than the others, those closest to it taking bites out of its stalk. At regular intervals the ones eating stagger off to collapse to the ground, either sickened or intoxicated, and more press forward until finally it gives way. The sheep scatter out of the great falling weight, but as soon as it lands they turn and charge towards the swollen cap, butting and bleating at each as they each try to be first to the fruit of their labours. With sickened curiosity you watch as they gorge themselves on the soft flesh. You'd wondered how anything could live in the Chaos Wastes, and it seems you have part of your answer. Just as with the Dolgan, a stranger atop a magic horse watching but not attempting to steal the livestock is the sort of conundrum that would send a worried and confused Yusak herdsman to seek answers from the Tribe's authorities. Just as with the Dolgan, the troupe that eventually arrives to investigate you is led by someone dressed in the panoply of a Shaman. But this time, you can see no Winds surrounding him, and that doesn't leave a lot of options for what he could be a Shaman of. But you remind yourself that Branulhune is only a thought away and let him approach, and to your surprise he offers you blood or tea in guttural Khazalid first. "Today, tea," you respond, and you go through the usual ritual of dismounting and drinking with him. "I am a Shaman of the Yusak Tribes. I serve the White of the Two." You try not to show any indication of relief that he's a Shaman of Mannsleib. "I am a Shaman of the Mountain Ring Clans. I serve the Shadowed of the Eight. My Clan is travelling north on pilgrimage." "Ah. You seek to test yourself against the Dum?" he asks. You consider your response for a moment. "Yes," you reply, which is true, to a certain extent. [Rolling...] "All are welcome against the Dum," he says. "The Kul and the Kvellige are there now, but the southern front is available to you." "What state is Dum in?" you ask. He gives you an odd look. "Dum is as it has always been." "Ah." You decide against angling for further information. Something about your question seems to have been wrong. "We shall arrive within the quarter-cycle, with beast-mounts and metal ships. We do not seek quarrel with the Yusak." "Then pass, and feast upon the bounty of the land freely." You watch thoughtfully as he remounts and departs. He had something of a listless, distracted air to him, which could be indicative of hard times for the Yusak, but you don't know nearly enough about Kurgan moon-worship to say if that's out of character for a Shaman devoted to Mannsleib. In any case, you've got as close as you're likely to get to a non-aggression pact with the Yusak, so you consider the job done. --- Forewarned by you of the terrain ahead, by the time the Expedition reaches what you're considering to be the border of the Chaos Wastes proper everyone is braced for what they encounter, and though there's a ripple of shock through everyone present as they set eyes on it for themselves, nobody is entirely taken aback by it. Now more than ever the Rite of Way proves itself as it gets the Expedition through the rapidly-changing terrain at a fast pace and without setbacks, circling around strange ruins and mushroom copses as it pushes relentlessly north. Each day leaves you mentally drained by the effort of keeping the flow of Ulgu as free as you can of the Dhar that's all too eager to cling to and corrupt any other Wind it touches. Several times you have to put out spot fires on your robes as the Runes on your Belt purge errant Dhar, and you're starting to worry what it would mean for anyone else to wield magic here. The mostly flat landscape starts to grow rugged as you approach the foothills of Karag Dum, and nervousness gives way to anticipation in the atmosphere of the steam-wagons. You stay quiet, occupied with the dark mutterings you heard from numerous sources about what fates might have befallen Karag Dum, and what lengths they might have gone to to avoid them. The temperature has been steadily falling as you ventured further north, but here it grows hotter and drier as the ascent continues. You pass tattered banners hammered into the bare stone of more varieties than you can identify, most seemingly Kurgan, some completely unfamiliar to you, and others completely wiped clean by the hot, gritty wind that seems to be blowing directly into your face. And then the Alriksson crests a final rise and the landscape opens up before you, and you barely manage to release the Rite before shock tears it from your grasp. You'd seen pictures of Karag Dum, the tallest of a small cluster of mountains approached through an exposed vale. But now it stands alone, jutting out from a great crater that you find yourself on the lip of. Directly below you is bone-white sand, interrupted regularly by actual bones that grow thicker on the ground the closer it is to Karag Dum. And with shocking abruptness the desert gives way to disturbingly familiar forest that now rings the base of Karag Dum, burying the bottom third of it in apparently primeval forest that by all accounts was not there a mere two centuries ago. And as you stare and as the Alriksson continues trundling forward, you see a figure at the edge of the forest, standing taller than a man and taller still when you consider the skull-adorned frill that juts from its skull. In a flash of realization, you know why your question had confused the Yusak Shaman. When he spoke of Dum, he did not mean the Dwarfhold of Karag Dum. He meant Cor-Dum. As you watch reality flinch away from him, Morghur the Shadowgave, immortal demigod of the Beastmen, bellows a warbling prayer to the mountain that has become his Herdstone, and from the trees countless more voices join him. To be continued.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 15

Wheels sink into sand as the Alriksson slows and then stops, your eyes locked on the figure as it tosses its head to and fro, sending energies arcing through the air with every motion. Most of what little you know of Beastmen comes from your former Master's stories, and what little he knew of Morghur was second-hand. He's supposedly been locked in an eternal war with Athel Loren that occassionally spills out to devastate some other part of the Old World. The only time you've really heard about him outside of those stories is in relation to the High Elves pursuing him through Bretonnia some centuries ago, which is part of why Karag Dum's warnings in the lead-up to the Great War Against Chaos were ignored. As the demigod bellows once more but shows no sign of approaching, you risk a glance sideways at Borek, who'd become more and more glued to the prow as you grew nearer to his home. You're not sure what you expect - shock? disbelief? despair? But you definitely weren't expecting resignation. "Borek-" "We did the best we could," he says. "When it comes time to tell the rest of the Karaz Ankor what has become of us, please tell them that as well. May the Ancestors forgive us." With that, he pulls loose a knot that causes a rope ladder to unfurl and clambers over the guardrail. "Borek?" you ask, trying to process this as the first of the other Dwarves start to spill out of the lower levels, seeking a better view than they could get from what would have to be very crowded gun-ports. "What in Grimnir's name is that?" says the first Ranger to reach your side. "Cor-Dum," you answer simply. There's silence for a moment. "Ah," he says. Then he looks down. "What's Borek doing?" "If that's Cor-Dum, that's it for Karag Dum," says another. "He'd be joining his kin." "Maybe," you say, watching him. Something about this isn't adding up. Though Borek's pace is steady, his process across the sand is anything but, as the heat-shimmer embraces him and sends mirages of his image shimmering to and fro. Morghur simply watches, and you can begin to make out parts of the forest's edge that are the silhouettes of other Beastmen, rather than trees. You ignore the steady thock of crossbow-fired messages from behind, then hear an out-of-breath Snorri swearing as he barges through the crowd behind you. "Why have we-" he stops himself as he looks out into the crater. "Where'd the other mountains go?" "Don't know," you answer. "Why is there a forest? And a desert?" "Don't know," you say again. "Why's Borek out there? Wait, who's that?" "I think it's more of a 'what' than a 'who'," you say. "Cor-Dum," one of the Rangers says. There's a moment as Snorri processes that. "Alright, job done, Borek's back home, time we accomplished the same for ourselves," he says briskly. "If this thing's stuck, leave it here." "Just a moment," you say. "Things aren't adding up." Across the sands, the two figures meet, and the Shadowgave bends down to consider the Dwarf before him. Then he reaches out a twisted claw and runs it over Borek's hair in what seems to be an affectionate gesture. He stands aside and Borek continues his march, disappearing into the trees. Deafening silence embraces the crowd of onlookers, broken only by the wind whistling past you. "Karag fucking Dum," one of the Engineers finally says. "I never listened to all the mutterings," Snorri says. "More fool I." Morghur gives one final bellow before disappearing back into the forest, and you exhale. Some time very soon, an even further reduced Council is going to meet, and all eyes are going to be on you to make sense of all this and suggest a course of action. You sigh and mentally begin to sort through the pieces of the puzzle before you. Morghur: - Morghur is said to have been 'born' three hundred years ago, but there's stories of beings identical to him stretching back throughout recorded history. - From your very limited knowledge, Morghur was last seen being pursued by High Elves in Bretonnia shortly before the Great War Against Chaos. - From what the Yusak said, and what the banners you passed seem to attest, Kurgan tribes have been fighting or 'testing themselves against' Morghur for some time. - Morghur did not attack Borek, instead greeting him with what to Dwarves is a very intimate gesture. - Borek's reaction to Morghur did not seem surprised. Karag Dum: - The magic flowing to Karak Vlag was uncorrupted, which you're fairly sure would not have been the case if the Hold had been conquered by Beastmen. - The landscape around Karag Dum has changed, including the disappearance of the smaller mountains around it, the growth of a forest around its base, and the appearance of a desert around the forest. It is also hotter here than anywhere else in the Steppes. Apart from the forests covering the lower parts of it, the exterior of Karag Dum appears unchanged. - The forest is inhabited by Beastmen, who seem to be obeying Morghur. - As far as Mathilde can tell, none of this is an illusion. - There is less ambient Dhar here than other parts of the Chaos Wastes Mathilde has seen, though still more than outside of it. Mathilde will present the leading theories and courses of action as possibilities to the rest of the Council. You may vote for multiples of each if you wish. Please use this format to vote for them: [ ] THEORY: [ ] ACTION: - There will be a three hour moratorium for the above to be digested and discussed. - If anyone has data points that Mathilde would have access to that they think should be added to the above, please suggest them. - If there's anything about this that's unclear but would be clear to Mathilde, please point out what.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 16

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] THEORY: The specifics are hazy, but this is a known contingency plan that Borek is entirely aware of, but hoped hadn't been enacted. The result breaks all Dawi notions of acceptability, but Karak Dum survives in some capacity and continues to inflict attrition on every local and visiting Chaos force that want to take a swing at them, so it is considered a lesser evil by the pragmatic Karak Dum. [*] THEORY: The Dwarves of Karag Dum did something to burn away the taint of Chaos, much as your Belt of the Unshackled Mountain does, but on a far grander scale. Perhaps it had an effect on the Beastmen here, Cor-Dum included. [*] THEORY: Karag Dum is using a fake Morghur to make the real beastmen fight for them. [*] THEORY: Karag Dum has somehow tricked or compelled Morghur to fight the Kurgan tribes. [*] THEORY: Omegahugger [*] ACTION: Gain more information. [*] ACTION: Turn back [*] ACTION: Politely ask Morghur to be granted entrance into Karak Dum. With the five steam-wagons lined up on the lip of the crater with broadsides pointed towards the mountain, the Council meets atop the Alriksson to discuss what to make of all of this. Unsurprisingly, all eyes are on you. You're the Wizard, but even more relevantly you're the Loremaster. Making strange and unpredictable circumstances make sense to the Dwarven mind is your job. And you've spent the time since Borek departed compiling theories and possible courses of action, with quite a lot of overlap, frustrations, and desires to yell at Borek finding their way into the list. "'We did the best we could,' he said," you repeat to the severely diminished council. "'When it comes time to tell the rest of the Karaz Ankor what has become of us, please tell them that as well. May the Ancestors forgive us.' I have about a hundred different theories, but to me, that would seem to imply that whatever we're looking at is a known contingency plan that Borek was aware of, but hoped that the besiegement of Karag Dum would never become desperate enough for it to be enacted. So I think that it's likely that Karag Dum is still intact and functioning in some capacity, and whatever they're doing is inflicting constant attrition on the forces of Chaos." "What have they done, exactly?" Sir Ruprecht asks. "I'm not an expert on Runes or Beastmen, but it seems clear they've used some sort of Runecraft to bind Morghur to their service. Perhaps some sort of illusion or ensorcellation, perhaps something to burn the Chaos taint off of him to free him from the orders of the Chaos Gods. Perhaps his latest incarnation was born to Dwarves, and they managed to either bind him or protect him or raise him so that he's more loyal to them than to Chaos. I don't know if Morghur's been sighted in the Old World since the Great War Against Chaos-" "Not since the Battle of Arden in 2244," Sir Joerg says. "Well, there you have it. Though it might just be a coincidence and all this is an illusion, one good enough to fool Beastmen into thinking that it's their demigod so they protect the Hold." "None of those possibilities are the sort of thing that covers Karag Dum with glory," Snorri says darkly. "Hence Borek's resignation. He assumed that once we clapped eyes on Beastmen defending Karag Dum, that would be the end of the Expedition." "Whatever the case may be, they don't seem to need rescuing," Sir Ruprecht says, running his eyes over the bone-strewn desert. "And as far as I'm concerned, if the forces of Chaos are killing themselves off here even faster than usual for their kind, that's to the good." "If our descendants are going to be faced with another variety of Chaos Dwarf, any information we can give them would be of benefit," Sir Joerg says. You nod. "This might be the last chance the Empire and the Karaz Ankor get to study whatever has happened here. The practical thing might be to depart at all speed, but I do want at least some answers to bring back." "I want to know what Gotrek died for," Snorri says. "If whatever's in there isn't boiling out of it to take a swing at us..." All eyes turn to Sir Ruprecht, who stares at the forest. "We won't be in much more danger for staying here a little longer," he concedes. "How long do you need to gather your answers?" Sir Joerg asks. "There's a few things I can do safely and quickly," you say. "Perhaps a couple of hours will shed enough light to know if there are more answers to be safely plucked." "We can reassess then," Sir Joerg says, and Sir Ruprecht nods. Snorri just stares at the forest that Morghur disappeared into pensively. --- "They're definitely Old World species," Journeyman Cyrston says, peering through a telescope. "I'd need to get up close and collect seeds and samples and bring my own Magesight to bear to say with any certainty, but if I had to guess, I'd say northern. Drakwald, Laurelorn, or Forest of Shadows." "Any idea how it would have got here?" "Apart from just labelling it Chaos Waste weirdness? None whatsoever. Until I clapped eyes on these I'd have bet good money you wouldn't see any of these species further north than the Western Oblast." "And their age?" "Under normal circumstances, which," he gestures vaguely at the Chaos Wastes behind you, "I'd say it would take centuries undisturbed, perhaps longer. These are old forests. The type you don't go into lightly, because if there's not something terrible already living there, it's because the trees are the something terrible." "Any sign of mutation?" "Nothing major. Though I can't rule out minor mutations at this distance." --- "This one's definitely Beastman," Esbern says, running his fingers over the curved horns attached to misshapen skull. "Look at the growth rings. This wasn't a sudden mutation, this was something they were born with that grew over decades." "Teethmarks," says Seija from the one she was inspecting. "But not as many as usual for a Beastman feast. They filled their stomach and left the rest where it stood. That's how they act on a raid when they're wary of counterattack." --- "I wasn't a part of that jaunt, but three of my cousins were," Asarnil says. "Finubar's attempt at building bridges. The Forest of Arden had been corrupted by Morghur and Beastmen flocked to it from across the Old World. L'Anguille called for aid against a foe they could not understand, the Everqueen pushed for its restoration, and the so-called 'Glade Lord' Araloth that was preparing a great hunt for the beast had a lineage greater than that of some Princes. Finubar the Haggler saw a chance to earn credit with three polities at once, and was all too eager to spill Elven blood for it, so Prince Eldyr of Taranoc and Handmaiden Ystranna raised a mighty host. Many of them never returned." Asarnil chuckles darkly. "Bitterness over that poisoned any hope of improved relations between Ulthuan and its abandoned colony, the Bretonnians gave all credit to their Lady, and as for the Everqueen, it wasn't long after that she found she much preferred the brother of your Teclis than the company of the Phoenix King. Finubar has a gift for snatching defeat from the jaws of victory." --- "This is how they act if they're near something they consider sacred and feel threatened," Sir Joerg says with a nod. "If they can, flank and kill. If they can't, stay out of sight and wait for an opportunity to flank and kill. If pressed, kill or die for the sacred whatever." --- "No doubt in my mind, definitely less ambient Dhar around than in the Chaos Wastes," Egrimm says. "Hard to tell much more than that with this much turbulence, though. Timpania has a headache and Barbitus can't stand up without staggering like a drunken sailor. The overall trend is it definitely being drawn towards the mountain, though." "That was my impression too," you say, nodding. "Can you pick up any more than that?" Egrimm looks to Citharus, who is frowning, his eyes closed as he concentrates. "It's like the busiest, noisiest shepherd's tone I've ever heard," he says eventually. "Always falling, but never getting any lower. Or at least not fast enough to be detectable to me." You consider that. "That could be hopeful or very grim. Any idea which?" He shrugs. "Very well. Thank you both for your insight." --- "The item we have to retrieve, is it in the Karak?" you ask Ljiljana. She concentrates. "No." You exhale. "Good." "Yes." "Do you know anything about Beastmen?" She sniffs. "No. Hag Witch business." --- Max reels in the long length of rope, his eyes on the half-apple attached to the end of it. "This has to be the least precise experiment I've ever done." "We don't need to know a ratio, we're just testing for temporal abnormalities," you reassure him. "I'm mostly sure it was just heat haze, but mostly sure is a good way to get killed." Max finishes the reeling, and compares the two halves. One's clearly more shrivelled than the other, but no more browned. "Well, it's definitely hotter in there," he says, "but there doesn't appear to be any time difference." --- "Smoke from fires from what looks like moderate-sized settlements or encampments," Snorri says to you after hearing from the Rangers who were straining their eyes to try to make out details through their own telescopes. "One northwest, the other northeast, I'd say about an hour's walk or a much shorter ride from the lip of the crater." You nod. "Any reaction from the semaphore?" "Nothing." "Thought not, but it was worth a try. What was the other matter you wanted to discuss?" "Look," he says, pointing at some sort of metal pole driven into the lip of the crater. "Eleven and three quarter inches between it and the sands." You consider that thoughtfully. "And what does that signify?" "An hour ago, it was exactly twelve. I'd stake my beard on it. Measured it three times, and two other seasoned Rangers measured it twice apiece. You don't put a theodolite stand in about the right place, you put it exactly where you wrote down you put it." You frown, and kneel down to consider the edge of the crater. To your eye, it's solid stone. You dig into the sand next to it, and find that there's no fresh crumbling underneath, just smooth stone. "It hasn't crumbled," you say. "The desert is expanding." "That's what I got from it," Snorri says with a nod. "A quarter inch per hour, times two hundred years," you say, looking at the forest in the distance. "Does that add up?" "We can't get an accurate measurement from here - we know the exact height of Karag Dum, but we can't see the base. So we're going off of eyeballing here. But... yes. Two hundred years at six inches a day, that's about the distance you get." You frown, then drop onto your stomach to examine the edge of the crater from an inch away, to see if you can witness individual grains of the stone crumbling into sand. "Find me whoever knows the most about stone in this Expedition," you say. --- "Dormant stratovolcano," says the Dwarf that Snorri fetched for you as soon as you ask about Karag Dum. "And the stone of the landscape around it?" you ask, still staring at the edge. "Don't answer from memory, look at it and tell me what it is as if you'd never heard of this place before." He obeys, producing a pickaxe from his belt to chip off a piece to examine, and then carefully chew. "Scoria," he says with confidence. "Is that what should be here?" "Aye. More mafic than I'd have expected, but then again, we are far from the mountains I know." "And the sand? Is it fragmented scoria?" "No," he says instantly. "Wrong colour completely." He bends down and picks some up, letting it run through his fingers before putting a pinch in his mouth. "Sedimentary silicate, not igneous. Nearest place you'd find this is the southern Dark Lands." You remember what Cyrston said. "Anywhere in the northern Empire with that sort of sand?" "Nowhere near. All I know of that would is the southern Dark Lands, Araby, and Nehekhara." With a tiny fizzle of Divine energy, a tiny piece of rock disappears from the lip of the crater, replaced by a few grains of sand that tumble down to join the rest of the desert. "Thank you for your insight," you distractedly tell the Dwarf as you stare. --- After running through all the safe experiments you could think of, you're much richer in questions but not exactly overburdened with answers. From here, the avenues for answers get significantly riskier, and often significantly more dubious. You also won't have long before the others begin to start pushing for the Expedition to leave, and not without reason - though nothing is currently attacking you, this is the Chaos Wastes, and enemies and corruption are never far away. [ ] Approach the Kul camp peacefully and attempt to discuss the Karak with them [ ] Approach the Kvellige camp peacefully and attempt to discuss the Karak with them [ ] Fortify here and see if anything interesting happens over the next day [ ] Attempt to approach Morghur to see if he can be communicated with [ ] Attempt to scout the forest at the base of the Karak [ ] Attempt to infiltrate the Karak with magic [ ] Attempt to infiltrate the Karak without magic [ ] Attempt to intercept a Kurgan war-party en route to attack the Karag and the Beastmen - Hopefully, this will trigger the Protector and implant the knowledge that you protected them in both the Beastmen and any remaining inhabitants of the Karak. [ ] Ask for a volunteer to approach Morghur to see if he can be communicated with [ ] Ask for a volunteer to test Morghur's reputed ability to turn anyone using magic nearby into Chaos Spawns [ ] Leave - There will be a two hour moratorium. - If you have an idea for some other approach, let me know. - If anyone isn't shown as being explicitly asked, assume that Mathilde asked them off-screen and they didn't have anything more to contribute. - If you have an idea for experiments that don't take long that involve no spellcasting, not leaving the fortified position, and not potentially starting a fight with the Beastmen, suggest them and I might edit in the results of Mathilde doing them. - Experimenting with the rock-to-sand effect will be set up before Mathilde does whatever is voted for, unless 'leave' wins. - Among Morghur's reputed abilities is that anyone casting spells near him as a change of turning into a Chaos Spawn. Just something to keep in mind.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 17

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Fortify here and see if anything interesting happens over the next day With it being past noon, you're able to convince the others that it makes more sense to fortify here than to set off and have to fortify in a few short hours somewhere less defensible and thicker in Dhar. You're hoping that something you witness or discover over that time will shed light on what's happening here, or at the very least give you something to argue for more time with. With the help of your motley group of Wizards, you set up an array of experiments at the lip of the crater to test the slowly expanding radius of sand and start scouring the edge of it for more skeletons that can be retrieved for examination without venturing too far into the sands. It's still far from being a census, but you manage to examine enough that the relative normality begins to stand out. Sure, there are Beastmen in their many forms, and you do find a few of what you assume to have been Kurgan with what would have been functional mutations, but there's no fatally chaotic alterations, nor anything resembling the skeleton of a Chaos Spawn. Perhaps the bodies would be different closer to the forest that Morghur seems to be protecting, or perhaps not. As dusk approaches, a clamour of horns and drums in the distance has everyone scrambling for defensive positions, and from your position atop the Alriksson you peer through a telescope as to the northeast, what you presume to be a Kvellige warband lines up along the lip of the crater, shouting war-cries. An answering clamour rises from the forest, and it doesn't take long for Morghur to emerge facing them, shouting his own warbling accompaniment. As soon as he appears, a dozen or so of the warband charge forward, the hooves of their horses churning up the sand as they make their way towards the Shadowgave. The first Kurgan to reach Morghur is swept off his horse by Morghur's staff, landing heavily on the sand and being pinned to it by Morghur's claw a moment later. The Beastman's cry of triumph becomes one of anger and frustration as arrows and javelins from the other Kurgan meet their mark in his sides and back, and at the cry from their demigod the Beastmen begin to boil out of the forest, charging at the interlopers with inhuman roars. This seems to spur the Kurgan to even greater lengths as two more close in on him, one managing to parry a swing from Morghur while the other leaps upon his back, clinging on to the spikes erupting from his back and sinking a dagger into his flesh over and over. Another cry of anger comes from Morghur, but this one is interwoven with something different, and to your Magesight Morghur begins to glow with malign energy that's as visible in the ambient Dhar as the sun amongst stars. As the energy sinks into him the Kurgan on Morghur's back throws himself free, limping towards his horse with some difficulty as both the Beastmen and the other Kurgan close in on him, and at this distance you can't really make out much of the chaotic melee that ensues except that the Kurgan that had been on Morghur's back reaches his horse and begins to gallop to the edge of the crater, followed before long by most of the other Kurgan. Morghur roars again as the energy flowing off him throbs, and he bends down to begin to feast on the Kurgan he struck down as the Beastmen do the same to those that did not survive the melee. At the edge of the crater, the limping Kurgan appears to be excitedly displaying his leg to the others, who crowd around until he's blocked from your view. Not long later the warband departs, horns blowing in triumph as they leave the bloodstained sands behind them. The Beastmen gather up bows and blades from the fallen and they too depart, melting back into the forest and leaving the partially-eaten bodies where they fell. Soon only Morghur remains as he goes from body to body, the snarl of Dhar in him dimming as he does so, and by the time he returns to the forest he's no longer distinct against the background energies of this place. --- Bright and early the next morning, you and your Wizards collect data from the various objects that had been scattered about the edge of the crater. The growth of the crater supports the rough six inches per day estimate that Snorri had suggested, and apart from the skeletons that had been returned to the sand after examination, all the objects that had been placed atop the sand are now gone. But one of Johann's contributions had been a series of objects anchored to solid ground with string, and most of them - a knife, a shard of metal, an apple, and a torn tunic - are able to be retrieved from the now-taut strings from deep below the sands. Only the string that was tied to a rock from outside the crater comes up with an empty knot. The conclusion: only stone is transmuted, everything else sinks below the sands - except skeletons, that for some reason remain buoyed above the surface. From a considerable distance back from the crater you summon your Shadowsteed and with a heavy escort of Knights you circle the crater until you're close enough to the site of yesterday's battle to examine the bodies through a telescope. You're quite sure that the hurried feasting from yesterday was nowhere near enough to skeletonize the fallen, but despite that you're completely unable to identify the bodies from yesterday from the myriad other skeletons dotting the sands. You swallow your frustration and return to the Expedition - no need to risk the Kvellige thinking you're trespassing on their side of the crater. "The Kurgan made a clamour until Morghur appeared, then went straight for him," you begin as you address the remainders of the Council. "And they defended and escorted the only one of their number that actually touched Morghur. Either they venerate those that draw blood against the beast, or they're seeking out his mutative aura." "Which is somehow muted until combat provokes it out of him," Sir Joerg concludes. "When all records and legends we can recall of him say that it is constant. So it would seem that it is the genuine Shadowgave, but something has been done to alter him." "The desert is expanding by about six inches a day," you continue, "though we'd need longer-term observation to confirm whether that was constant or if it would slow as the circle grows bigger." "Two hundred feet a year," Sir Ruprecht says. "So, what, four miles a century?" "I'll make a note to warn Karak Vlag that a desert might knock on their door in the year thirty thousand," Snorri says wryly. "I take it that means we're done here?" Sir Ruprecht asks. "If that's definitely Morghur and those were definitely Beastmen, then that's all we need to know," Snorri says. "Karag Dum has fallen. Let the experts on Grudgelore argue over the exact degree." "Lady Magister?" Sir Joerg says cautiously. "I've worked with Esbern and Seija long enough to know that mysteries like this are as attractive to Wizards as a hot dinner and a warm bed in winter, but every moment spent here is less food, more danger, and more exposure to fell energies. The Expedition has reached Karag Dum and has enough information to reach a conclusion about their fate. Our responsibility now is to return with that information." You exhale. It seems you've run out of time. The rest of the Council are united in their desire to return to the Old World, and you don't have a strong argument against doing so to override them with. Just a long list of questions that you wish very much to answer. Course of Action - you should vote for at least one option under this category, unless you have no preference between them. [ ] Last minute You will remain here long enough for a last-ditch effort to snatch a few answers, then rejoin the convoy. [ ] Stay You will remain here until you find answers. [ ] Leave Details - you may vote for as many options as you prefer under this category, even if you did not vote for the associated course of action. [ ] LAST: Attempt to infiltrate Karag Dum [ ] LAST: Attempt to scout the forest at the base of the Karak [ ] LAST: Attempt to approach Morghur to see if he can be communicated with [ ] LAST: Approach the Kul camp peacefully and attempt to discuss the Karak with them [ ] LAST: Approach the Kvellige camp peacefully and attempt to discuss the Karak with them [ ] STAY: Attempt to join the Kvellige camp [ ] STAY: Attempt to join the Kul camp - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Staying alone is not really a viable option. This is the Chaos Wastes. Even Deathfang wouldn't come here solo, let alone set up camp here. - If you have another course of action to put under the Last or Stay category, suggest them. - Attempted infiltration will involve magic use, as without a fortified fall-back point the possibility of Morghur's antimagic field getting involved is still less dangerous than getting caught.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 18

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Leave You sigh. "The Expedition has fulfilled its mission," you concede. "It's time to return home." Some of the tension goes out of the room at your words. "I'm glad we're in accordance," Sir Joerg says. "Our attention must turn to our return trip, then." He unrolls a map and weighs down the corners with your steins. Spoiler: Map "Our path here worked, but we left a lot of trouble in our wake," Snorri says. "The Chaos Dwarves would have had time to collate reports about the steam-wagons and consider what it would take to set up an ambush, the Plotter-daemons are undoubtedly up to something, and the Iron Wolves would have had plenty of time to consider the wreckage we left behind and whether they consider themselves capable of taking us on, should we return. And not least of which..." He jabs a finger at the ascent between Zorn Uzkul and the Steppes. "Gotrek would have been able to give hard numbers, but my gut is telling me that we'll lose at least one steam-wagon to that corner." "And even if we don't, the Iron Wolves would have to be imbeciles not to realize how perfect an ambush position it would be," Sir Ruprecht says, "since we have to either disembark and unload and then reembark and reload each one, or risk the crew and contents of each. I'd pit us against any Kurgan impromptu ambush with confidence, but I don't want to know what they might have come up with, with near a month to plot and plan and prepare." "I was under the impression that the only other route was shelved for good reason," you say cautiously. "Damn good reason, and one we can largely work around now that we know the terrain," Snorri says. "We go south to Dolgan land, load ourselves down to the gunwales with cows, then skirt the edge of the Wastes until we reach the mountains. That way we minimize time spent in the Chaos Wastes and in Kul territory, which the original route didn't." "Okay, walk us through the entire route, then," you say. "These mountains," he says, pointing to the northernmost spur of the World's Edge Mountains, north of Uzkulak. "We know there's navigable passes through them, and navigable by the original plans of the Expedition, before we had the fogs to ease our passage. There's also beasts that lurk them, but as far as our scouting revealed, no worse so than around the ascent." "And the sea?" you prompt. "The Frozen Sea, as well-named as it could possibly be. Apart from the Icebreaker-led convoys to and from Uzkulak, all there is to encounter is seals and ice crabs." "It can hold our weight?" Sir Ruprecht asks dubiously. "The Chaos Dwarves need to use fire sorcery and leashed daemons to weaken the ice enough that their dreadnoughts can break through it. Our steam-wagons won't even make it creak." "Then through the Goromadny via Black Blood Pass, I take it?" Sir Joerg asks, and Snorri nods. "Controlled by the Baersonlings, but they are far from the worst of the Norscans. They send traders south as often as they do raiding parties. At the southern end of the pass is Fort Straghov, which tends to rise and fall with the seasons - it's a precarious position because it's only connected to Kislev proper by a chain of forts and Ungol villages, but it's also the first warning Kislev tends to get of invasion from the north, so they do their best to keep their grip on it. From there, Fort Kaminski and Fort Ostrosk along the Tobol, and overland via Iaryn and Dushyka to Praag." "It's a more direct route, but one that is largely without roads," Sir Ruprecht says. "Under normal circumstances, the route we took would likely still be faster. With the fog-path, though... Dame Weber, your thoughts?" You consider the map thoughtfully. It's the Rite of Way that could make the original route faster and possibly safer than the one the Expedition took here, and so your words here will probably tip the scales one way or the other. Known dangers versus a bevy of unknowns is an unenviable choice, but it's one that you're in a position to make. [ ] Road of Skulls Stick to the same route for the return trip that you took to get here. [ ] Frozen Sea Return via the route the Expedition was originally planning to take. [ ] Demur Avoid tipping the scales one way or the other, leaving the choice in the hands of Snorri, Joerg, and Ruprecht. - There will be a one hour moratorium. - The Road of Skulls route took four weeks. The Frozen Sea one seems like it would take two to three. - I won't be in the thread as frequently as usual over the next two or three weeks, so if you have a question, ask the rest of the thread first. A lot of things have already been answered and there's usually somebody who can dig it up.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 19: The Great Steppes

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] The Frozen Sea "I do not like the idea of trying to squeeze all five steam-wagons past that corner," you say, tapping the ascent on the map. "I think it would be best to take our chances with the original route." There's a series of nods in agreement to that, as you expected there would be. One known, implacable, and unavoidable danger can be more threatening than any number of unknown ones, and it seems that the others agree with you that it would be preferable for the Expedition to take its chances with the unknown and hopefully find only dangers that can be met with cannon and crossbow, and axe and sword. "Right," Snorri says. "First leg is the return to relative normality, rather than this barren plain of ruins and giant mushrooms. We get the cows as bargained from the Dolgan, or we steal as many as we can find if they decide not to stick to the deal, then we head west, skirting between mountains and Chaos Wastes as best we can until we reach a navigable descent from the steppe plateau." "Do we know what beasts we might encounter in the mountains?" Sir Joerg asks. "Scouting was entirely by gyrocopter," Snorri replies, "so it was mostly limited to confirming that there were navigable routes to find. It could be beasts from the mountains we know, or from the Mountains of Mourn, or some combination of the two. Or something entirely different." "We'll keep on guard, either way," Sir Ruprecht says, to further nods. --- As the Expedition's morale is likely to be somewhat shaky from Borek's abandonment of it, the apparent loss of Karag Dum, and the lack of any solid answers, you decide your time is best spent getting them out of the Chaos Wastes and back to relative normality as soon as possible. A couple of days of Rite of Way-smoothed travel later, you reach the abrupt transition from waste to steppe as you emerge from Yusak lands into Dolgan. There seems to be a watcher on every hill, and you hope that's a sign that they're eagerly looking forward to their honestly-earned silver, rather than watching for any sign of weakness. If that's what they are looking for they apparently don't find it, as the first morning out of the Chaos Wastes sees you greeted by the Ghur Shaman and a massive herd of cattle. "I trust you will accept cows in place of tea, Shadowed Shaman of the Mountain Ring Clans," he says, and you nod to him. He's quite different to the Amber Wizards you're used to, but then the Kurgan live much closer to nature than the citizens of Altdorf, so perhaps they see little need to distance themselves from the mannerisms of their people. "We will be happy to, Untamed Shaman of the Dolgan Tribes," you say as you climb down from the Alriksson. Behind you the Winter Wolves are doing their best to sort out the davits and hoists to unload the silver - cumbersome, but preferable to showing a crew of Dwarves to the Dolgan and raising questions about whether you're really the Norscans they've assumed you are. "How did the Blessed Lands receive you?" he asks politely. "Our leader was accepted by the Dum, and we last saw him entering the forest." "Truly?" the Shaman asks, his eyebrows raised. "A great honour for his Clan, and an admirable showing in the face of hardship." You raise an eyebrow at this, and he smiles. "The Iron Wolves are crowing to all that will listen how their Old One defeated a metal titan, and that its bones will arm their tribe for generations to come." You scowl. "Vultures pretending to be eagles. The road from the Zorn Uzkul is all that deserves credit for that kill." "We had thought as much, especially since you have returned intact. The Iron Wolves are the type to find the meekest lamb in a herd to vent their aggression upon, boasting all the while that they pave the way for their long-absent master." He smiles as the first of the silver reaches the ground. "Slaaksho Irnik will be well pleased. Much of this silver will become ornamentation that he is confident will be pleasing to Slaaneth. Our rewards will be grand. Slaakshami, Q'tlahs'itsu'aksho consorts, Q'qha'thashi'i mounts... who knows, perhaps even a favour from a Q'tlahsi'issho'akshami?" You conceal your wince at the terrible syllables of the Dark Tongue being spoken openly, and resolve not to mention this to the Dwarves. "Do you know anything of the mountains to the west of here?" you ask casually as the Shaman examines a bar of the silver. "You would know more than I from your earlier travels," he says with a shrug. "The only places where one can access them on horseback are in lands that have been controlled by the Kul since the last Great Crusade." Well, it was worth a try. As the Dolgan load up their silver onto a wagon that was almost certainly taken from a merchant travelling along the Road of Skulls, you and the other Wizards get to work seeing to the cattle, as first Sleep and then Mockery of Death is cast upon each in turn. Though the spell is one you have known for quite some time and is far from the most complicated piece of magic you know, casting it so many times in a row remains chancy. Familiarity leads to repetition, repetition leads to inattention, inattention leads to miscasts. For the rest of the trip you can space it out enough that it shouldn't be a problem, but with the Dolgan delivering the entire herd at once there's nothing for it but to grit your teeth and hope for the best. [Constant casting: Learning, 88+28=116.] [Rolling] You must admit that your attention did wander, but wandering attention is preferable to zoning out completely. You'd gone back to your promotion to Lady Magister, which is certainly a pleasant memory but also your formal introduction to the pocket dimension that the Grey College is entirely ensconced within, which also provides the mechanism for some of the more esoteric spells of Ulgu. Substance of Shadow is the one you know, and somewhere along the way of trying to mentally examine the spell itself for how it might link in to that border plane, some of the syllables of that spell slipped into Mockery of Death. And instead of exploding in your face as the spell had every right to do, the result was something more unusual. "Um, Mathilde?" Max asks, passing his hand through the solid-looking cow. "Paper," you say, and Max only hesitates for a second before fishing a notepad out of his pockets and passing it to you with a quill. With haste you jot down the shorthand for the syllabic jumble you'd inadvertently said before it drifts from your mind completely, and take a number of notes on the part where you'd inadvertently blended two syllables together in a way that didn't really translate to letters. "Okay, I think I know what happened there. Pass me the rope." Max does so, and you're able to loop it around the beast's torso without trouble. You hand the rope to Max, and he gives it an experimental tug and it remains in place, even as his hand once more passes through the cow's torso. "That's an interesting effect," he says diplomatically. "Still affected by gravity," you say thoughtfully, "and not dispelled by light. So not a straightforward blend of the two spells. And it doesn't appear to be suffocating. Max, can you feel its exhalations?" He waves his hand in front of the cow's nostrils, and nods. "So it's still able to interact with the air. Odd. And not terribly useful here and now. But in the future, perhaps." You jot down a few more notes, then return to the task at hand. [Mastery obtained - Mockery of Substance: When affected by Mockery of Death, the subject is also intangible to anything except the caster and objects under the control of the caster. They are still affected by gravity, and will still require food and water. They are still able to breathe normally. The caster can end the intangibility at a touch without interrupting the main effect of the spell.] --- The first few days of the next week will be spent skirting along the border of the mountains and the lands of the Kul, and then the rest of the week spent amongst those mountains descending to the Frozen Sea. It's not known what type of creatures of beings might call these mountains home, but the ground is likely to be unreliable as it would be the result of gravity and time rather than deliberate artifice. This is also the most natural time for you to fulfil your side of the bargain with the Ice Witches if you want to do it with Ljiljana's assistance - though if you're willing to do so completely solo or with only the assistance of Johann and Hubert, you could do it while the Expedition is crossing the ice, as the three of you are much more able to cover ground than the others. The four with the most votes will be chosen. Spend time getting to know... [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Use Rite of Way for the worst patches of rough terrain [ ] Use Rite of Way for the moderately difficult ground [ ] Use Rite of Way nearly constantly - For these, vote cumulatively. For example, if you want to use two of Mathilde's four choices on it, vote for both the 'rough terrain' and 'moderately difficult ground' options. [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Kul - These are the most infamous of Kurgan tribes, who gave rise to Asavar Kul. They are said to live to the west of Karag Dum. [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Iron Wolves [ ] Attempt to steal the Chaos artefact [ ] Explore these mountains for any exotic animals, plants, or phenomena If Heist wins: [ ] [HEIST] Alone [ ] [HEIST] Ljiljana [ ] [HEIST] Write in At this point, anyone can join it. If left until next week, it will only be Mathilde, Hubert, and Johann that have the mobility to do so. You can vote for who should be on the heist without voting to go on the heist. - There will be a one hour moratorium. - I didn't give an option for what to do for the Karag Dum - Dolgan land stretch since they decided to play nice and it would have resulted in three very short updates in a row. The action you would have gotten for that stretch is available here instead. - The end of this set of actions will see you at the edge of the Frozen Sea.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 20: Kul Encampment

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Use Rite of Way for the worst patches of rough terrain [*] Use Rite of Way for the moderately difficult ground [*] Attempt to steal the Chaos artefact [*] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler [*][HEIST] Ljiljana As the steam-wagons begin to make their winding way between the Chaos Wastes and the mountains, you and Ljiljana separate from it to perform the duty she has come all this way for: the theft of what the Ice Witches call the Za-Goblet, a filled chalice that mutates those that drink from it and, when emptied, shatters and vanishes to be rediscovered intact and refilled in another place and another time. The Ice Witches hope to take this potent tool of Chaos out of circulation permanently, and in doing so leave one less tool for the followers of the next Everchosen to arrive at Kislev's doorstep. As you leave sight of the steam-wagons, Ljiljana walks a zig-zagging path through the steppe, stopping here and there to sniff the air or touch a stone or have a whispered conversation with a breeze. Then, with the suddenness and intent of a loosed arrow, she takes off in a straight line slightly west of north. She'd turned down your offer of a Shadowsteed but her pace is impressive for any person, let alone one of her advanced years, and as she strides the muted heat of a northern summer begins to fade away and a chill radiates out from her. You've heard that the Ice Witches have their power muted the further they go from Kislev, but evidently nobody has told her that, and storm clouds begin to gather overhead as you nudge your Shadowsteed to a trot to keep up with her. "This land was our land until the Widow called," she says, apparently for your benefit as she does so in Reikspiel. "It is not beyond the Widow's reach, and it still remembers the Bear and the Sun and the Sky, who will answer the call of Their sister." Despite the clouds roiling overhead, the sun still shines brightly through, and somehow the pitiless glare of the sun and the biting chill of winter do nothing to cancel each other out. "By your Wind and your God, I would label you a sneak, but your reputation speaks of sword and gun. Does that reputation speak true?" "To an extent," you say cautiously. "Then let us remind the Kul why they celebrated when the Gospodar departed these lands." The snow beginning to fall does not seem to impede her. If anything, she seems to accelerate as the landscape turns white. You urge your Shadowsteed to a canter and then a gallop as you do your best to keep up with her, who never seems to walk faster than a determined stride even as the carpet of snow flows beneath her. If you'd known it was going to be this sort of adventure, you might have brought others along with you, but it's too late to do anything but curse the tight lips of the Ved'ma as the rising blizzard begins to howl. You're pretty sure you must have crossed into the Chaos Wastes by now, but all you see is a blanket of white as the power of the Widow stretches out to reclaim this land. Thunder rumbles overhead and you catch glimpses of hulking ursine figures through the snow keeping pace alongside you. Ljiljana has shed her coat and scarves along the way, but though her bared arms are thin and pale, the wiry muscles underneath give no impression of weakness as strange energies crackle along her fingers. All you can do is mutter a prayer to your own God and do your best to withstand the simultaneous heat and cold as you ride alongside this manifestation of Kislev's wrath. --- Slaakhamshy'y Yg'a'tedaar threw his head to and fro, ignoring the suddenly-falling snow and trying to taste the strange energy to the air. He was not one of the Tzeen'ksy that could feel and twist the God-Winds, but his elongated head had unlocked new senses when Slaaneth had gifted it to him. "Azyr'ksy!" he shrieked in anger, calling upon his Shaman in the only language he could still form the words of. "The future is clouded," said the cringing man who claimed to see fate in the sky as he approached, and Yg'a'tedaar's crab-like claw snapped at the Shaman's head in irritation, though stopping just shy of crushing him. One does not destroy a Shaman lightly. "Azyr'iakash?" he asked, and the Shaman shook his head. "Tzeen'iakash? Hysh'iakash? Ksy'akhshami!" "This is nothing from the Blessed Realm, Slaakhamshy'y," the Shaman said, still shaking his head. "The sudden snow, the piercing sun. This is the work of southerners, it must be." "Mnahn'akami?" Yg'a'tedaar asked, contempt and disbelief in his tone. "Mnahn'akami syha'hagl? Naflehye!" Perhaps if he had used that opportunity to rally his followers to his side instead of scoffing at his Shaman, he may have been able to put up a defence and survive the day, and perhaps eventually been awarded the final syllable that would mark his ascension. But instead Slaakhamshy'y Yg'a'tedaar found himself looking down at the spears of ice that had punched through his armour and into his chest, and his final thought was that his patron would not smile upon such an inglorious and uninteresting death. --- "Vdova, cześć, Kislev!" is Ljiljana's cry as the storm she has become the center of impacts and bowls over the palisade of the Kul settlement, and you guide your Shadowsteed to jump over the shattered wood and then dismiss it, landing lightly on your feet inside the camp. You pride yourself on your adaptability, so it's time to adapt. You reach out with your magical senses to try to read the terrain around you, even as your eyes and ears insist there's nothing but the white of snow and the howl of wind. [Magesight: Learning, 95+28+10(Windsage)+10(Avatar)=143.] [Read the battlefield: Martial, 13+23=36.] With the Divine energies contrasting against the Dhar that stains everything this far north, the world becomes clear in an instant. But seeing doesn't always mean understanding, if there's anything to understand of the mess of Kul warriors scrambling to get away from the onslaught of snow and spectral bears and jagged shards of ice. But Ljiljana's unspoken plan comes into focus as you gaze around the chaos and recontextualize the task once more. This is still a heist. Stealth doesn't always mean being unnoticeable, it can mean being merely less noticeable than whatever else is going on. And here and now, that covers just about everything. So you stealthily march straight across the battlefield, stealthily cutting down those unfortunate enough to get in your path. You reason that whether it's on display in a temple or protected as the treasure of a Champion, the Za-Goblet would be towards the center of the camp, so that's the way you go, pausing at the edge of the swirling snow to call down a torrent of Ulgu to shroud yourself in. [Spot check: Learning, 96+28+10(Windsage)=134.] [Stealth: 56+28+20(Distracted)=104.] After a short detour to bisect a Shaman attempting to call down Azyr, you weave your way through the crowd of warriors running to or from the blizzard towards a hideous stain of Dhar that itches at your eyes and parches your throat even at this distance. You beeline towards the shockingly large silk tent that you have to squint through the Dhar-taint to even make out and, checking that your presence has still gone unnoticed, duck through the ribbons that cover the entrance, only to stop abruptly as an overpowering wall of scent overwhelms you. As your senses struggle to make sense of the overwhelming smell, your eyes adjust to the candles inside the tent and you begin to make out a figure sprawled on the bed of pillows before you. Your Magesight immediately identifies horns and a claw and an unmistakable aura and screams Daemonette, but under your mundane eyes the figure shifts from a deeply tanned, battle-scarred, and severely underdressed maiden to a much more recognizable and equally underdressed figure, every detail exactly as you remember it. "You've come to rescue me," breathes what your eyes insist is Panoramia. [Bewitchment: Piety vs Intrigue, 71+26+20(Windsage)=117 vs 14+25+20(Glamour)+10(Musk)-10(Surprise)=59.] "Impersonating a Wizard is a capital offense." The Daemonette just has time to look startled before your bullet sends Daemonic ichor splashing across the pillows, and you shake your head as your senses immediately begin to clear - except for your hearing, which will be ringing from the gunshot for a while. Perhaps a bullet was an unwise choice, but in the moment you thought it preferable to getting closer or trying to wield magic in a Daemon's presence. You head right for a pile of chests and crates and push hurriedly through them, spilling precious metals and ornamented weapons across the silk floor until you find the case that glows with malign light, and before you realize what your fingers are doing you've opened the clasps and thrown the lid open. [Bewitchment again: Piety, 15+26+20(Windsage)-10(Again)=51.] You stare at the deep red liquid that bubbles softly within the embrace of the chalice, suddenly thirstier than you've ever been in your life. It seems to whisper to you, speaking of the gradual transformation that began twenty-five years ago when you first channelled Ulgu into your soul, and how much it could accelerate your ascension. If your Magesight wasn't quite so potent, if your soul wasn't already claimed, you might already be drinking. As it is you stand transfixed, torn between two equally overpowering urges: to embrace and to reject the Chaos Gods from whom your magic ultimately flowed. [Interrupt: Martial, 30+23-20(Surprise)=33 vs 35+15-20(Surprise)=30.] You'd owe a debt of gratitude to the Kurgan that burst into the tent at that moment for breaking your fixation on the liquid if they hadn't immediately drawn blades and attempted to kill you. Thankfully Branulhune is never further than a thought away, and it appears in midair to block the first blade as the second shot from your revolver sends the other two reeling back, trying to avoid it. [Round two: Martial, 72+23=95 vs 98+15=113.] You take one step back, then another, as Branulhune has to flit from place to place to fend off three different blades trying to find a way into your guts. The Kurgan are shouting either warcries or calls for help as they push forward, and you're very grateful for the tumult Ljiljana's causing outside that seems to prevent anyone else from taking heed and joining the three. But three would seem to be plenty, as part of the force of a few blows slipping through makes it through your Aethyric Armour, leaving aches that are vastly preferable to stab wounds but still an unwelcome distraction when fighting for your life. Round three: Martial, 69+23=92 vs 15+15=30.] One opening is all you need, and you get it when one of them slips on Daemonic ichor and clutches at a second as he fights to retain balance. For one crucial moment, the three-on-one becomes a very lopsided duel as Branulhune shatters the sword of the third Kurgan and goes on bite deep into his torso. The second takes a bullet to the chest as he tries to shrug off the grasping of his fellow, and the one who originally slipped goes sprawling as he tries to duck under Branulhune, and your downward thrust pins him to the silken floor before disappearing once more. You exhale, close the case, and shroud yourself in invisibility once more as you slip out of the tent and back into the tumult. [Ljiljana vs everybody: Learning vs Martial, 19+???+???(Widow?)+???(Tor?)+???(Dazh?)+???(Ursun?)=??? vs 66+20=86.] Outside the Kul have rallied, and their forces are forming up and delving into the blizzard to seek the mortal focus of the power at work here. You hesitate as you double-check the clasps on the case and secure it to your person, your eyes flicking over the hundreds of Kul and more charging to the assistance. You're not fully able to gauge the balance of power here, but it seems to be tilting against Ljiljana. She seemed quite ready to die to see the Za-Goblet denied to the forces of Chaos, so she'd likely consider it a win if you took the goblet back to the Expedition and turned it over to the other Ice Witches upon your return to Kislev. But on the other hand, perhaps that need not be how her story - and her life - ends. Given the opportunity to gird yourself with the many potent magics you know, you could be capable of tilting the battle single-handedly, routing the forces of Chaos as a second magical maelstrom is unleashed upon them. Or perhaps that is the voice of hubris, and you should make sure Ljiljana's sacrifice is meaningful by focusing on the fulfilment of her mission. [ ] Fight [ ] Retreat - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Part of this update was originally posted here. - Dark Tongue has only a handful of canon words, so I'm using Lovecraft's Cthuvian (which it seems to be partially based on) to fill in the gaps. Kislevarin is likewise fairly scarce, so I pick words from various Slavic languages based on whatever sounds best to my monoglottic ear. In general if I don't give a translation in the text, it's because the gist of what's being said is made clear by context. - With apologies to Sandy Mitchell.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 21

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Fight Scanning the battlefield, you resolve to add your own influence to it. But as your fresh bruises remind you, even if Branulhune is perpetually ready, you aren't. You reholster your revolver, draw your staff from your back scabbard, and take a moment to cast Aethyric Armour and feel the slight ache of exertion lift from your muscles. More concentration and a handful of whispered syllables sees the billowing gas of your form of Universal Confusion start to pour from you, and Dread Aspect has your shadow take form around you as a supernaturally terrifying aura. Then you interweave Smoke and Mirrors into a casting of Shadow Knives aimed at the nearest Kul, and you disappear from where you stand with a swirl of fog. [Join the melee: Martial, 70+23=93.] You appear mid-swing next to a Kul with a single brass horn emerging from his forehead, and take his head off his shoulders before anyone has time to react. By the time the men he was rallying are able to turn their weapons on you, the murderous tendrils of your shadow and the bewildering wisps of fog emanating from you have reached them, and you're able to cut through several more before they begin to scatter. With another burst of knives into the back of the nearest, you're gone. Another knot of resistance has formed around a shield-wall at the border of the tempest, but the central warrior being impaled by Branulhune has the others recoil first from him, then from the figure of terror doing the impaling. As Ulgu gives their greatest terrors form in your swirling silhouette, they drop their weapons and flee into the storm, and moments later a bolt of lightning obliterates them. A Kul wielding some sort of pike that sparks and shimmers to your Magesight is jabbing at a spectral bear, interrupting its feeding upon the fallen. It gives a silent roar and flinches away, but before the pike can find purchase in flesh or magic or wind given shape or whatever it is, you're there to slice first through the haft, then through their wrists. Then you disappear again, this time with the teleportation cantrip woven into a recast of Dread Aspect. A wooden cage contains a misshapen beast of mouths and limbs that must be a Chaos Spawn. You cut down the Kul trying to unleash it, and then cut open the cage, and then slice the Spawn into halves, then quarters, then keep cutting until it stops trying to bite you. It takes many more cuts than it should. It takes you almost too long to spot the gathering Ulgu, as at first you mistake it for a place you'd already visited. By the time you appear next to the Shaman, there's already a wailing adding to the din of the storm as reality begins to tear open and suck the air into the space between the physical and the Aethyr. It implodes in a scatter of arcing magical energies as the Shaman is cut down, and you flinch back and swear as the spilled blood begins to boil - more by reflex than out of any real danger, as your Belt protects you from extreme heat. You take a moment to dismiss Branulhune so the blood can fall from the blade, then resummon it as you scan the chaos for the next place to intervene. [Ljiljana vs Kul: Learning vs Martial, 74+???+???(Widow?)+???(Tor?)+???(Dazh?)+???(Ursun?)+30(Mathilde)=??? vs 99+20-10(Losses)=109.] Despite the hummock of snow that marks the boundary of Ljiljana's storm growing higher with buried bodies, the Kurgan keep coming. Perhaps that's only to be expected, as to the most devout of the Kurgan - which, by all accounts, would be the Kul - this would be the very definition of a holy war. To allow the Gods of the Gospodar to triumph over them could lose them the favour of their Gods, and this far into the Chaos Wastes that could be just as much of a death sentence as charging into the blizzard. [Continued intervention: Martial, 23+23=46.] Unfortunately the Kul seem to be catching on to your methods, as each teleportation starts to be met with shouted warnings as the most strong-willed push through the aura of confusion to meet Branulhune with their own blades. You and your shadow still reap a bloody harvest but it is now a battle, rather than a slaughter. You don't like fair fights so you switch from Shadow Knives to Melkoth's Mystifying Miasma for weaving your teleportation cantrips into, making sure that wherever you appear there is also a field of jittering time, sending even the most skilled warriors off-balance as their well-trained reactions encounter the concept of time as a variable. Blades lifting to parry a swing moving a hair too fast or too slow, feet stumbling as one moves slightly faster than the other, sights and sounds taking a fraction longer to arrive and shaving just enough time from their responses to make all the difference. You feel the change in the energy of the battlefield before what has heralded it comes into sight, as the Winds are battered backwards by an invisible and overwhelming force and magic begins to answer your call a little more hesitantly. A hulking figure barges through the crowd, his skin as brass as the spiked collar fixed to his neck, his arms lacking hands entirely, instead being fused directly to the haft of an enormous steel axe. He turns his gaze to you, hatred shimmering in his eyes, then to the blizzard. Enemy spellcasters or foreign Gods, which does a Champion of Khorne hate more? [Rolling...] Evidently, you. He charges straight in your direction, barging aside any foolish enough to get in his way as you ready your blade to meet the charge. You can't run from this foe without risking the entire battle, as if he meets the storm and brings his unholy patron into direct conflict with the Gods of Kislev, that could end it all. You can't turn spells directly on him either, not with any confidence, as the collar around his neck is a physical manifestation of the Blood God's hatred for magic. But that doesn't mean you're out of options entirely. So as the Champion gathers speed, you refresh the spells surrounding you and then ready another. [???: ???, 51+10(Making Amends)-10(Not Their Idiom)=51 vs 50+10(Hatred)-10(Split Attention)=50.] [Mathilde vs Khornate Champion: Martial, 58+23+20(Spells)=101 vs 33+30+20(Charge)=83.] A second before the Champion reaches you you vanish from vision, but they're either too lost to fury or too canny to think you've teleported and swing their axe in a great arc you're barely able to sidestep out of the way of. You swing Branulhune in an arc in return, and for the very first time since you received it, the blade judders in your hand as the Runically-enhanced force of the swing is arrested by the flesh it has only sunken partially into. You yank it free as the Champion roars in outrage, backpedalling from his next swing. [???: ???, 32+10(Making Amends)+10(Upper Hand)-10(Not Their Idiom)=42 vs 69+10(Hatred)-10(Split Attention)=69.] [Mathilde vs Khornate Champion 2: 10+23=33 vs 36+30-10(Wounded)=56.] But not fast enough, as the Champion's muscles swell with unnatural vigour as his swing meets your invisible stomach, causing you to cough and retch as your Aethyric Amour absorbs enough to turn what would have been a bisecting into an extremely painful blow to the gut. You look to the Champion's stomach for the response from your Belt, but instead the collar glows red and blood begins to seep down the Champion's neck, the influence of Khorne somehow denying the Rune of Rancour any purchase on His Champion. You backpedal further, looking for any opening and painfully aware that the impact of the axe has turned you visible once more. The air crackles with energy you can't spare the attention to examine and you can taste blood and bile that you swallow down. You let the staff fall from your fingers, trusting it to be sturdy enough to still be intact should you survive long enough to find it, and draw a revolver from its holster. It probably won't make a dent, but it might prove enough of a distraction... [???: 48+10(Making Amends)-10(Not Their Idiom)=48 vs 75+10(Hatred)-10(Split Attention)=75.] [Mathilde vs Khornate Champion 3: 38+23-10(Wounded)=51 vs 64+30-10(Wounded)=84.] Apparently not, as the Champion ignores the bullets slamming into its torso in favour of swinging his axe once more, meeting Branulhune halfway and sending an agonizing jolt through your arm as the two forces arrest each other. Is the Champion swinging with as much force as Kragg's Rune imparts on Branulhune? Surely not, or it would have cut straight through your Aethyric Armour without effort. It must be the aura of the Blood God dulling it, imposing brutal reality where strength is all that matters, not ephemeral energies and cunning artifice. And that is a battlefield that a Champion of Khorne is much more at home in than you are, as it recovers from the impact much faster than you do and swings the pommel of the axe into you, sending you sprawling. [???: 86+10(Making Amends)-10(Not Their Idiom)=86 vs 85+10(Hatred)-10(Split Attention)=85.] [Mathilde vs Khornate Champion 4: 77+23-20(Heavily Wounded)=80 vs 70+30-10(Wounded)=90.] It's been quite some time since you hurt this much, but you pull yourself to your feet once more nonetheless, meeting the gaze of the Champion as he approaches. He's not going to give you time for the Seed to restore you, and you don't trust it this close to the aura of his patron either. As you see his muscles bulge for another swing and ready Branulhune to try to meet it, you feel a strange sense of serenity. All you can do is the best you can... [Meanwhile, Ljiljana vs Kul 2: Learning vs Martial, 95+???+???(Widow?)+???(Tor?)+???(Dazh?)+???(Ursun?)+???(Ranald)=??? vs 2+20-30(Losses)=-8.] ...and hope you bought enough time. To his credit, the Champion of Khorne is more aware than you of events outside of your duel, and whirls to meet the oncoming figure. But it is not nearly enough. The axe shatters on skin crackling with Divine energies, and a wiry arm shoots out to grasp the Champion by the collar, lifting him off his feet as tendrils of frost engulf the bronze. "The disciple of Our kin is not yours to break," says Someone else with Ljiljana's mouth. "We are the inheritors of this world, and We will brook no interlopers." There's a creak and then a crack as the frozen metal gives way, and shards of bronze rain down as the collar shatters and the Champion falls free. In an instant the overbearing energies filling Ljiljana grow even stronger, and the Champion swings at Ljiljana with the ruined remains of his limbs as the blizzard engulfs him. When it recedes, he is frozen in place, his shattered axe and collar bearing testament to the power of Winter. Silence falls upon the camp, and you take a moment to run your eyes over the utter ruin where an encampment once stood. Bodies litter the ground, some frozen, some mauled, some burned, and some apparently untouched but just as dead, and there's not a living Kurgan in sight. "Pizdets," Ljiljana says in her own voice, flexing her hands. "Zhizn’ ebet meya, could have put a blade in, but no, had to use my fingers to break metal. Blyat, ja zaebalas." She turns her gaze to you, and to the blood dripping from your mouth. "Will you live?" With a thought, you nudge the Seed to do its work. "I'll be fine in a moment," you say. "How about you?" She looks down at herself, and the many rips in her clothing with unmarred flesh underneath. "Yha, did not quite reach the handle. You did well, tovaritch. Za-Nekulturny would have been bothersome." She exhales as she looks around the ruined encampment. "Downside of battle without rota, nobody to make carry the loot. Can your ghost-horse carry?" "Just a person, and whatever they can carry." "The cat weeps. You got Za-Goblet?" You nod, frown, check it's still there, then nod again and hand it over. "Good. Will fill pockets with silver. You should too." You exhale again and look over the ruins, where the first of the vultures and ravens are already descending. Silver is never unwelcome, but you hope you can find something a little more exotic for your troubles. The two with the most votes will be chosen. [ ] Silver Coins of every kind and hacksilver of unknown provenance. You should be able to carry a few hundred crowns' worth. [ ] Jewels Possibly more valuable than silver. Possibly just polished glass. [ ] Magic Weapons Some of the magical weapons do not bear the taint of Dhar, though you don't know who made them or what they do. They could be very carefully collected for future study. [ ] Scrolls In runes that look slightly similar to Queekish and you assume are Dark Tongue. There's no good excuse under the Articles for not throwing them in the fire immediately, but the same could be said for some of your other reading materials. [ ] Shrine An icon that appears to be dedicated to the moon you know as Mannsleib. The Kurgan worshipping the Chaos Gods and the Winds is easy to understand, the sun and the moons, not so much. You can feel some sort of Divine energy at work here, but can't say much more than that unless you're able to get it somewhere quiet for further study. [ ] Silks Definitely not the ones that the Daemonette was lounging across. Not quite spider-silk, but at least you'll beat Gretel to silk sheets. [ ] Khorne-Brass The metal of a Chaos God, shattered by the power of the Gods of Kislev. Even more unforgivable than the scrolls, should it be found on your person. But perhaps even more educational. - There will be a one hour moratorium. - Ranald vs Khorne rolls: 1st round, Ranald won and tried to use that victory to get an upper hand in future rolls. Rounds 2 and 3, Khorne won and used the opportunity to buff his champion, including the antimagic effect. Round 4, Ranald won and made sure that Ljiljana (who was on her way anyway) intervened before the Champion could finish you off.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 22: An Unnamed Mountain Range

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Shrine [*] Magic Weapons Unfinished business: [*] Use Rite of Way for the worst patches of rough terrain [*] Use Rite of Way for the moderately difficult ground [*] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler After a bit of thought, you collect up the magical weapons, wrapping their business ends with leather and silk to keep them from disagreeing with each other, and use some ropes to fashion the centrepiece of a shrine to the moon you know as Mannsleib into something like a very awkward backpack. As promised Ljiljana returns with her pockets bulging with precious metals, and you waste no time in summoning Shadowsteeds for the two of you and putting some distance between you and the ruined encampment. The pace of the Shadowsteed makes conversation difficult for Ljiljana and you give up on your attempts to winkle information out of her after you get nothing but Gospodarinyi expletives. It doesn't take too long for you to meet up with the Expedition once more, and without a word the two of you present a united front of aloof, mystical smugness to questions about the strange and violent storm that had dominated the horizon for much of the day. --- There's no sign of any pursuers, so in the coming days you turn your attention to the journey ahead. The path through these unnamed mountains is a rough one, as the path taken has seen no sculptor but time and gravity. Though the Alriksson has been the head of the convoy since the beginning, that is put aside here to rotate the steam-wagons in and out of the lead position to evenly distribute the wear and tear of having to carve a path through stone and rubble, the rams at the front of each becoming dented and chipped as the days wear on. Rite of Way helps to an extent, but it's here you encounter a major limitation of the spell: it actually reduces traction when going down a severe slope, as rough surfaces become smooth and brake-locked wheels slide right over the magically-created surfaces, just as the spell was intended to do. The days become a blur of stopping and starting the spell when appropriate, and grumbling amongst the Expedition frequently returns to the idea that Gotrek would have ideas for how to better handle the terrain if he was still with the Expedition. [Sliding down mountains: 28-10(no Gotrek)=18.] [Rite of Way: 18.] [Rolling for steam-wagon...] Unfortunately, when there's one spell trying to smooth the way for five fairly spread-out steam-wagons at once, there's going to be situations where what helps most will hinder others, and that appears to be what happens about two thirds of the way through the mountains: the Kriestov, currently fourth in the convoy, loses traction and begins to slide down the slope, accelerating as it dislodges stones beneath it that join it in a growing rockslide. Thankfully this time there isn't a terrible drop to swallow it, but when it leaves the relatively smooth area scouted out by the Knights and into uneven scree and hardy mountain trees, its momentum eventually fails it as the wheels on one side roll up a hillock and the wheels on the other buckle, and it ponderously and noisily topples over, turning the trees unlucky enough to be beneath it into splinters. Being the steam-wagon called home by the Winter Wolves, there's only Dwarves aboard during most of the day and they're hardy enough to emerge swearing and grumbling within minutes, fretting more over the steam-wagon than their own injuries. Their concerns are quickly vindicated: with axles bent, driveshafts twisted and pipes torn free, there's no hope of getting the steam-wagon mobile again in anything less than weeks, more likely months, and there's nothing for it but to transfer everything useful to the other steam-wagons, destroy everything that can't be allowed to fall into enemy hands, and keep on moving. The cows that survived the toppling fill the gaps opened up atop the other steam-wagons by the Expeditions' appetites over the past two weeks, and the ones that didn't fill the bellies of the wolves and Demigryphs. Still preferable to facing the crevasse opened up by the Urmskaladrak, you conclude as the toppled Kriestov disappears behind you. --- "Journeywoman Kohler," you say as you knock on the open door of her cramped cabin. "May I have a word?" "Certainly, Lady Magister," she responds, dogearing the book she's reading from and turning to you. "Please, have a seat." "Thank you," you say, sitting atop her bed, the only available flat surface. "I thought I'd check in with you after the events so far, see how you're doing with all of it." "Much of it wasn't what I expected," she admits with a shrug. "I thought that we'd be fighting for every league, but our speed and show of strength seems to have gotten us most of the way without too much trouble from the locals. I suppose we're not giving them enough time to work up their courage." "Came for the fight and got mysteries instead?" you ask. She shrugs again. "Wouldn't put it that way, as it's not much of a mystery. They made a deal with forces they shouldn't have, and now they're just one more drop of Chaos in a sea of it. Still, at least now the Dwarves know. And it's not like the trip was entirely wasted, thanks to Karak Vlag." "That is likely to be what is focused on when we get back," you say with a nod. "And it means we did get at least one proper battle out of the journey. How do you feel about your showing?" Truth be told, you'd missed whatever contribution she'd made in all that was happening, so you'd deliberately phrased the question to fit however she feels she did. She sighs. "I think I prefer it more, well, intimate. Throwing fire from behind fortifications into a mass of enemies wasn't that much different to practicing back at the College once I shook off the whispers." You wonder if that's a true statement of preference, or just a justification for what she might be seeing as a poor showing. "Everyone has their niche. The major battles might be what they write songs about, but there's skirmishes every day somewhere in the Empire. And your College should be able to match you up with an appropriate force if you decide to go that route, the Bright Order has good relations with most of the Empire's armies. A letter of recommendation from the Dwarves would get you in the door, and from there you could either build a relationship with a specific Division or Regiment, or go to wherever the hotspots are and lend your services as needed." She nods. "I'll keep that in mind. Thank you, Lady Magister." You take a moment to consider her. More than any of the others, Alexandra Kohler might be the Wizard least affected by her journey through the Wastes, and after a few years might see this as one mediocre battle, one notable accomplishment, and a lot of dull travel. You wonder if that makes her steadfast, or lucky, or just incurious. Or it might just be that you're too different to really connect and get much of a read on her. A charcoal burner much of her life, and a Bright Wizard now - it would be difficult to think of an upbringing more different than your own. Still, even though you're unlikely to come away from this considering her anything more than an acquaintance, you got the job done. The Bright College entrusted this Wizard to you, and unless the final stretch goes badly, you'll be returning her intact and with a new notch on her belt. That's what matters. "Did you get a chance to offer your services to the Engineers?" you ask, pausing on your way out the door as you recall mentioning that possibility to her at your first meeting. "With Inextinguishable Flame, yes, for a while. Head Engineer Gurnisson was studying its effects on the Urmskaladrak. But after it was lost, the other Engineers don't want to take a chance with it." "Ah," you say, a little disappointed. "I suppose that's not unexpected. Dwarves tend to be wary about changes to their designs in general, and around magic in particular." --- What wildlife there is that calls these mountains home seems to have no desire to approach the rumbling chorus of engines, and if it were not for a handful of reports from the Knights of Taal's Fury of wary Sabretusks deciding against conflict with packs of Demigryphs, you'd be left with the impression that there was no life in these mountains but hardy trees. Perhaps that's evidence that these mountains are more relations of the Mountains of Mourn than the World's Edge Mountains, or perhaps it's an isolated population that's made itself at home far from its native range - it's impossible to say one way or the other without a proper study. Whatever the case, they aren't making a nuisance of themselves, so for the Expedition's purposes they can be discounted entirely. As the convoy finally reaches sea level, you relax your grip on Ulgu and run your eyes over the endless expanse of blues and whites. You'd expected something as flat as a frozen pond in a Stirland winter, but the sea here seems to have been frozen between one instant and the next in the midst of a roiling storm, with vast, smooth mountains and valleys of frozen waves giving the surface texture where you expected none. A relentless biting wind blows from the north, mirroring the Winds blowing far overhead, and the snow piling in the low points seem like they'll give the steam-wagons some traction as they weave their way through the unmoving waves. Merciless terrain to those that don't bring their heat with them, but to the Expedition, it will hopefully prove a nice, quiet interlude before the final sprint through Norsca. The four with the most votes will be chosen. Spend time getting to know... [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Be ready to use Rite of Way should it prove necessary [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Baersonlings - The Norscan tribe that calls the area you'll soon be travelling through home. They are known for their bravery and their golden hair. [ ] Study the seals and ice crabs that call this ice home - With Esbern and Seija [ ] Attempt to locate and observe an icebreaker-led convoy from Uzkulak - There will be a one hour moratorium. - The end of this set of actions will see you at the edge of Baersonling territory in Norsca, with about one week remaining until you reach Kislev.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 23: The Frozen Sea

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Ice Crone Ljiljana [*] Be ready to use Rite of Way should it prove necessary [*] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [*] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann As the steam-wagons grind their way across the frozen landscape, everyone who ventures out from the warmth radiating from the boilers is wrapped in the winter gear that has been mostly lying unneeded in the cargo holds. The only exception is Ljiljana, who has erected a hammock atop the Magnus with one end tied to the funnel and the other to the fore cannon. The display reinforces your suspicion that Wizards are Wizards wherever they come from, and an affinity to the ephemeral energies of the world comes with an overwhelming desire to show off. It may have somewhat backfired as the concerned Knights have been emerging every so often to check that she hasn't succumbed to the cold despite her insistence that she's as comfortable as they would be on a Tilean beach, but then again, perhaps she's not entirely displeased by being doted over by large young muscular woodsmen, especially since it gives her the opportunity to get them to fetch snacks and drinks for her basking. "You have questions," she says as you approach. "Tch. Imperinyi zabloudit-ved'ma always have questions. Lost as children in a blizzard." "'Nothing in this life or the next is free,'" you quote, "'and whilst I am willing to trust in my own abilities and limitations, and accept any errors I make while weaving my spells, I do not wish to trust the continued benevolence of a deity whose need for my faith and dedication might far outweigh my own need for His or Her aid.'" "Pretty words," she says after a moment of thought. "Your Volans, yha?" "Yes." She opens her eyes and looks at you. "But you do not follow his advice, do you? Was not just you staring down Karneth, was it? If child in blizzard emerges with a new friend, they are one to watch. Even if yours is not quite so respectable as a bear or wolf or owl." "Do you think Gods are necessary partners for wielding magic?" She snorts. "Pointless to go without. A bachór feeding from a boyar's garbage is just as bound as those sworn to his service." "I suppose that makes sense, if that's how you see the Winds. You think they won't always be a constant?" "I think it is foolish to assume they will be. If our Gods abandon us, we will know why. If your Winds stop blowing, will you?" You consider that. "I'd like to think we could figure it out," you eventually say, "but I'll grant you they might not be considerate enough to give warnings." "Yha. The source of our power is never shy with anger, and then can be, shtuka, przebłagać... honoured and made pleased again. Can the Winds? Can Ulgu?" You nod, silently conceding the point. It's a similar point to the comparison Cython had made between Gods and Winds, but approached from the other direction. However similar the two might be, as far as you know there's no way to propitiate a Wind. Does that make Gods preferable? Then again, Winds are remarkably free of baggage, too. "You said that Ranald had wronged the Widow in some way," you probe. "And now he seems to be making amends. You do not know the tale?" You shake your head. "The short of it is that the Widow and Her siblings were once much more than four, before Salyak had your Ranald interfere." She sighs, and closes her eyes again. "The details are ugly, and not to be shared with those outside Their service. In the aftermath They found us, the Gospodar. So perhaps it was for the best. But amends are still required." You frown, considering that. "I thought Salyak was quite well established in Kislev." "Salyak is easier to forgive," she says with a snort. You make several mental notes with the intention to cross-reference this with everything you can get your hands on later, and by the time you're done with that, Ljiljana has begun to snore. You smile and shake your head before retreating from the chill of the northern winds. --- You find Snorri in his quarters, poring over an assortment of maps. "Loremaster," he says, not looking up. "Any insight on our route to be found there?" "Not any time soon," he says with a snort. "Who'd map this? Land cartographers just draw the outline of the sea and call it a day, and the ocean-going ones can't exactly sail or steam their way here. No, I'm looking at the last leg of our route before we hit Kislev." You sit alongside him and study the map. "Where are we coming ashore?" He points at an inlet. "Here, this fjord will take us straight into Black Blood Pass. There's apparently a Baersonling village there, but there's no going around them - it's thick woods on one side and a river on the other. Southwest through the pass, past..." he squints at the map, "I'm pretty sure that says 'sausage lake', and then to Fort Straghov at the other end of the Pass." "Any interesting landmarks nearby?" He points at an unmarked patch of mountains. "I've heard that the source of one of the feeder rivers to this Sausage Lake is at a Norse Dwarf settlement, Kraka Ravnvake. Couldn't tell you which one. There's been a few Expeditions to try to find it, and none have found anything but collapsed tunnels. There's a major Skaven stronghold nearby too, though I can't recommend giving it a visit. Apart from that, just mountains and Norscans as far as the eye can see." You nod. "And after Black Blood Pass?" "Two weeks to Praag, which should be uneventful, as we'd be traveling alongside the Tobol which marks the edge of Troll Country and Kislev built a chain of forts alogn it after the Great War - used to be the furthest settlement north was Zioshenk, which is another week south of Fort Straghov. East from Fort Ostrosk to the North Lynsk, then follow it south to Praag, and from there the Expedition dissolves. Knights travel back to Talabecland, Winter Wolves to Ulrikadrin, steam-wagons to Karak Kadrin, and my Rangers back home to High Pass. Get to work on trying to convince Karak Vlag they're back in reality, I suppose. Make sure nothing tries to move in to the upper levels before they retake them." "You think Clan Redbeard will join Karak Vlag?" He shrugs. "Perhaps, in time. Our fate will be interwoven with theirs for the foreseeable future either way. Even if we remain part of Karak Kadrin, our task at High Pass won't be properly completed until guarding it can be turned over to Karak Vlag once more." You nod, making a mental note. Gotri had mentioned the possibility of recruiting Snorri for Clan Huzkul, but it looks like he's not going any further south than Praag for the foreseeable future, as he considers himself dutybound to Karak Vlag one way or the other. "So we're almost done," you say. He nods firmly. "I'll be glad to put this behind me and get my legs under me again. Karak Vlag might have made it all worthwhile, but everything after that was a disaster. The best we can say is that now we don't need to wonder any more, and now there'll be no more Borek trying to convince anyone that will listen to spend lives on discovering the fate of Karag Dum." You nod, and let silence take over for a while as you try to think of the best way to phrase the next question. "Will Karak Kadrin take responsibility for contacting Gotrek's widow?" you finally say. "They should," Snorri says darkly, "but I wouldn't trust them to do the job properly. I'll be sending a few letters with the Expedition, I know a few Dwarves there I trust to deliver the news suitably, and offer support to them." "Karak Eight Peaks was going to try to recruit Gotrek after the Expedition," you say after a moment's thought. "The offer still stands for his widow and daughter, if they'd like." Snorri looks surprised, then thoughtful. "The new Engineers Clan?" he asks, and you nod. "I was going to offer the same from Clan Redbeard after I badgered the Elders into letting me. I'll give her both offers, though I've a feeling she'll continue to go her own way. She has an independent streak a mile wide, same as Gotrek." --- You stare out at the seemingly endless ice, trying to remember to keep your eyes slitted to keep from going snowblind. So far the steam-wagons seem to be handling the snow-covered ice as well as could be hoped, thanks to the route the Knights determine at the end of each day that will take the Expedition through the smoothest gullies and keep it from bare ice exposed to the constant wind. You've lent magical assistance here and there, but so far it doesn't feel like you've made significant difference in the Expedition's speed, just shaved off a few minutes on the rougher patches. "Lady Magister," Egrimm says as he comes alongside you, arms hugged to his torso against the chill of the air. "You wanted to talk to me?" You glance around the deck, which has been bereft of other souls for hours. "Now is probably the best time," you say. "I wanted to check in with you about your Light Wizards." He nods. "I thought you might. Barbitus specifically, right?" "He seemed normal enough to me when we studied the Windfall, but..." "But since then we've ventured into the Chaos Wastes, where Dhar lies thick on the ground and we all come out a bit more tainted than when we entered," he says with a nod. "I'm going to write a very strongly worded refutation to the 'Chaos Wastes is a relative term' theory as soon as I get back to Altdorf. It couldn't have been any more clearly demarcated if it had a checkpoint." He shakes his head and rubs his arms. "Barbitus. He's sleeping and eating better, but it's hard to say with any certainty if that's necessarily a good thing. He might be more at peace because he's thrown off the influence of Chaos..." "Or he might be more at peace because he's accepted it," you finish, and Egrimm nods grimly. "How do you want to handle it?" "I'm still torn," he admits. "If he's tainted, he should be executed - for his own good, as if the tendrils are not yet too deep, he might still go on to a peaceful rest. If he's not, he should be allowed to continue with his Journeying and some day become our peer. But I can't say for sure one way or the other, not with any confidence, and there's no way to get hard answers without tainting his future career if he is innocent. Demotion to Apprentice or handing him over to the Magisters Vigilant might prevent a future Black Magister, but it's also very likely to prevent a future Light Magister, too." You nod. "I'll give the matter some thought," you say, and let the rumbling of the engines fill the air for a while. "Any thoughts on what we encountered at Karag Dum?" "I've been trying to get it straight in my mind," he says, "but what we saw doesn't make any sense once you look past the surface. It's easy to say 'they're guarded by a Chaos thing, ergo they fell to Chaos, job done, off we go'. But I've read of the Shadowgave before, and though it shares several properties with Daemons, the way it acts is entirely different to them. As far back as is known, it acts according to whim and chance, reacting to whatever stimuli it encounters. The closest thing it has to any sort of motivation beyond killing and eating and twisting is its tendency to wander in the direction of Athel Loren." "And yet it is acting like a Daemon either bound or summoned by Karag Dum," you finish. "I could hazard some guesses as to how that would be possible, but it would require much greater insight into whatever the Shadowgave actually is for them to be any more than guesses. Maybe they've convinced it that the woods that have sprung up around the base of Karag Dum are Athel Loren, or replaced whatever fascination it has with Athel Loren with an obsession with their mountain, or some other means of manipulation, but whatever theory you apply, it requires an understanding of Beastmen that Karag Dum has no reason to have. Beastmen don't exist in the Chaos Wastes - they're the antithesis of civilization and cannot exist without it. Animalistic mutants back there are simply accepted by their tribe instead of being cast out to form a separate society." "All of that makes sense," you say after some thought. "But what conclusion does that lead to?" "I haven't the faintest idea," Egrimm admits. "But I think the answer lies in the nature of the Shadowgave. It doesn't fit neatly into any known category - it's not fully a Beastman, not truly a Daemon, definitely not a Sorcerer. I think if you can figure out what category it is in, you can start to ask actually meaningful questions - like how the Dwarves know enough of whatever that nature is to manipulate it." You sigh. "So much of these past few months would make such amazing papers if I had just a few less questions and a few more answers." He chuckles. "That's the nature of the job. The Light College's basements are practically exploding with bits and pieces we've never been able to figure out." "Any idea what you're going to do after all this?" His smile vanishes. "None," he says with a sigh. "Alric likes to use me as a troubleshooter, so until I make Lord Magister or Mira takes over again, I'm stuck cleaning up his messes - and that's if he's not outright preventing me from advancing so I have to keep doing so. So no doubt I'll have at most a few weeks to potter about in Altdorf until he sends me off on some new errand." He grimaces, then forces himself to relax. "And you?" "Back to Karak Eight Peaks, I suppose," you say. "Of course. First non-Dwarven Loremaster of a Karak in recorded history, and all that." "Mm, that might be the problem. It was all well and good when we were a foothold facing..." you frown, and take a moment to count, "eight different enemy factions, but now that the Karak is reconquered and secured and getting more so every week, there's not really bizarre and potentially dangerous oddities that need poking on a regular basis. The job's probably mine for as long as I want it, and it might just be my imagination, but it's seeming like Belegar's finding work for me, rather than me being the answer the Karak needs. A more traditional Loremaster, one that knows the laws and the traditions and the Clans and the Guilds inside and out, might be a better fit for the problems the Karak has now." "Or it might be that now there's not eight factions to stare down, you're getting itchy feet," Egrimm says shrewdly. "Did King Belegar send you on this Expedition?" "No," you admit. "Just asked that I assist in its preparations." "When Loremaster Weber saw the breadth of her domain, she wept, for there were no more worlds to conquer," Egrimm says, and grins at the look you shoot him. "Most Wizards would be ecstatic with that sort of sinecure. But most Wizards would have more sense than to be trundling in a wheeled boat over a frozen sea. Just leaves more fun for the likes of us, right?" He smiles, then shivers. "I'm going to head back to the Volans before parts start dropping off. Let me know if you come up with any input for the Barbitus situation." As he leaves sight, you allow yourself the shiver you've been holding in ever since he'd arrived and seriously consider ducking back below to visit the kettle perched atop the boiler, but not before turning your eyes back to the ice ahead. Very soon the ice will give way to land, and right after that the Baersonling-dominated Black Blood Pass. As Snorri said, one more week of travel should see you through to civilization in the form of Fort Straghov, and from there you can part ways with it with a clean conscience, as the remainder of the journey will be through firmly Kislevite territory - though you might stick with it until at least Praag, you haven't decided yet. Do you have a recommendation for how Egrimm should handle the question of Barbitus? [ ] [BARBITUS] Execution A sudden death, and transportation to a Garden of Morr to be interred. [ ] [BARBITUS] Demotion Reduced to Apprentice and returned to the rigid routine of the Light College for long-term observation. [ ] [BARBITUS] Scrutiny Turned over to the Magisters Vigilant for testing, which is likely to be painful but at least should be quick. [ ] [BARBITUS] Interrogation Intervene personally, and spend several days interrogating and studying him to see if you can determine if he has succumbed or thrown off the influence of the Chaos Gods. Will take up an action. [ ] [BARBITUS] Nothing - Allow Barbitus to continue his Journeying unimpeded, with nothing more than a note in his file for an eye to be kept on him in the future. [ ] [BARBITUS] No recommendation - Leave the matter in Egrimm's hands. [ ] [BARBITUS] Other (write in) Will you leave the Expedition in a week's time when you reach Fort Straghov, or stick with it for another two weeks until Praag? [ ] [DEPART] Part ways at Fort Straghov [ ] [DEPART] Remain with the Expedition until Praag The four with the most votes will be chosen - or three, if Interrogation wins the Barbitus vote. Spend time getting to know... [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Be ready to use Rite of Way should it prove necessary [ ] Attempt to make contact with the Baersonlings - The Norscan tribe that calls the area you'll soon be travelling through home. They are known for their bravery and their golden hair. [ ] Attempt to scout the Skaven stronghold of Hell Pit [ ] Attempt to find the Norse Dwarf outpost of Kraka Ravnvake - There will be a two hour moratorium. - The decision as to whether Mathilde leaves the Expedition at Fort Straghov is entirely one about whether you want two more turns of Expedition or to wrap it up after this coming turn. From that point on it will be in friendly territory and will be able to get everyone home safe, whether Mathilde is there or not.

A Visitor to Karak Vlag

Dozens of eyes peer suspiciously through the darkness at the pool of light that was the latest arrival amongst the many beings claiming to be Dwarves that now swarmed the upper levels of Karak Vlag. Their every word and movement rang true, but so it had innumerable times before, and every previous time it had ended the same way. Eventually these new interlopers stopped trying, and seemed to be waiting for some new plot to hatch. At long last what they had been waiting for is carried into the chamber that is the border between safety and danger, held atop the shoulders of four sturdy Dwarves, Runelight glinting off the steel and gromril that covers them, and placed in the center of that chamber. The many illusions and glamours of the Daemons had often included a High King, usually come to laud them for their steadfastness. Sometimes the Throne of Power had been brought along too, the twinkling of the counterfeit Rune of Eternity filling their hearts with false pride and the seductive promise that the Karaz Ankor had not forgotten them. But this time, it was different. This time, the High King was not Alriksson. This time, the Rune of Eternity did not reach out to them but instead stood unmoving, a stark light in the darkness that was somehow realer than the stone that surrounded it. This time the High King bore something that the Daemonettes had never even tried to seduce them with: the Dammaz Kron. "'In the year 6824, contact was lost with Karak Vlag as the forces of the Everchosen Asavar Kul made their way through High Pass,'" Thorgrim Grudgebearer reads, his voice carrying through the darkness. "'Extensive scouting in their wake revealed that Karak Vlag had been made to disappear, appearing to most scrutinies as though it was never founded.' It was decided that until new information came to light, the Grudge would be levelled against the Chaos Gods collectively, and against all that follow them." A slight squeaking echoes as an inkwell is unstoppered, and the nib of a quill is dipped into the royal blood within. "This is insufficient. The Karaz Ankor must know the being or beings responsible for the disappearance of Karak Vlag." The High King's gaze seems to penetrate the defences that the Dwarves of Karak Vlag were huddled behind, and afterwards each would swear that they were looked directly in the eye. "It is our duty." All the Dwarves that stood between the Daemons and the Karak were those Longbeards old enough to remember another world, but the first Dwarf to emerge is an Elder even amongst these, who would likely be somewhere in his fourth century if the passage of time could still be known with any confidence. Perhaps his wisdom allows him to recognize the truth, or perhaps he is willing to surrender his life to the Daemons in the hope that this time, at long last, it was not a trick. In any case he approaches the Throne of Power, and when no evil springs from the darkness to carry him away, he begins to speak of the many evils inflicted upon the Dwarves of Karak Vlag in the lifetimes they had been trapped in the Warp. --- By the time the recitation of evils is done, many pages have been filled and a second inkwell has been unstoppered and subsequently drained. The breath goes out of the Dwarves as the final dot marks the end of the final sentence, for by now they have emerged, one by one, to add their own wrongs to the tally. To have the crimes against them recorded does not bring them pride or comfort, but the weight of the Grudges within them now had a sense of rightness to them. They would still do everything in their power to set matters right, but should they fail or fall the Karaz Ankor would remember, and the Karaz Ankor would avenge. Even if it took until the end of time and the last drop of Dwarven blood to make it so. "Now," Thorgrim says, running his eyes over the Longbeards before him, "tell me which of these Grudges have already been avenged, which Daemons you know to have fallen after performing the deeds I have recorded." Silence fills the air, as glances go back and forth amongst the Longbeards as they roll the question around in their minds. They could tell of Daemons who had been slain, or at least wounded until they stopped moving and their essence melted away into the background matter of the Chaos realm. But all of that was lost in the long, timeless chaos of more years than could be counted straining to see movement in the darkness before it could steal away another Dwarf to be bewitched. More prominent, so much more prominent than any of those battles was the knowledge that each of them somehow held, and knew in their souls to be true: the intervention of the strange Zhufokrul, the severing of the flow of magic, the shattering of the imprisonment spell, and the battle where Slayer had cut down Slayer, and Dwarf and man and beast and Wizard and Dragon and even an Elf had inflicted vengeance upon each and every one of the Slaaneshi Daemons, scattering their essence across the mountain stone far from their native realm. They knew of the dangers she had risked in doing so, not just against the claws and blades of the Daemons, but also the many terrible fates that could befall someone who bends the energies of magic to their will. And they knew that she did so for no other reason than because it was the right thing to do. It was a strange and troubling tale, one that they could not explain their ability to tell, but every one of them knew it was true. The Elder takes a breath, and tells High King Thorgrim Grudgebearer of the Wizard that each of the twenty thousand remaining Dwarves of Karak Vlag know to be their saviour.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 24: Draksfjord

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] [BARBITUS] Interrogation [*] [DEPART] Remain with the Expedition until Praag [*] Attempt to make contact with the Baersonlings [*] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [*] Attempt to find the Norse Dwarf outpost of Kraka Ravnvake -[*] With Johann In the Steppes, the Expedition avoided most conflicts by speed and bluff. Neither will serve you with the Baersonlings. The Norscans are much more likely to be able to identify an Imperial by sight and accent, and here they occupy a chokepoint between a river and a forest on the entrance to Black Blood Pass. Taking them by surprise seems more likely to lead to an unwanted conflict than it is to avoid it, so you organize a suitably impressive escort of Winter Wolves - enough to cause them to think before they act, not so much that they take it as a raiding party - and ride for the Baersonling settlement the day before the steam-wagons are due to arrive there. It's easy to assume that Black Blood Pass is named for the general role that Norsca plays in Kislev's history, but it's actually named for Black Blood River. Water trickling in from volcanic springs stirs the deep and ancient mud on the bed of the lake Snorri labelled 'Sausage Lake', and it flows out again blackened and sluggish and steaming. When it reaches the Frozen Sea it forms an oasis of life as the heat of the water holds back the ice and the minerals in it cause a flourishing of ocean life. It's a natural place for a settlement, and as it comes into sight it becomes clear that the Baersonlings weren't the first to take advantage of it. At the centre of a sprawling cluster of wooden Norscan structures are stone buildings laid out with geometric precision around stone roads, with long, sturdy wharves allowing access to every inch of liquid water. "Must have been a Norse Dwarf harbour," you say to Sir Ruprecht beside you. "The Dwarves aren't going to like this." "I already don't like this," he says, nodding towards the trees visible over the roofs of the settlement. At first you think that the nearest are swaying in the breeze, but then you realize that the movements are much too violent for that, and a series of cracks echo like gunshots as the trunk of a great tree surrenders to the grip of the mammoth that is assaulting it. It bellows in triumph as the tree falls, reaching out with its trunk to tear off branches and shovel them into its maw, and the rhythmic thuds of axes begin to sound as the Norscans get to work on the tree their mammoth has felled. Well, that complicates matters. But the Norscans aren't going to get any less in your way just because the situation just got uglier. So you take a deep breath and lead the way over the ice towards the settlement, keeping your pace relaxed even as a horn blows somewhere amongst the buildings and an armed, watchful, and mostly blond crowd gathers on the shore, watching your approach. You've no intention of alarming them and prompting a hasty reaction. The Norscans are renowned for martial valour but they're dab hands at archery too, possibly due to cultural cross-pollination from their coreligionists of the Steppe. "Heill ok sæll," you say as you approach, hoping you have the pronunciation correct. Happy and healthy is a cheerful enough greeting until you realize that it serves dual purpose as a threat: ready to fight and glad for the opportunity to. "I am here to speak to your leader." Beside you, a Nordlander of the Winter Wolves translates into the Norscan tongue. "I am Vindslaktare, Chieftain of Sjoktraken," comes the translation of the reply of the man who steps forward, a short and wiry man of advanced years with a sword of shimmering black stone and a short, greying beard. "Why are Southerners approaching from the north?" "Our fleet seeks to travel to the lands of the Gospodar." "In service to the Wolf-God?" he asks, running his eye over the Winter Wolves. "Our service was fulfilled in the lands of the Kurgan. Now we return with the favour of our Gods." There's some chatter amongst the crowd at that, a few stepping forward to mutter to the Chieftain while a few shouted suggestions that you probably don't need translated. "You wish to avoid spilling blood?" Vindslaktare says after listening. "Then pay the blood price for passage." "What they call 'weregild'," the Nordlander explains. "200 silver coins for a free-man, ten times that for their equivalent of a Knight." "Over ten thousand crowns," you say after a moment's thought. "Exorbitant. And with your mounts, they're unlikely to believe that you're 'just' free-men." And if you try to negotiate, you'd have to mention the numbers of your Expedition to have a figure to negotiate, and your low numbers might convince them that they're in a position to press an attack and win. "Do we have any other options?" "Apart from just bulling through? We could challenge them," the Nordlander says. "Champion against Champion, or Vitki against Vitki - that would be a Wizard against their Shaman or Sorcerer. Our victory would mean the Gods intend for us to pass unhindered. Or we could gift them our excess cows in exchange for being invited to a feast, which would leave us covered under their hospitality traditions, which would also allow us to pass - though the feast would be dedicated to their Gods." "Your call," Sir Ruprecht says, "but I think I could take him. And I definitely think Joerg could." You consider the options as you return the gaze of the Norscan Chieftain, who seems filled with grim anticipation. As the Nordlander mentioned, the other option would be simply smashing your way through the Baersonling settlement, which the steam-wagons should be fully capable of doing - either by full light of day or by surprise at night. But that mammoth of theirs, which is already shaking the earth as it wanders over to see what's going on, could complicate matters. [ ] Martial Challenge -[ ] Joerg -[ ] Ruprecht -[ ] Snorri -[ ] Asarnil [ ] Magical Challenge -[ ] Yourself -[ ] Johann -[ ] Maximillian -[ ] Egrimm -[ ] Michel -[ ] Ljiljana [ ] Feast [ ] Day Assault [ ] Night Assault [ ] Negotiate passage fee [ ] Other (write in) - There will be a two hour moratorium. - As the Expedition is so close, there's no time to go back and confer with the rest of the Expedition's leadership. You and Ruprecht have enough authority between you to make the decision without upsetting Snorri and Joerg. - You can vote for a candidate for either of the Challenges without voting for the Challenge itself. Simply vote for '-[ ] Whoever' without voting for the '[ ] Challenge', and that way if the Challenge wins you will have a say in who will be fighting in it. - The other options chosen for this 'turn' will take place after you gain access to Black Blood Pass. - You are only a week away from Kislev, so there should be no supply problems from gifting cows to the Baersonlings. - If you challenge and lose, then you're back to square one with the challenge option off the table. The challenge is to the death, with the loser considered a sacrifice to the God of the winner.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 25

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Martial Challenge -[*] Asarnil "Tell the Chieftain that we'll challenge them for passage," you say to the Nordlander as you make up your mind. "I just have to head back to the Expedition to fetch our Champion." "Joerg, then?" Sir Ruprecht asks. "No," you say, smiling as you turn your Shadowsteed. --- By the time you return, much of the Norscan town has gathered around a small island in the frozen sea where the challenge will take place. You've read that the tradition exists so that nobody can interfere with the battle and there's no chance of escape for anyone that tries to flee, and it seems that the Baersonlings maintain that tradition despite the very different sea. It does have the advantage that spectating is simply a matter of walking over instead of having to anchor a longship offshore. Those Norscans hoping for a good show are immediately rewarded by your arrival, as instead of having a rider alongside you, you ride in the shadow of Deathfang as he lazily drifts through the air, moving much slower than he is capable of to give onlookers a proper chance to register the majestic being that has deigned to grace them with his presence. He swoops low over the island as the Norscans duck and Asarnil hops lightly off at the nadir of the arc, allowing his momentum to drive the Dragon banner of Caledor into the stone and running an amused eye over the would-be spectators. "Ah, Norscans," he says as you arrive and dismount next to him. "Nobody quite like them for reliably delivering an invigorating fight. We've spilled an ocean of blood keeping them hemmed into the Sea of Chaos, and yet they never stop trying. There are parts of Cothique and Yvresse that have seen more Norscan invaders than Druchii over the years." "Ready to add another gallon to that ocean?" you ask. "Always, and then much more if that doesn't get the point across." He smiles in anticipation as he runs his eyes over the crowd. "Which unfortunate will taste my blade today?" You nod towards Vindslaktare, who's gazing thoughtfully back at the two of you. "That's their Chieftain, but he might not be the Champion they put forward." Asarnil's grin widens. "I hope it's him. Old men in a profession where men usually die young are always the most interesting." The Nordlander joins the two of you as you walk across the island to the Chieftain, whose eyes are locked on Asarnil and who barks a question as you approach. "He wants to know if Asarnil is a Ljósálfar or a Dökkálfar," the Nordlander translates. "Er, he means-" "Oh, I know what he means," Asarnil interrupts, his smile growing strained. "Tell him that I am a Fjallvættr of Álfheimr, and that at the slightest provocation I might decide it is my duty to wear the guise of Víðarr on behalf of the Dvergr." "I got most of that from context, but who's Víðarr?" you ask as the Nordlander translates. "Drakira," he says distractedly, watching the expression of the Chieftain as he listens to the threat, and to the Chieftain's response. "He says it would be ungracious for him to take the glory of what promises to be a battle for the sagas," the Nordlander says, and Asarnil sighs in disappointment. "He grants the honour to his nephew Völundr Jólling." The crowd turns almost as one, and you follow their eyes to a bear of a man as muscled as he is fat, his beard adorned with steel rings and with a short-hafted hammer on his belt. Völundr steps forward, smacking a meaty fist against his chest and bellowing a challenge, one word of which you wince at. "He says he'll earn the favour of the Blood God with the skull of a Ljósálfar," the Nordlander says. "I suppose the natural response would be to dedicate the kill to Khaine," Asarnil says with artful casualness, "but we Caledorians have our differences with the Bloody-Handed God." He draws his blade, which would seem precariously thin if you didn't know it was made of Ithilmar, and examines the tip of it. "Instead, I shall dedicate this victory to Vaul." --- There's a short delay as Völundr's armour is fetched from his smithy, which gives an opportunity for more of the Winter Wolves to arrive, trailing behind the pace set by you and Deathfang. You don't think the Norscans will go against a duel they believe to be adjudicated by the Gods, but you'd rather have the forces on hand to press the matter if you turn out to be wrong. The wait isn't as uncomfortable as it could have been as the fjord shields the ice here from the bitter northern wind, but you're still suppressing a shiver here and there by the time Asarnil and Völundr stand alone in the middle of the island. [Asarnil vs Völundr, round 1: 26 vs 29.] The clash of Norscan steel against Caledorian Ithilmar begins immediately, with Asarnil parrying the first swing of the Norscan to obliterate the patch of ground he had been standing on a moment before, which causes you to raise your eyebrows and concentrate your Magesight as you realize there's more to the hammer than steel or more to Völundr than baseline human muscle. But at this distance you can't make out any flash of energies from the hammer amongst the eddying ambient Winds, so you give up and return your focus entirely to your mundane senses as the two warriors dance around each other, seemingly evenly matched. Seemingly. "I thought the Old World's dearest mercenary would have a bit more flash to him," Sir Ruprecht says beside you, and you remember that his attention was elsewhere when Asarnil went blade-to-claw with a higher Daemon of the Tempter and came away unscathed. "What do you know of Vaul?" you ask as you watch. "Vaul?" he says distractedy. "Vaul. You mean Vallich? Nordlander God of Shipwrights? Not much, really." "They do get around a bit, don't they? I must admit, I don't know a whole lot about Elven Gods. What I do know is that Vaul is the God of Smiths and the patron God of Caledor. And most notably..." [Asarnil vs Völundr, round 2: 97 vs 7.] You wince as Asarnil's blade flicks out twice, faster than the eye can see, and a scream of pain rises from the Norscan as he clutches at his face. "Most notably," you continue, "he was blinded..." Asarnil circles his foe, and you wince again as the Elf's greaved leg lashes out with a crack of shattering bone. "And crippled by Khaine," you finish, almost drowned out by the second crack. "Ah," Sir Ruprecht says as Asarnil's blade slips between Völundr's ribs to skewer his heart. "'Victory is a foregone conclusion,'" you say, echoing Asarnil's promise to any who are able to afford his prices. To be continued.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 26: Black Blood Pass

Spoiler: Unfinished business [*] [BARBITUS] Interrogation [*] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [*] Attempt to find the Norse Dwarf outpost of Kraka Ravnvake -[*] With Johann Thankfully, the Norscans leaving enough room on the thoroughfare for mammoths meant there was enough room for steam-wagons, so you're able to slip between the buildings and through the town without damaging any of it and risking angering the locals, who seem to be accepting the Gods' judgement on the duel. You run a thoughtful eye over their mammoth as you pass, noting its clear eyes, symmetrical features, and hair as blond as the humans around it. They say that the second set of tusks and the fangs on its trunk are a mutation induced by chaos, but they say the same of Demigryphs. The mammoth seems to be inspecting you right back, possibly surprised to encounter something even larger than it trundling through town. With the town safely behind you, you turn your attention to other matters: performing the interrogation of young Journeyman Barbitus. This far into the journey, there are plenty of empty rooms that were once filled with peat-coal or provisions. You select the least odorous of them, set it up appropriately, and have Egrimm direct the potentially wayward Journeyman your way. "You wanted to speak to me, Lady Magister?" he says cautiously as he pushes the door open warily. Your dramatic side wanted gloom for him to peer into, but for the sake of his nerves there's a lantern on the floor between the two chairs. "Take a seat, Journeyman Barbitus," you reply, gesturing to the chair opposite yours. There's a moment of hesitation before he obeys, glancing around the room and then jumping as the door swings shut behind him. That was another thing your dramatic side wanted, but credit here goes to the design of the doors which makes them swing shut unless actively held open. "I wanted to check how you've been doing, after all we've encountered." "I'm fine, Lady Magister," he says instantly. "I'd hope not," you respond. "There's no good reasons and plenty of bad ones for somebody to be serene after their first encounter with something like a physical manifestation of the Ruinous Powers. While I was growing my calluses in Stirland, I lost my lunch the first time I encountered a man twisted by Dhar. So please, answer honestly." "Is this an interrogation, Lady Magister?" he says after some thought, and to his credit he quells the surging of Hysh he had started to unconsciously draw upon. "No, what could be waiting for you back in the Empire is an interrogation. This is your chance to avoid that. Magister Egrimm feels you have promise, and the Empire always needs more Magisters, so I'm willing to be convinced." He considers that for a moment. "You've got visual Windsight, haven't you?" "Mostly. Some secondary olfactory synaesthesia with Dhar and Waaagh energies. And you have visceral?" He nods. "Visual is easy, there's names for every colour imaginable. With auditory, you can map directly onto musical notes. All five main senses have an entire lexicon for communicating. But visceral? Most people only know hunger, satiation, pain, nausea, and the call of nature. Even most Wizards assume it works like emotive or intuitive when they hear about visceral Windsight. But it's not, it's an entire sense as well-developed as sight or hearing or taste and it's completely alien to normal human experience. And there's no filters either, none of the psychosomatic tricks like blinking for visual or vomiting for gustatory to block out some of it. All you can do against a bad visceral sensation is curl up in a ball and hope it passes." You nod. "And how did the servants of the Tempter manifest through that?" His eyes dart around, and you'd think it was regular evasiveness if it weren't for the blush starting to rise up his neck. "At first, in the way you'd expect," he finally says. "Then it split into entirely alien sensations and became overwhelming. It was all I could do to focus on Hysh and follow the Chant. It took days for the sensation of phantom organs to fade, and then came the Windfall, and then the Wastes." "It sounds like it must have been quite draining." He shakes his head, then stops. "Well, yes, I see what you mean and in that sense I suppose it was, but 'draining' is a sensation in itself and it wasn't that. This is what I mean, Lady Magister. Words quite literally fail me." You nod. "And I imagine there's a bevy of lessons for dealing with visual or auditory Windsight at the Light College. But for you..." He nods. "My Master recommended the diary of Supreme Patriarch Ptolos, but it was extremely redacted and from what remained I believe he had intuitive Windsight. So I'm almost entirely self-taught. That wasn't a problem once I grew accustomed to the environment of the College, but adapting to the outside world has been a challenge, even before all this." "So what brought you to this Expedition at all? Surely there's work aplenty for a Light Wizard in the Empire?" "Timpania recommended me to Magister Egrimm after he said he wanted different Magesights. Each batch-induction divides up by language until everyone learns Reikspiel, so the three of us knew each other pretty well already. They say Magister Egrimm reports directly to the Magister Patriarch, so I figured the chance to work alongside him would be worth the discomfort." You nod. The Light Order takes on the most Apprentices of any order, but produces the fewest Magisters. It makes sense for someone with ambitions to rise from the Choirs to take chances to be noticed. "Do you still feel that way?" He takes a moment to consider that. "Now that it's almost over, I do. But I don't think I'd do it again any time soon." "Tell me about the Wastes." He hesitates. "I'd expected to be nauseous, or something like it. But it was more like the feeling you get in your gut when you've been awake too long. A constant weight that drags down everything you try to do. It was never much more than an annoyance, but it was always there." You nod at that, remembering the campaign in Sylvania. The dull throb of Dhar had been everywhere, and you're still not entirely sure if some of the darker thoughts you had then were entirely due to circumstances or if the constant ambient corruption had crept in. "And after we left there, things returned to normal." "Yes, Lady Magister, once we went into the mountains." And then Egrimm had taken the return to his normal appetite and sleep patterns as reason for concern. You suppose that's understandable. One advanced in the use of Hysh would be naturally resistant to that sort of low-level onslaught and might not have noticed it at all. But for a Journeyman barely used to the streets of Altdorf, let alone the Chaos Wastes... "It's to your credit that you're bouncing back from the experience. I'm sure by the time you return home this will all seem like one big adventure. It's not every Journeyman that can claim to have participated in the rescue of a Dwarfhold and the defeat of a Higher Daemon." "I suppose so." He hesitates. "So you won't... I mean, I won't, uh..." You smile. "I see no reason for concern, and I'll share that information with everyone that needs to know." He exhales and gives a shaky smile. "Thank you, Lady Magister." --- "You think it was just the influence of the Chaos Wastes?" Egrimm says doubtfully, fidgeting with a small square mirror. You nod. "It's a matter of perspective. You're Hysh-y as a lighthouse and it's not my first experience in a Dhar-rich environment, but Barbitus has the worst of both worlds: he can directly experience the Dhar and he's not immersed enough in Hysh to resist it. It fits that he'd be worn down as we go north, then start to recover as we leave the Steppes." Egrimm considers that. "I suppose he'd barely had the opportunity to recover from the Daemons when I hit him with the Windfall, and barely had time to recover from that when we entered the Wastes. He rang true to you?" "He did. There was genuine frustration in his tone when he talked about it. If he was tempted and trying to hide it he'd either brush it off or play at being disgusted with it, not annoyed." He nods thoughtfully. "That makes sense, and I'm glad to hear it. The three of them work well together, and I doubt the other two would be willing to work with me if I had to hand Barbitus over to the Magisters Vigilant." "Yes, he said they were all inducted together. Is that common for the Lights?" "Oh, yes. There's an old joke that the best way to contact a Light Wizard is to found an orphanage, there'll be one there the next morning to winnow through the urchins. The three of them were from Tilea originally, hence the names." "Is that how you came to the Light Order?" you ask curiously. He smiles. "No, I woke up one day with the realization that I needed to go to Altdorf. 'Seeing the Light', we call it. Once I made it through to the Pyramid of Light I was accepted as an Apprentice. I did my time in the Choirs and ended up on the Choir for Magister Patriarch Alric during a rather tricky exorcism. I was one of the few left standing after the smoke cleared, and the rest is history." He sighs. "A very apt choice of words when it comes to that man." "He has been around for quite some time," you prompt. "Oh, yes. He doesn't like his age being talked about, but he can't hide the facts. Let none forget he was Supreme Patriarch during the Night of a Thousand Arcane Duels, and that means he must have won the position in 2406, so he must have been at least a Lord Magister. I doubt he's any younger than 120. No wonder he needs to hand the reins off every so often." "To Lady Magister Mira?" "The one and only. Devastating woman. From what I've heard she never even made it out of Altdorf as a Journeywoman - was about to set off when the city was besieged by Tomb Kings after some trinket or another, and by the time they were rebuffed she'd made enough of a name for herself on the walls that they promoted her to Magister. Pity she keeps handing back power, she's much better suited to it." He sighs. "What about yours? Magister Patriarch Olorin, isn't it? I've never heard much about them, which I suppose is only natural." "Olorin retired back when I was an Apprentice. Algard is the current Magister Patriarch." He frowns. "Algard, of the Storm-Towers? I'd assumed he was dead." You resist the urge to smile. "No, called away from his collections for a higher purpose. Hopefully his Towers remain hidden away until he can return to them." "I tried to chase down rumours of one during my Journeying, but when I got there, an Outrider patrol was riding down a group of cultists and the storm moved on and the Tower disappeared before I could circle around the battlefield. They're a magnet for trouble." You have to bite your lip. "It sounds like it. Algard seems well-suited to his current position, so they'll have to fend for themselves at least a while longer." "Mmm." He spins the mirror on its corner. "What do you think, did the Expedition succeed?" You exhale. "The goal was to ascertain the status of Karag Dum. Personally, I have many more questions, but this wasn't my Expedition. It was Borek's, and it's Karak Kadrin's, and it's the Karaz Ankor's. Borek's apparently got his answers, and to the Dwarven perspective, we've uncovered enough information that they can write it off with a clean conscience. So, yes. We cauterized that wound in the Dwarven psyche. That's a success even before you factor anything else in." "That's an odd choice of words. Are you worried about the Dwarven psyche?" "It's twenty-five centuries since their dark age, and their population is still going down. Why do you think that is?" He frowns. "Well, they're always fighting one war or another." "So are we. So are Kislev and Bretonnia and everyone else. That's just the world we live in. They haven't changed biologically since their Golden Age, and yet their oldest and richest Holds are shrivelling, even during times of peace, even though those Holds were built and populated when Daemons walked the world freely. So yes, I think it's the Dwarven psyche. I think that the average Dwarf woman does her duty in bringing four children into the world, and then chooses not to inflict it on a fifth." "Four? But-" You wave a hand. "Three quarters of Dwarven births are male." "Ah. I suppose that explains why I mostly ever see ones with beards." He spins the mirror as he considers your words. "Is that why you do what you do? Hoping to single-handedly heal the Dwarven soul?" You shrug. "If it happens I'll take it, but I joined Belegar because Abelhelm died and I didn't know what else to do with myself, and I found Vlag because I was lucky enough to be in the right place at the right time with the right talents. I can't grab the entire Dwarven race by the beards and shake them until they stop looking backward and start looking forward. But I like them, so I'll do what I can to make the world a better place for them." "There's a line for their history books. 'The Mathilde Age: She liked us, so she made the world a better place for us'." You roll your eyes at his teasing, but can't help smiling. "Why do you like them? Dwarves aren't exactly fans of magic." "They don't like magic because they know magic is often dangerous and unreliable, and they physically react badly to it. I can respect that. That's probably what it comes down to: what I disagree with them about, I can usually still understand and respect. Not like how it is in the Empire, where every other person is a twit with a fistful of virulently-held beliefs they've never given any thought to." He smiles. "I thought the Greys were supposed to cleave closely to the Articles." "Even we didn't lay down our staffs and let ourselves be burned after Alric let the Night happen. Being a bigoted fool is not part of the 'ideals and laws of Sigmar's Holy Empire', even if it seems like that sometimes." "Hear, hear," he says, his smile widening. --- As the Expedition travels along the banks of what you can't help but refer to as Lake Sausage, you and Johann circle around it in the other direction, making your way across the river and through a forest to seek out the lake's main tributary, which is easier said than done and involves some going back and forth and arguing about whether one river seems wider or deeper or faster than another. Eventually you settle on what you hope is the correct candidate and then following its long, winding path uphill as it flows through the mountains. Your Shadowsteed is as tireless as Johann's golden lungs and muscles, but neither magic grants proof against boredom and you can't find refuge in a book without risking missing your goal and rendering the entire purpose of this journey pointless. What feels like a lifetime later, you're thoroughly sick of the sight of mountains and Johann is frowning at the river. "The Norse Dwarves were sailors, weren't they?" "That's what I've heard, they'd build their holds along rivers and then travel up and down them. Why?" "Because I think we've gone too far." You frown and consider the river alongside him, which definitely seems like it's grown too shallow to be navigable. "Damn." Several more hours later, the setting sun forces you to find shelter for the night behind a network of Magic Alarm tripwires and several piles of pebbles under the effects of Eye of the Beholder to lead any wandering Norscans into thinking they've found river-gold to lead them into said tripwires. You glare at the patch of sky where the sun was last sighted, grumble under your breath about how unreliable it is, and then have to mentally concede that as you are quite far north and it is summer, the sun is sticking around for much more of the day than you're used to. Just not long enough. The next morning sees you resuming your search, and you eventually find what you're looking for on the other side of a narrow crevasse that can't be seen all the way through no matter which way you look at it: a small hidden valley that looks like it was quite beautiful once. Now all that remains is charred stone foundations and Runestones so thoroughly defaced you're just guessing about the Rune part. You make your way through the rubble, frowning at the Norscan graffiti covering everything still standing, some of it sigils in honour of the Chaos Gods, some of it what looks like the same sort of thing you'd find on the walls of Altdorf, just in a different language. "Metal fragments," Johann says, kneeling down to inspect something. "Looks like a weapon was shattered, but they took away the largest pieces." "What kind of metal?" "Iron. Bad iron. Coldshear by the feel of it." "It doesn't bode well if the Norscans were comfortable enough here to cover it with graffiti and take away all but the crumbs." You turn your gaze to the entrance. "Shall we?" "I'm not going to turn back after coming all this way." Lit by a Glowing Light, the two of you venture into the mouth of the Dwarfhold of Kraka Ravnvake, frowning at the walls as you do. The interior lacks the graffiti of the outside, but bloodstains cover much of the floor and the walls are marked with chips and divots from errant swings and shots. It doesn't take you long before you reach the cave-in you were told about, and Johann kneels down to concentrate. "There's... a hammer or an axe, about fifteen yards in," he says. "High-quality steel, but badly battered, and completely covered by stone." You run your eyes over the cave-in. "Fifteen yards? There's no way we're getting through that much stone." You frown as you consider it some more. "For a good weapon to be under there, chances are its wielder is too." "So they're not just hiding behind the rockfalls and hoping any intruders wander off of their own accord," Johann says grimly. "They would have recovered the body and taken the weapon while they were doing so." "It tells us this was made to collapse, rather than it being disrepair. Otherwise either Dwarves or Norscans would have taken the weapon before it got buried by the stone. It matches what I've heard about the defence of Kraka Drak: falling back and caving in the Hold as they go." "Dwarves destroying their own Holds," Johann says, shaking his head. "They must have known it was the end, so all that mattered was taking as many Norscans with them as possible." "Not just Norscans," you say, looking around the tunnel. "Kurgan, Hung, Tong, and probably other Tribes we don't even know the names for. And mutants and Daemons and champions of the Chaos Gods. Asavar Kul gathered his forces from the entire Chaos Wastes, and after he died they all came up here. They probably would have fallen to infighting before long, but they had a common enemy and the surviving lieutenants of Asavar Kul to unite them." "So when Magnus saved Kislev, he doomed the Norse Dwarves," Johann says, rising back to his feet. "Seems so. Let's check the side-passages. I don't think we'll find anything different, but we may as well while we're here. The two of you map out the accessible portions of Kraka Ravnvake, and you ultimately find that every one terminates in a wall of rubble. Both of you strain your Windsight to try to glean any suggestion that there might be life on the other side or the rockfall might be thin enough to dig your way through, but all you find is evidence that at some point in the past, others have tried and had eventually given up. From the traces of metal left behind in pick-marks Johann deduces that there were at least two groups that tried to make their way through, one with middling-quality iron and another with high-quality steel, which you assume to be Norscans and southern Dwarves respectively. A closer examination of the main shaft reveals a cavernous expanse of missing roof partway in, indicating a cave-in that had been excavated at some point in the past. A great deal of work to find nothing but more blockages on the far side. "After Vlag, I was half expecting to find them alive and well," Johann admits as the two of you emerge into the sun. "Part of me was hoping too," you say, "but I suppose it makes sense. This is a mystery the Dwarves are entirely capable of solving themselves, and it seems like in this case they have. The Norse Dwarves have fallen - or at the very least, Kraka Ravnvake has." "They could still be alive, deep underground," Johann says half-heartedly. "Runelights and cavern farms and underground springs and geothermal heat." "Maybe, but if they are, it makes no difference up here. If they're burrowed that deep they may as well be on Mannsleib." "It's nice to imagine, though," he says wistfully. "Or at least nicer than the alternative." "I suppose it is," you say, dusting off your hands. "Let's head back." --- As the walls of Fort Straghov come into view, you exhale and feel yourself relax a bit. You are now officially in Kislev. Northern Kislev, populated largely by Ungols who never fully assimilated into Kislev and are still prone to banditry and worshipping the wrong kind of Gods on occasion, but Kislev nonetheless. The Expedition has finally returned to friendly territory. The next week will take you south along the River Tobol, passing Fort Kaminski and eventually arriving at Fort Ostrosk, where you will cross the river and be ready to begin the final stretch overland to where the Expedition began months ago. The four with the most votes will be chosen. Spend time getting to know... [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Be ready to use Rite of Way should it prove necessary [ ] Attempt to scout the Skaven stronghold of Hell Pit [ ] Attempt to steal the mammoth from the Baersonlings - With Esbern and Seija - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Before anyone asks, I will not reveal if the state of Kraka Ravnvake was the result of dicerolls or was a foregone conclusion.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 27: The Tobol

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Asarnil the Dragonlord [*] Ice Crone Ljiljana [*] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [*] Deathfang Fort Straghov would have to be extremely alarmed at the appearance of giant metal behemoths on the horizon, but if the cluster of flags of various Karaks and Colleges didn't convince them to hold their fire, the blue-on-white sword ensign marking the presence of an Ice Witch definitely did the trick. Once they see the largely Dwarven crews and Ljiljana emerges and yells at them in Kislevarin from the prow of the Magnus they're more than happy to allow you on your way. --- "Too easy," Ljiljana says scornfully as she looks back at Fort Straghov. "Should have checked papers, should have tried to search steam-wagons. Didn't even have to threaten to freeze their yaichki off. Tch, Northerners. Too barbaric for Kislev, not barbaric enough for the Chaos Gods." "How are you doing?" you ask. "You seem to have gotten your energy back." "Yha, yha, fretting from Knights was nice but got boring. Will make it home to die in the usual way. Play more rounds of games with the Tzar." She snorts and spits over the railing. "Needs to die already. Fights against threats, yha, but just keeps throne warm when there's nothing around for him to ride out and hit. Doesn't listen to Ice Witches, doesn't listen to courtiers, doesn't listen to diplomats, just listens to generals, who all grow fat and lazy. Young Boris born under good omens, respects the Gods properly, will be better Tzar." She snorts again. "Still, could be worse." You nod in understanding. Directly after Tzar Alexis who fought in the Great War Against Chaos was Tzarina Kattarin the Bloody, who reigned for a century and a half before being staked, frozen, and supplanted by her son, who proved quite adept at dodging questions about how someone who had been a Vampire for at least a century could have a living human son, and also provided the inspiration for the Tsarevich Pavel Society. After all that, a merely incompetent Tzar must be quite refreshing. "I think most everyone will be returning to politics of some stripe," you venture. "The Dwarves will have a tough time adapting to the results we've delivered, and there seems to be some Engineers Guild disagreements about the steam-wagons themselves. And there's the whole Marienburg situation, too." She frowns, thinking. "The rebel merchants who block in the Wolfships from hunting Norscans?" You conceal a smile, remembering Chamberlain von Bitternach's gambit to frame the situation that way to foreign eyes. "The very same. The Dwarves are building canals that threaten their monopoly, and the merchants don't like that." She frowns. "Have they met Dwarves? Easier to convince the sun to stop turning than to tell them to stop building. But merchants are like that, think gold in a purse means more than steel in a hand. Perhaps Erengrad will go the way of Marienburg one day, guilds richer than boyars." "Perhaps Kislevite pressure can help resolve the Marienburg situation and defang the trade families, and help keep the merchants in Kislev from growing too big for their boots." She narrows her eyes at you thoughtfully. "Perhaps," she eventually says. "Will perhaps have a word or two with my sisters. Tzar will only care if it turns into war, but the Tzar is far away. Perhaps we could involve ourselves in the matter, and in doing so build useful ties with the west." "The Magister Patriarch of my Order has taken a keen interest in the Marienburg situation, and has the ear of the Supreme Patriarch. He would be very open to reaching an agreement on the matter. And the Empress would be just as happy to build new ties with our eastern allies." "Powerful titles," she says thoughtfully, "and interesting words. I will put them in the right ears." You nod, smiling. Just a few planted seeds, but they could end up sprouting in all sorts of useful ways. --- Ever since the Urmskaladrak succumbed to the call of gravity, Asarnil and Deathfang have spent most of their time aloft rather than relaxing atop one of the steam-wagons. Part of the reason for this is practical, as part of the cargo of the Urmskaladrak was the foods that Asarnil prefers and in their absence nothing less than freshly-hunted and Dragon-roasted meat is suitable for his palate, and part of the reason is for the simple reason that the remaining steam-wagons have less deck space and what they do have is largely taken up by cannon and cows. So the only good time to approach the two of them is as the day draws to a close and the steam-wagons come to a halt, and the two of them descend with whatever beast was unfortunate enough to encounter them clutched in Deathfang's claws. "It is growing increasingly difficult to find anything but trolls and goats," Asarnil says as you approach, seamlessly switching the target of his complaining from Deathfang to you as he carefully examines the day's catch, a heavily-muscled bull. "Take this beast. A bull without horns? What sort of challenge is that? But still preferable to the rest of the creatures nearby." "A mutation?" you ask, frowning at it. "No, it's just a quirk of the local species. The first time we came to this part of Norsca, we spent quite some time searching for a 'normal' cow." Deathfang snorts, his eyes not moving from the butchering. "As long as the major organs all look wholesome, this should make for a suitable meal." "You didn't take it from nearby, did you?" Asarnil waves a hand dismissively. "I crossed into Aesling territory. If they pay any mind at all, the Baersonlings will be celebrating the theft." "Any herder should be grateful for the visit," Deathfang says grouchily. "It will be a generation before any wyvern or manticore dares to be seen above their pasture. To charge a single cow for the privilege? It is we that were robbed." "That was quite a showing against the Norscan." Asarnil shakes his head as his blade cuts through hide. "Humans have perhaps two or three decades to hone Eldrazor's art before their body begins to fail. Without magic or mutation or blessing, no human has a chance to stand against me. I would have felt pity for him had he not invoked the Blood God." "So you sacrificed him to Vaul." "Not the most conventional sacrifice," he says with a smile, "but I trust Vaul would appreciate the spiting of the Bloody-Handed God." "I've never fully understood how Ulthuan reveres Khaine," you admit carefully. "When His worship reaches our shores, it always ends poorly." "Oh? I'd have thought that Teclis' acolytes would understand quite clearly. Something in the nature of humanity makes you incapable of proper moderation, perhaps you simply do not have long enough lives to cultivate it. Just as you embrace Ulgu instead of weaving all eight Winds into Qhaysh, human worshippers embrace a single God instead of understanding the place each has in a well-rounded soul." "Don't Dragon Princes learn just Aqshy?" you ask, perhaps a little stung. "We're not trying to be Wizards," he says with a tolerant smile. "We adopt a few cantrips to help make our partners comfortable, and to protect ourselves from their flames. We save our full attention for Vaul's works, not Hoeth's, and every one of our number has skill in spears and swords, halberds and lances, whether on foot or on horseback or in partnership with a Dragon. And even then there are those that call us dangerously overspecialized because we do not also develop our skill with a longbow. So we do specialize, in our way. Just as we still revere all the Gods and recognize their place in ourselves, even if there are those we pay especial attention to." He cuts free an organ you'd guess to be a stomach and lifts it up for Deathfang's inspection, who sniffs at it and nods. "The Cytharai represent the world as it is now. The Cadai represent what we strive to make it. To embrace one while ignoring the other leads to either depravity or derangement. So we recognize Khaine just as we recognize that the world contains violence and hatred, but anyone who pays attention to only that facet of life is doomed. It is no wonder that human worship of Him goes poorly." "So when you go to war, you balance Khaine and Vaul in your thoughts?" "And Kurnous, and Eldrazor, and Addaioth. They are all facets of the whole. What do you do, without Gods to structure your thoughts around?" "She serves the Dancer," Deathfang says distractedly. "She was glowing with His energies when she and the Ice Witch returned from spreading devastation." "Ah," Asarnil says, pausing in his work and looking you over. "That fits. Perhaps that gives you some measure of stability as a counterbalance to the pull of Ulgu." An impatient snort from Deathfang has him return his attention to his work, and with a grunt he pushes a lung aside to expose the heart. "It all looks normal enough," he says after a moment of careful study. "Care for a haunch?" "Sure, thank you," you say. In truth you are getting rather tired of beef, but a meal with the Dragonlord isn't an opportunity that comes by every day. Asarnil cuts enough of the hide loose to expose the joints, then cuts the rear legs almost free with deft and practiced bladework. From there you simply have to stand back far enough to give Deathfang room to work, and he exhales what would have to be a very carefully controlled amount of flame in a slow but intense stream. The rest of the camp barely looks up, having grown used to their mealtime preparations. Once Deathfang is done, all that remains is to pull the haunches free from the carcass before Deathfang starts biting chunks out of it, and then carving still-steaming meat off it with a knife. It's certainly tender and juicy, but it doesn't quite live up to Asarnil's claim that Dragon-roasted meat is a world-class delicacy. "Many of your cities are built on what were once ours, before the..." he glances around the camp. "The disagreement with the Karaz Ankor. Much of Tilea, and Marienburg, of course, but also Altdorf and Talabheim and even Kislev City. So I suppose it is no wonder you added many of our Gods to the pantheons you brought from the east." "I have heard of some worshipping Kurnous in Talabecland," you concede. "Yes, I suppose you would have," he says in an amused tone. "Are you suggesting that Taal and Kurnous are the same?" you ask directly. Cryptic asides are a lot more fun when you're the one making them. Asarnil smiles archly. "Are you going to suggest that he isn't? That there's two horned Gods of the hunt, two Kings of the wilderness, two husbands to the Goddess of fertility and bounty?" "Rhya isn't Isha," Deathfang interrupts around a mouthful of beef. "What?" Asarnil says, taken aback. "Rhya isn't Isha," Deathfang repeats. "Draugnir joined with your Gods, but Radixashen joined with Rhya. I know not of Kurnous and Taal, but Rhya and Isha are two different beings." There's quiet as you and Asarnil digest that. "I don't suppose you're going to go any further into that?" Asarnil asks, and Deathfang just grins and takes another bite of cow, and you conceal your smile similarly. "Thought not. Though I don't know if that has any significance. Gods tend to have complicated relationships." You remember your own thoughts about the relationship between Ranald and Shallya, and refrain from commenting. Asarnil sighs. "I never thought I'd get much use out of ancient history when learning it as a child, and here I am living amongst its ruins and trying my best to remember the Tars and Tors and Kors." "If it helps, I think Altdorf was a Kor. I've heard that the Celestial College's towers are a recreation of an Elven tower that used to stand on that location." He shakes his head. "No, I'm almost certain the Kor was in Laurelorn." You let him dwell on that a while as the three of you eat in silence. "Any idea what you'll do after we return to civilization?" He shrugs. "I'll stop in at Marienburg to pick up some replacement travelling equipment, then keep going west. Do a circuit through Bretonnia, and then down to Estalia and back through Tilea. There's always something interesting or profitable going on somewhere in the Old World." "Not going to let them court you again?" "The Marienburgers? No. The more I think about that business, the uglier it seems. It's either going to go nowhere and leave the two of us extremely bored and underpaid, or it's going to get very ugly, and Marienburg is about as bad at gratitude as the Dwarves are at forgiveness, and your Empire is no slouch in the grudge department either. So I'd much rather go on a good straightforward monster-hunt, or browbeat one city-state or another and be paid extremely well for it." "What is it you do with your payment?" you can't help but ask. "Even the best of food and drink couldn't eat through the amounts you charge." "Do?" he repeats, confused. "Treasure is not for doing, treasure is for having." Deathfang nods firmly in agreement. --- "Bloody Marienburg," Egrimm says as you bring the topic up with him. "A thousand curses on Dieter IV and all his kin." "Does the Light Order have a position on the matter?" you ask carefully. "Officially, no. You'd think the place would be a breeding ground for apostasy and abomination, but the Star Chamber and Baron Henryk's pick up the slack left by the secular authorities, and as long as that's the case we consider the conflict outside our jurisdiction. Unofficially, the Great Library being all but closed to us gives us a quite large axe to grind, and if the Emperor decides that it's time for the city to return to the fold, he'll find us more than willing to do our duty." "That's a rather prosaic take," you say. He shrugs. "We are the Order of Light. Our Wind is the Wind of wisdom and truth. To deny us our books is like denying soil to the Jades." "I'd wondered about that, actually. If it's the Wind of truth, can you-" "-use it to identify objective truth?" he finishes, and you nod. "No, sadly. It was the first large-scale experiment the Order of Light ever performed. It's attracted to any moment of revelation, no matter how flawed or factually incorrect it may be. Pity, if it could be used in that way we'd put the Celestials to shame." He snorts. "Then again, if it did pick a winner out of the mess of conflicting philosophy schools and mystery cults we were in the early years, we might have torn ourselves apart. Our slow descent into secularity might have been the only way forward." "How can you be secular if you're dedicated to the Wind of holy radiance?" "Now there's a question for the philosophers." He shrugs. "Best I can offer is that perhaps the Gods use Hysh too." "So you're not a man of faith?" He shakes his head. "I searched when I was young. We all do, it's as much of being an Apprentice as the choirs are, and the library is bulging with works on philosophy and religion. But I never really found anything that fit. I've heard that the worship of Sigmar was once the most common amongst our Order, but ever since the Night of a Thousand Arcane Duels, relations between the Order of Light and the Cult of Sigmar have been rather strained. Mira might be able to fix that once Alric's out of the picture, but for now the closest we have to a majority is Shallyans. We work with them relatively often, for exorcisms and for the pursuit and purging of Daemons of the Fly Lord." He shakes his head again. "They do good work, but most are too dedicated to mopping up the aftermath to do anything about the actual causes of problems. What about yourself?" You shrug as you formulate a scrupulously honest response. "I'm not a part of any formal Cult, but any that work in the shadows will at least cross their fingers, even if they lie about it afterwards." He nods. "I've put a prayer or two in that direction myself. Only a fool would completely scorn Him." You consider the matter further. "To be honest, I'm not entirely convinced the Cults have the right of it, or at least not the entire picture. The Dwarves talk of their Ancestor Gods as beings that walked the world, and their history books agree. The Elves speak of the Gods as though they were abstract concepts in one breath and then speak of their deeds in the next. The Dragons speak of their own ancestors dealing with the Gods as equals. I'm not sure if we're all talking about different beings, or if we're all talking about the same thing from different perspectives and there's a larger picture we're not putting together." He looks at you oddly. "Is this a Grey Wizard thing? You just seek out the biggest question you can and bang yourself against it like a moth against a lantern so you have a constant source of confusion at hand?" You open your mouth to respond, then consider it. "That would explain a few things, honestly," you admit. Like how some of the most potent Ulgu spells operate through directly manipulating time or space. He smiles, seemingly amused. "Ever been to the Imperial Museum?" You frown. "The Magnus Museum? Or the ruined one?" "Neither, the one at the Collegium Historica at the University." You frown in thought. "I don't think so. Why?" "There's an old runestone there, the Obernarn Stone, along with a translation. It speaks of some of the Gods and their acts as though they were a band of adventurers. I don't think it will give you an answer, but it might give you more interesting questions." You nod, making a mental note. "I'll have to pay it a visit. More interesting questions might be the best I can hope for, at least for now. The Gods seem to cling tightly to their secrets." He smiles. "Yes, they do." --- After passing Fort Kaminski and Fort Ostrosk, both of which proved just as willing to let the convoy continue on its way as Fort Straghoy was, the convoy has crossed the Tobol and is entering the final overland stretch to Praag, where it will circle around the Golinyi Hills and leave deep furrows in the Ungol-dominated steppes. Renewed energy has filled the convoy with just a single week remaining until the Expedition comes to an official end, and everyone goes their separate ways once more. It's been quite an adventure and you're extremely relieved to be returning with all the Wizards you left with. The four with the most votes will be chosen. This is the last week of the Expedition. Spend time getting to know... [ ] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [ ] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [ ] Sir Ruprecht Wulfhart the Younger [ ] Asarnil the Dragonlord [ ] Deathfang [ ] Ice Crone Ljiljana [ ] Magister Egrimm van Horstmann [ ] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [ ] Magister Michel Solmann [ ] Journeyman Cyrston von Danling [ ] Journeywoman Alexandra Kohler Become involved with: [ ] Ranging far ahead of the convoy - With the Knights of Taal's Fury [ ] Scouting near the convoy - With the Winter Wolves Other: [ ] Be ready to use Rite of Way should it prove necessary - There will be a one hour moratorium. - The Asarnil and Deathfang portion of the update was originally posted here. - Fun fact: Altdorf canonically has at least three museums that could be described as 'the Imperial Museum', though one was destroyed during a harsh lesson on why Nehekharan mummies are a poor choice for museum exhibits. - The Obernarn Stone is canon, and if you're curious about it Google can provide the text. - I'm pretty sure I can think of something for them if you just want to read more about hanging out with them, but if you want to keep spending time with Asarnil/Deathfang/Egrimm/Ljiljana because you're imagining there's something juicy if you 'max out' the relationship, that's not actually the case.

The Karag Dum Expedition, Part 28: The Golinyi

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Citharus, Barbitus, and Timpania [*] Head Ranger Snorri Farstrider [*] Preceptor Joerg von Zavstra [*] Deathfang You once more find Snorri engaged with his collection of maps, many of which inherited from Gotrek and Borek, but this time he's not studying a future route, he's detailing the past path of the Expedition with the help of a pantograph and a reading stone. "Preparing your memoirs?" you ask lightly. "I wish," he grumbles. "Only need to write a memoir once, I'm going to have to tell this tale over and over. Karak Kadrin, Zhufbar, Karaz-a-Karak... just make sure you make it back safely or I'll need to tell it to Karak Eight Peaks too." "So what's the take-away?" "Speed, surprise, and a show of force," he says immediately. "The original plans were hoping that speed alone would work, but our actual speed turned out slower than what Kurgan could have managed. But the surprise of the steam-wagons, being something that nobody here has encountered anything like before, and the show of force of the carried warriors gave us enough time to be gone before anyone decided to attack. I'm certain that the steam-wagons alone would have been attacked at least by the Iron Wolves if they had a chance to observe them and convince themselves they had a chance, but the Knights kept them off-balance long enough for us to leave their territory." "You said similar back at Karag Dum," you said with a nod. "That they'd be ready for us if we returned the same way. So you think that the same force would run into more problems a second time?" "Even apart from the bloody ascent, aye. Word would have spread around the steppes, reports would have been sent to Zharr-Naggrund. If not by now, then at least by next spring, every force east of Karak Vlag would have heard about steam-wagons and will have decided on the best way to assault them if they ever have the chance. I don't think our relative success here can be replicated." He frowns. "At least not here, anyway." He leafs through the maps. "The Badlands, maybe?" you say, guessing his train of thought. He shakes his head. "The Dragonback greenskins have put almost as many ships into the water as Sartosa, they'd be familiar enough with our monitors to know how much force it would take to counter." He pulls out a map of the Old World and lays it atop the pile. "Kislev, the Empire, Bretonnia, Estalia, Tilea - the only places you'd need significant force just to get through are places you couldn't get a steam-wagon into. Forest of Shadows, Athel Loren, Massif Orcal, the Zombie Swamps, places like that. The Border Princes are full of rivers and they've all got major Holds at one end or both, so Barak Varr could reach anywhere trivially using their current navies. The Marshes of Madness, no. The deserts of Nehekhara, certainly not... If Karak Azul was still cut off I'd recommend it for the next expedition to there from Karaz-a-Karak, but that's no longer a problem..." He taps the Badlands. "The southern Dark Lands. If there's a possible repeat to be had, it will be there." You frown down at the map, where only the major features of the area in question are included - the Expedition didn't bring maps of areas half a continent away from where you'd be operating, unfortunately. "The Desolation of Azgorh, the Wolf Lands, the Plain of Bones... Scouts from the Tower of Gorgoth would probably pick it up, but it would have the same problem Uzkulak had - the Chaos Dwarf Navy operates out of Zharr-Naggrund so the necessary expertise wouldn't be at hand... what about Crookback Mountain? Skaven, isn't it?" "One of the Warlord Clans. Avoiding it would be as simple as not using Mad Dog Pass. And Mount Grey Hag is Night Goblins, they wouldn't be a problem." "But not any further east," you note. "Black Fortress and Daemon's Stump along the River Ruin, they'd have the know-how and probably the firepower to handle small vessels." "And I wouldn't want to try to tackle the river itself, it'd eat through anything you try to caulk the steam-wagons with. And the Ogre Kingdoms have taken to buying cannon from the Chaos Dwarves. So you could get anywhere within the Dark Lands themselves, but you couldn't get into the Mountains of Mourn or to Ind or Cathay." "I can't think of anything that would be worth the effort or the expense," you conclude after a moment of thought. "Not if you couldn't get further east than River Ruin." "Me neither," he says with a shrug, "so the steam-wagons are most likely bound to be converted into proper River Monitors when they get back to Karak Kadrin. Ancestors know we need all of those we can get, every shipyard and slipway in the Karaz Ankor has been at capacity ever since they broke ground on the canal project. Doubly so, now that Karak Vlag will need reconnecting." He leafs through the maps once more until he finds one of Kislev. "Here's the Talabec... which of these tributaries is the Brunwasser?" you ask, comparing the map to your own mental one of the Empire. "Here," he says, pointing, "and the Urskoy splits off the Talabec here, at Zavstra." "So you could easily get from Karak Kadrin to..." you trace the rivers north. "Vdovya, it looks like." "It would be just as easy to dock at Kislev and take the road north," he says. "Or you could go up the Lynsk from the Sea of Claws. That's easier said than done, especially with the Marienburg troubles, but that would get you as far as Praag." "So the only real trouble is the leg from Praag to Karak Vlag." "The Dukhlys Forest is swarming with Forest Goblins, but traders keep the road cleared and me and the Redbeards will see to the rest. They'll be isolated, but not much more so than Karak Kadrin has been, and Kislev will be glad to have them back." You smile. "I'm glad. Karak Vlag makes the whole Expedition worthwhile." He nods firmly. "That it does." --- With the biting cold of the Frozen Sea behind you, the relative warmth of northern Kislev means that the decks of the steam-wagons have become more popular, and you find the trio of Light Wizards lounging atop the Volans, idly chattering in Tilean while passing a few freshly-written pages back and forth for editing and corrections. "Good morning, Lady Magister," Timpania says as you approach, wiping ink-stained fingers on a robe that indicates it's far from the first time, and you feel a pang of sympathy for them for being obligated by their Order to always wear white. "Journeywoman, Journeymen," you reply. "Getting your notes in order?" "We'll be travelling with the steam-wagons until Kislev City, and then back to Altdorf by river," Barbitus says distractedly as he writes, "and Magister van Horstmann wants to get at least the first drafts written before we get back to the College in case he gets sent somewhere else." "Hopefully somewhere that needs a three-Wizard choir with proven Battle Magic capabilities," Citharus says with a grin. "And if not?" you ask curiously. "We'll have a better idea of the opportunities in Altdorf," Timpania says. "Maybe Sylvania, I've been hearing there's a siege there that's about to get interesting." "The Lahmians Mihnea and Ioana," you say, after a few moments to rack your memory. "The Elector Countess wouldn't turn away more hands if you decide to turn your attention there. But the Sylvania Decree is still in force, so you might be overshadowed by the Battle Wizards if you head there." "Told you," Barbitus says. "I thought it was just for the war," Timpania says. You shrug. "A lot of them have gone home now that the campaign's at a low burn, but the wording of the Decree has it in effect until there's no more Vampires anywhere in the Empire. When it comes time to take the towns proper, the Battle Wizards will be there." Citharus sighs in disappointment. "Maybe Drachenfels, then, or Marienburg. Or some new hotspot. There's always something." He looks over at you. "What about Karak Eight Peaks, Lady Magister? Any adventures that way?" You shake your head. "Not in recent years. There's still enemy strongholds nearby, Iron Rock and Thunder Mountain and Black Crag and the like, but that would be rather overambitious." You give it some thought. "If nothing else is stirring there might be work in southern Stirland, where the Dwarves are building the canal. The Black Water is full of nasties that might be stirred up by the construction, Karak Varn is uncomfortably close, and there's still survivors from the Ghoul Woods in the area. You should be able to pick up some straightforward bounties. Or you could come back out here. Karak Vlag is going to need to rebuild its ties with the greater world, and the Dukhlys Forest is home to a fair number of Forest Goblins, and I'm sure Snorri would be happy to have you helping out the Redbeards." "Wouldn't mind working with Dwarves again," Barbitus says thoughtfully. "Good pay and decent food," Citharus agrees. "We'll keep those in mind." "What about yourself, Lady Magister?" Timpania asks curiously. "Back to Eight Peaks?" "At least at first. I'll give the matter some more thought while I'm on the road. Like I said, not a lot of adventures left there, which is great for the Karak but it does mean I need to get creative if I want to make myself useful." They nod in understanding at that. You take a seat with them and look over their notes, and fleshing out some of the parts they're not so sure about turns into a rambling discussion on magical theory. They three of them are fairly sharp and work together well, and you don't find many areas of magical knowledge where at least one of them doesn't have enough knowledge to make up for the other two. You can see why Egrimm would have brought them along, and find yourself hoping that he's able to retain them for whatever his next adventure is. --- With the lights of Praag glowing on the horizon, you make your way over to the Knights' section of the camp. You exchange nods with a few Knights you vaguely recognize and after asking you're pointed in the direction of their leader, who you find setting up a shrine to Taal. You're not very familiar with the King of the Wilds, not even from your upbringing, as Stirland is mostly free from the forests that blanket the Empire and thus the Cult never gained much influence south of the Stir. But impossible to miss, at least to you, is the strand of Divine energy flowing out of Joerg and taking root as the shrine is very carefully constructed. "Yes, Lady Magister?" he finally asks, as he finishes the construction and his murmured prayer. "I didn't realize you were Anointed," you say, nodding towards the shrine. "I'm not," he says simply. "A Priest may be Anointed, but I have never been Initiated into the Order of the Antler." You resist the urge to frown. "You can shape the Divine Magic of Taal, is what I mean." "Taal can act through me, as He can through any of His followers." He faces the shrine and slaps his thigh, chest, and arm, causing a faint jingling of chainmail, then turns back to you. "What is it you wish to discuss?" You consider and reject a debate about the importance of proper terminology. "A few things," you say. "Firstly, I had hoped you had some more insight to share about what we witnessed at Karag Dum." He sighs, and you fall into step beside him as he leads the two of you away from the shrine for the Knights waiting nearby to pay their respects to it. "I do know more about the Cloven Ones than most, but all that I do know insists that what we saw was impossible. Even if the Dwarves of Karag Dum had fallen to the worship of the Dark Gods, the Beastmen would not dedicate their lives to defending their home. At most they would fight against a common enemy with them, which is what Asavar Kul managed. Even some Chaos Cults have been destroyed by failed attempts to make common cause with the Beastmen." "But they were definitely Beastmen," you point out. "Yes, everything about them except their purpose there was correct." He shrugs. "Some sort of illusion that has convinced the Beastmen that Karag Dum is a Herdstone to be protected is the best guess I can make, except even that doesn't explain the presence of the Shadowgave. No, I don't think I can be any further help to you in this matter." He hesitates. "Except, I have a guess as to how they got here. Have you heard of the Beast-Paths?" You frown. "The trails in the deep woods that Warherds travel along?" "In part. And what of the Worldroots?" Your frown deepens. "I don't believe so. Unless it refers to leylines." "They might be connected to them in some way. It's a network of underground passages that once connected all the lands of the world, but in modern times many of its branches are sickened or dead, and the Beastmen burrow into the dead Worldroots like woodworms. In this way the Beast-Paths allow Beastherds to reach many parts of the world unseen and unsuspected. It may be how they have reached this place, far from the defiled woods that they usually haunt, and how their population has survived however many years of combat with the Kurgan." You resist the urge to sigh as the list of things you intend to look up when you return to civilization grows ever longer. In your defence, who would have predicted that you should have read up on Beastmen before travelling to the steppes? "Thank you. I'll investigate the possibility when I have access to the libraries of Altdorf once more. Is this a mystery of Taal or Rhya I should keep to myself?" He shakes his head. "A curiosity known to those that dedicate themselves to pursuing the Cloven Ones." "Very well. The second matter I wanted to talk about is how the Knights feel about the results of the Expedition." He smiles. "There are only two things the Knights of Taal's Fury ever feel upon returning from a campaign: either disappointed that it was less eventful than they expected, or mourning for those that were lost because it was more so. Apart from clashing with the Daemons in the mountains around High Pass, we had only minor skirmishes along the entire journey, and I will cherish the disappointment that this Expedition has left me with." You can't help but smile. The simplicity of a Knight's perspective reminds you why they exist: because there needs to be those who do not care for politics or puzzles, just that there are enemies to kill. While you are digging through bookshelves trying to figure out what Cor-Dum is doing a continent away from where he should be, the Knights will already be on their way to the next battle. "I can respect that. There was another matter, but it's something I want to ask as a person to one of Taal's faithful, rather than as a Wizard to a Knight." He looks at you curiously. "Oh?" "A close friend of mine has something of a family dispute involving worship of the Earth Mother, and whether it should be pursued as they traditionally have done, or whether they should join the Cult of Rhya. I wanted to know if you knew anything of that division." "Would this family live in Altdorf? In a round house with a very tall wall?" "It might." He considers that for a while. "A man once sought to truly understand water, and followed every river he could find to its mouth. His conclusion was that the true nature of water is salty, and he died of thirst." You consider that for a while, and nod. "Thank you." --- Deathfang is not the chattiest being you've ever encountered, but some of what little he has said has been rather intriguing, so you resolve to see if he can be convinced to let any more pearls of wisdom drop. One day while Asarnil is dozing in a hammock you're pretty sure he stole or borrowed from Ljiljana, you take the opportunity to sidle up to the Dragon and try to make conversation. Easier said than done, especially when the Dragon has had to live without pillows for almost two months now. The flat look he gives you as you approach almost has you forget the opening remark you'd decided upon, and the direct "what do you want?" has you discard it entirely. Eltharin is a very difficult language to be direct in, and having a Dragon manage it in your direction is rather alarming. "When I've spoken to Asarnil and yourself before, you've made comments that were very interesting. I was hoping you'd make some more." The look he gives you is long and flat, but eventually he snorts and scratches at his neck, where the scales punctured by the Greater Daemon have grown dull as they prepare to shed. "Very well. I will tell you a variation of a tale I have told my children." Twenty thousand years ago, though the length of a year was different then, the world was a ball of ice floating in an endless void. It had been for millennia beyond counting, and the crude and limited creatures that had come to live on the thin strip of liquid water and uncovered land at the equator had grown complacent in their eternal stalemate: the Prometheans ruled the seas, the Shartak ruled the mountains, and the Fimir ruled what was between. How they must have despaired when we graced their world, the sky turning red as the air itself tried fruitlessly to hamper our arrival. We were led by five, the greatest of our flight: Draugnir, Abraxas, Radixashen, Urmskaladrak, and Kalgalanos. They led us on the long flight through the void, and decided this ball of ice would be adequate for us to rest and grow. The Shartak were the first to encounter us as we claimed the highest peaks and the grandest caves for our own, and we drove them from the heights and slew those that resisted. The Fimir grew maddened at the Shartak invading their lowlands, and tried to unite to make war against us, and they too we shattered utterly. The Prometheans were wise beyond what their forms would suggest, and sank below the waves, only emerging to feed on the battlefields we left in our wake. The world was ours. Many years passed, and many children were born. They grew into Sun Dragons, who could breach the sky itself and warm themselves in the unobstructed radiance of their namesakes. They grew into Moon Dragons, and would stretch their wings by visiting the white moon, which at that time was the only moon of this world. And at last they grew into Star Dragons, ready to leave to find new worlds to conquer, and many flights did so. But for every Dragon that left this world, one would add their bones to the blown plain of stone that was the only place suitable to die, too far from the mountains to be found by Shartak, too far from rivers to be explored by the Fimir, and too far from the oceans to be fed upon by the Prometheans. The world was large, but so much was unusable that many Dragons grew gaunt and withered without ever growing strong enough to withstand the embrace of the void. Our leaders came together, and the plan they reached was brilliant. If only our tools had been the equal of our ambitions. We knew of other beings that plied the void, travelling in silver ships to protect themselves from the radiance we happily bask in. But though their forms were primitive, their cunning was almost sufficient, and we reached an accord with them. The worlds danced in the grip of their magics, and the sun grew larger in the sky as the ice began to melt. We spread across the entirety of the world, from the equator that we had dominated to the poles where the cunning beings made their grand machines. The continents were reshaped into five, and five cities were founded and our five leaders each joined with one. Draugnir with the city of Qt, Abraxas with the city of Iz, Radixashen with the city of Cd, Urmskaladrak with the city of Zl, and Kalgalanos with the city of Cl. Deathfang pauses, and looks over to the hammock with what almost seems like fondness. "It was Qt that created beings worthy to guard our nests and grow our food. That is almost enough to forgive them for their ultimate failure." Attracted by the jealous whispers of the Fimir and the broken despair of the Shartak, the Ruinous Powers turned their eyes to this world. After ten thousand years of their insidious scratching, they finally found an opening. The great machines begin to fail and the energies they were supposed to harness began to pour into the world, and the Ruinous Powers began to mould those energies - but the machines were more clever than they expected, as most of the energies were transformed by their passage into the world into forms that followed their own natures, rather than the orders of the Ruinous Powers. But enough remained true to them that they were able to pour their minions into the world. Daemon and Shartak and Fimir fought against Dragon and Elf and the cunning beings and their creations, and we begin to turn the transformed energies of the Ruinous Powers against them. In the end, the greatest creation of the cunning beings were those they created by accident. With the great machines sealing the world against the Ruinous Powers, the combined beliefs of their creations had accumulated and grown into an entirely new form of life. When the cunning beings finally fled, we fought alongside the Gods instead. To defeat the inrushing of energies at the poles, we and the Gods and the Elves built the Great Vortex, and magic drained back out of the world, and Daemons shattered as the world grew inimical to them. In the end, we were victorious. But Draugnir lay dead, having given all he had to create a terrible blade that had held back the Daemonic legions. Abraxas sent himself into exile. Kalgalanos was never seen again. Radixashen was corrupted and disappeared into the earth. Urmskaladrak died not at the hands of Daemons, but errant creations that he had attempted to recapture. Those who are true to who we are live beneath the land that was created for us, growing in strength and waiting for the day when even the least of our number is able to depart. But many lost themselves to these new energies that permeated the land, either in desperation during the long war or out of curiosity after it. By embracing the artificial energies that exist nowhere else but here, they doom themselves and all their descendants to die with this world. They live and die without ever knowing the true radiance of stars. One day, we will leave this world behind to be squabbled over by lesser beings and fallen Dragons. One day, this world will be swallowed by the Ruinous Powers, who will rejoice for a moment or two and then grow bored and turn their backs on it. One day a new sky will turn red as we descend upon an unsuspecting world and make it ours. And one day, we will leave that one too. Deathfang takes a deep breath, and then turns to look at you once more. "Does that satisfy your curiosity?" All you can do is nod. "Then go."

The Karag Dum Expedition, Completed

With the sun starting to peek over the horizon, you give the room that had been your quarters a final once-over for any errant notes or dropped quills. The pace of the last few weeks have been almost relaxed, but you'll be parting ways here and making your way towards Altdorf atop a Shadowsteed along with your more portable possessions. "You sure you don't want me to travel with you?" Johann asks again. "Someone needs to keep Max out of trouble," you reply lightly. "And lug an unreasonable number of books across the continent." "And that. Besides, it's not like you're missing out on an adventure, I'm just making sure Altdorf is still standing and checking my mail before heading back to the Karak." He nods. "Ride safe," he says, clapping you on the shoulder as you pass him. You stop at a few doors on your way up to exchange farewells with Michel and Cyrston and Alexandra. You didn't grow particularly close with any of them, but they pulled their weight and gave you no reason to regret their involvement, and you'd be happy to cross paths with them again in the future. They'll be continuing with the Expedition all the way back to Karak Kadrin to either collect or negotiate their payment. The trio of Lights similarly proved themselves, and you suspect if they manage to stick together and fight appropriate challenges they'll make quite a trio of Magisters in years to come. Up on deck, Egrimm is watching the rising sun and you take a moment to take in the landscape with him. Dawn is a time of significance for both your Orders, though for quite different reasons. To Ulgu it is a transition, the moment on the cusp of day and night, not fully one or the other, where shadows stretch longest and fog still clings to the ground. To Hysh it is illumination, the hidden and unknown becoming suddenly clear as a single source of pure light banishes the darkness. As the two of you stand there, strands of Ulgu creep up the side of the steam-wagon to seep into you and wisps of Hysh ride sunbeams to find purchase in Egrimm. "It's been a pleasure working alongside you," he eventually says, "and a very welcome reminder that the competent can still claw their way up the ranks." "Likewise. The journey would have been a great deal more stressful if I couldn't count on you to keep the Lights in hand," you reply, avoiding commenting on the latter part of his statement. You do hope he manages to get out from under Alric's shadow and make his own way in the world. "Any messages you'd like for me to pass on?" He shakes his head. "We'll not be too far behind you, it's only about a week to Kislev City and from there it's all downstream to Altdorf." You nod. The Lights were here at the behest of Magister Patriarch Alric, so they have no payment waiting in Karak Kadrin, just whatever reward the Light Order might see fit to grant them. "If you ever have another adventure in mind, let me know, and I'll see if I can claw my way free to join it." "I'll keep that in mind," you promise with a smile. Down below the camp is waking up, and you pass through it making your goodbyes. You exchange respectful nods with Preceptor Joerg, a hearty handshake with Ruprecht, who promises to get Hubert home safe, and a pair of warm hugs with Esbern and Seija. "You're off, then?" Snorri says, approaching as Esbern and Seija head back to their mounts. You nod. "I'd rather get going now than try to fight my way through the mess that will be tomorrow. Your Rangers going east, the Knights going west, the steam-wagons going south... it'll be a mess." "And with that horse of yours, you'll be halfway to Erengrad by then," he says with a shake of his head. It's more like two thirds, but you resist the urge to correct him. "How are you getting back to Karak Eight Peaks?" "Gyrocopter relay from Karak Norn, probably. Want me to send some messages about Karak Vlag?" "May as well, you might reach there before I do Karak Kadrin. I know my lads wouldn't know where to start trying to winkle that lot out." He exhales. "And... thank you. For Karak Vlag. If it weren't for that, it'd be very easy to think it was all for nothing." You nod and clap him on the shoulder. "Range far, range fast." "Range far, range fast," he agrees. "Safe travels, Loremaster." A day and a half to Erengrad, you mentally calculate as you summon your Shadowsteed. Call it two, better to overnight in Bolgasgrad than to try to find a suitable tavern in a village. Norden the next day, Middenheim the day after that. Two more days to Altdorf, so overnight in Delberz, they have such lovely wine. From there... well, one day to Nuln would be pushing it, so let's spend a night in Kemperbad. Finest brandy in the Empire, and you're pretty sure the EIC has an office there too. One day from Nuln to Karak Norn, then gyrocopter-hopping to get back home. You pat the insubstantial flank of the Shadowsteed below you. You owe quite a debt to whichever Wizard managed to turn the conceptual link between Ulgu and twilight into a steed that somehow taps into the speed of the line of day. Later that day, far behind you: "What do you mean, she's gone?" the Longbeard asks in disbelief. "What do you mean, the High King's here?" Snorri replies. --- A week of relaxed travel later, you make your way through Altdorf's most reputable disreputable neighbourhood and into the grounds of the Grey College, and despite actively looking for it you're still unable to spot the point where you transition from reality into the artificial plane that the College resides in. When you reach the correspondence offices you find reason to frown as you consider the familiar array of pigeonholes. They're enchanted so that the eyes of any viewer slip past any square but their own, and you find your gaze skittering across them without finding any purchase in where you remember your pigeonhole being. You'd been in the same place for almost twenty years now, ever since your promotion to Journeyman, and finding it absent was quite jarring. With nothing else for it, you approach the nearby desks of the Registrars. "Oh, Lady Magister Weber, you don't have a pigeonhole any more," says the young man you accost. "All the Lord Magisters have lockboxes. Do you want to access yours?" "Please," you reply. "Follow me" he says and bustles off, leading you on a jingling path marked by him applying a ring of keys to several extremely sturdy doors and into a small room with nothing but a table with a normal-looking chest with a slit in the lid atop it, and a chair to one side. "It would have been keyed to you by the Porter when you were promoted," he says cheerily. "Please don't open it until I'm safely out of the room, the protective measures can be a bit sensitive. Once you're done, simply close the chest and pull the door closed on the way out." "Okay, thank you." "Of course, Lady Magister." You wait until the Registrar leaves, taking the opportunity to examine the chest. You can't see any protective enchantments, but that only means it's no more enchanted than the rest of the Grey College. If it was keyed in to the same magics that allow the College to exist within the realm between reality and the Aethyr, then it could utilize that to do all sorts of things to someone snooping where they shouldn't. You shrug and lift the lid, and then frown at the mound of correspondence within. --- To the esteemed Lady Magister, I write on behalf of my master to beseech you to pay heed to this request... You grow used to variations on this theme as you make your way through easily twice as many letters as you'd ever received as a Journeywoman or Magister, and as you do your shock gives way to understanding. The Colleges have thousands of magic users and hundreds of those are Magisters, but the total number of Lord Magisters couldn't be much higher than fifty, and many of those are too busy, eccentric, or retired to work outside the Colleges. So when a new Wizard reaches the lofty status of Lord Magister, there seem to be many parties that will send them a request or invitation in the hopes of being able to take advantage of their skills or status to their own ends. You discard the invitations to various parties, balls, and gatherings, many of which already occurred while you were busy up north. Then you discard all the ones that make it clear that the writer has never heard of the Vow of Poverty or that the Grey Order is forbidden to meddle in the Empire's internal politics. Then go the ones from towns and villages whose problems barely merit the attention of a Journeyman, let alone a Lady Magister. Even after this culling there's quite a pile of offers, some troubling, some intriguing, and some both. In that you possess unrivalled insight into the problems that will face any administrator of these territories, it pleases the Grand Countess to offer the position of Markgraf of Eastern Stirland to the Lady Magister; if that is not suitable for concerns of inheritance, the titles of Count of Waldenhof, Count of Tempelhof, Baron of Mikalsdorf, and Baron of Nachthafen will be revived and granted in the coming years, and the Lady Magister is considered an ideal personage for any of the above... It has come to the attention of Grand Count Konstantin von Liebwitz that the Lady Magister Mathilde Weber has peerless expertise in certain sensitive matters that may present difficulty for Wissenland and Nuln in these coming years, that would benefit the Empire as a whole should she accept the position of Spymaster of Wissenland... Given the Lady Magister's sterling reputation amongst the Empire's allies in the Karaz Ankor, I have the honour of writing on behalf of the Chamberlain of the Seal to invite you to join the Graf's staff as Ambassador-at-Large to the many Dwarfholds that bulwark the Empire... As it has been vouchsafed that the Lady Magister's trustworthiness and suitability are beyond reproach, the Chamberlain of the Imperial House invites the Lady Magister to act as Bodyguard and Tutor to Crown Prince Mandred... Given the unique challenges presented, it is felt that the Lady Magister is eminently suited to the position of Governor-General of the New World territories and control over the entrepôt commonly known as Swamp Town... Thanks to you, our mutual friend has the opportunity to mend some important bridges in Kislev, and thinks that you'd be perfect for the job. It will let the cat out of the bag in some respects, but what better way to do that than to be named High Priest of Ranald? In recent years, piracy, sabotage, and border skirmishes in the Border Princes region has shown that Dwarven dominance over the area is required to guarantee the safe flow of trade. King Byrrnoth Grundadrakk of Barak Varr wishes to make you aware that support would be available should an Umgi of proven trustworthiness seek dominion over the territories of the western end of Mad Dog Pass, near the banks of the Howling River. He also extends the observation that the Lady Magister is of proven trustworthiness. You put down the last of the letters, reeling from the barrage. To restore your sense of normalcy, you turn to a letter you hope to be much more prosaic: an official announcement of some sort from Karaz-a-Karak. An announcement from the Emergency Meeting of the Ancestor Cult Conclave of the Karaz Ankor, hosted in Karaz-a-Karak. After certain confidential information was vouchsafed to this body by a source of undoubtable repute, a Grudge is hereby levelled against the being, spirit, force, ancestor, demiurge, and/or anthropomorphic personification commonly known as Ranald, believed to originate somewhere in or about the continent called The Old World, for the crime of theft of a disembodied Dwarven soul, which has subsequently been incarnated in the form of an Umgi. Reparation or vengeance for said Grudge is to be postponed pending the full and proper evaluation of the consequences of those actions, which may be considered to mitigate, in whole or in part, those actions. Witnessed and entered into the Great Book of Grudges by the High King. Well. Okay then. That certainly didn't help. You take a deep breath, quell the internal screaming, and begin to apply cold logic to the document. First of all, you'll operate under the assumption that it's genuine, as it will be easy to confirm the existence of the announcement in Dwarven records, so all someone counterfeiting an announcement like this would achieve is to earn a very swift death for the crime of counterfeiting the seal of the High King. Second of all, Ranald. Well, you haven't exactly kept your worship of him a secret, considering your involvement in His worship at Karag Nar and, before that, the attempt to institute his worship among the Stirland Watch. It wouldn't take much investigation to uncover that. Third, you having a Dwarven soul. You spend some time turning the idea around in your head, before ultimately discarding it as unfalsifiable. And on top of that, it doesn't ring true. Would Ranald steal a Dwarf soul to reincarnate them as human? Well, maybe. Would He do so for something they'd achieve decades down the line? No. He's not that sort of Trickster God. And the argument that He might have done so for a laugh and that person just happened to later become involved in world affairs stretches credulity. And you're pretty sure you're not actually a Dwarf. As much as you like being around them, actually being one seems incredibly stressful. So, fourth, why? Assuming the Dwarves don't have some sort of secret runic device capable of detecting the very nature of a being's soul without said being ever becoming aware of the detection, they must have been convinced by something. And you frown, and pull on the chain around your neck until the Coin emerges from your robes, where the face of the Protector glints smugly in the light. Well, you suppose that would do it. Not only did you save Karak Vlag, but also however many Dwarves survived in there had the divine revelation that you were the one that protected them, and that you did so for the noblest of motivations. You can't see the Dwarven ego being particularly good at managing the fact that a Umgi succeeded so spectacularly where the rest of the Karaz Ankor failed miserably for one hundred and eighty-five years. You examine the date on the letter - early in Nachgeheim, only three weeks after the return of Karak Vlag. The Expedition had sent Knights to ride back to Praag and arrange for word to be sent to the Dwarves, and you frown as you consider the distance. Best case scenario, Karak Kadrin would have heard about it in two weeks, and sent a Gyrocopter to Karaz-a-Karak. They send someone to confirm matters, they take however many days it would take to get past their jumpiness, then word goes back to Karaz-a-Karak, then a Conclave is summoned, then they deliberate, then they make an announcement... No. That doesn't happen in seven days or less, even if every Conclave representative dropped everything they were doing to get aboard a gyrocopter. The only way this announcement would be remotely possible is if Karaz-a-Karak had some way to know immediately that Karak Vlag had returned... like, say, a sudden inrush of energy from two Old Holds being reconnected to the Karaz Ankor waystone network. Damn and blast. For the sake of harmony you'd been hoping that the waystone network was a Golden Age relic that had been forgotten, but this could indicate that Belegar's suspicion might be correct, that the High King is actively and knowingly siphoning magical energy from the Karaz Ankor without their knowledge or consent. You sigh, and move on to the fifth consideration: repercussions. A quick mental recitation of the Articles confirms that you're in the clear with the Colleges, as even if you were a Dwarf, you were still a magic user that existed within the bounds of Sigmar's Holy Empire, and as such the Colleges were able to bestow upon you full rights to study, document, practice, and experiment with the arcane forces of magic. As for everyone else... well, in your experience Dwarves are more likely to direct pity at you than hostility over this, considering how they feel about Umgi. Humans? Well, probably better to be a Dwarf than a Wizard in the eyes of most citizens of the Empire. Elves? From your admittedly limited experience with them, you suspect they'd scoff at the idea of a Dwarf doing magic, so they'd discount it as a salve for wounded Dwarven pride. As far as you can see, this announcement doesn't seem likely change anything for the worse. Time will tell whether it changes anything for the better. You exhale and gather up the letters. You can continue mentally processing all of this on horseback as well as you could here, and there's still a lot of road ahead of you. --- The thing about being a Lady Magister, you reason a day later under the calming influence of a few fingers of Kemperbadian brandy, is that you don't have to simply take an assignment. If you show interest in something, people will be invested enough in getting your assistance that they'll answer all the questions you have without needing to actually commit to it. You don't have to make the decision based on a few sentences on parchment, you can investigate the possibilities and figure out which one takes your fancy after you're much better informed. Bolstered by this, you begin to weigh the possibilities in your mind the next day as you travel along the Upper Reik. You can't deny that things in Karak Eight Peaks have settled down considerably since you took the position of Loremaster, and recently you've been suspecting that a more traditional Loremaster would be better able to contribute to the Karak's long-term wellbeing by helping negotiate the return and immigration of Dwarf Clans, as well as smoothing over any conflicts that might arise amongst the Dwarves. Maybe your work in Karak Eight Peaks is done, maybe it's time to move on. Or maybe not. Either way, it wouldn't hurt to investigate. [-] Sinecure The first possibility, of course, is that you accept the current status quo as a reward for your hard work, rather than a deficiency to be addressed. Belegar will keep finding ways to make use of your talents, and you'll have time and resources enough for your pet projects, as well as still being on hand should something go drastically wrong and need correcting. [ ] Loremaster-at-Large of Karak Eight Peaks Or you could push Belegar to continue sending you afield. He does want to continue to enhance the stature of Karak Eight Peaks in the Karaz Ankor, and what better way to do that than for you to travel it and solve all their strangest problems? It would also mean getting to see every corner of the Dwarven world and encounter all the strangest phenomenon it would have to offer. [ ] The Waystone Project Or you could turn to the biggest possible project you could pursue. The Laurelorn Elves have voiced their desire to work with you to unravel as many secrets as possible about the network in the slightly inaccurate belief that you already have some of those secrets. This might be the only chance to pool the knowledge of the Laurelorn, the Empire, and the Karaz Ankor, and for a project that could do wonderful things. Sure, you doubt you'll be able to replicate the combined efforts of the Elves and Dwarves at their heights, but every scrap of understanding of the existing network could make all three peoples better able to protect and make use of the ancient energy streams. [ ] Markgraf of Eastern Stirland A Markgraf exists to transform troublesome land into a land of productive and obedient tax-payers, usually after said land has been conquered. Historically, it also apparently exists to create rivals to the Elector Count that appointed them, which is probably why the letter made it so clear that no inheritable position would accompany the title of Markgraf. It still remains a position of extreme power, prestige, and influence, second only to the Elector Counts themselves. And it would be quite a feather in your cap if you could one day boast to have pacified Sylvania. [ ] Count of Sylvania Or you could go even further with House Weber and turn them - well, turn you - into proper aristocracy. One slice of Sylvania would be significantly easier to pacify than its entirety, and rulership in this corner of the world seems to have worked out quite well for the former Countess of Nachthafen. [ ] Spymaster of Wissenland Grand Count Konstantin von Liebwitz of Wissenland is known to be quite touchy about his independence, so when you spread word that the Skaven were in a civil war, he lead the forces of his county against the Skaven stronghold of Under-Nuln without any outside assistance except a single Dwarven diplomat. It went rather poorly, as the Civil War had already been decided there and what he had taken for continued fighting was mere squabbling over the spoils. Reading between the lines of the offer, it seems that there may be further consequences for that failed attack, and Wissenland wants your help to avert them. [ ] Ambassador-at-Large to the Karaz Ankor An Ambassador is appointed to a single polity, whereas an Ambassador-at-Large has broader rights for many more places. In this case, for the entire Karaz Ankor. A prestigious and important position, and one that might be a stepping stone into even greater positions within the administrative infrastructure of the Empire. You may not be quite as diplomatic as other candidates might be, but you pride yourself on your understanding of Dwarves and your reputation amongst them is, to put it mildly, rather good. [ ] Bodyguard and Tutor to Prince Mandred Though the offer came through the Chamberlain of the Imperial House, this has Heidi's fingerprints all over it. You're not sure if the offer is for exactly what it says or as a cover for beings her catspaw as she plays politics, but either way it would be a position extremely close to the levers of power, and one that would let you have a huge amount of influence over the likely future Emperor. [ ] Governor-General of Swamp Town This one is an oddity. The others, you can follow the logic as to why it was offered to you, specifically. But why Swamp Town? Are things there so drastic they need a powerful Wizard to get it under control? Is something particularly magical going on there? Has it become a haven for Black Magisters? Whatever the case, if you want mysteries and adventure, there's few places like the New World for encountering both on a regular basis. [ ] Ranaldian High Priest of Kislev Another one from Heidi, this one more directly. This is a wheel you set in motion yourself, and perhaps it's suitable that you follow it through to the end, resolve the grudge between Ranald and the Gods of Kislev, and establish the worship of your oldest friend in a new land. You did leave quite a few mysteries behind in and around Kislev that you'd quite like to get to the bottom of, and it would be fun to have the undeniable right to attend future Grand Conclaves. [ ] Border Princess of the Howling River With Karak Vlag returned, the only pass through the World's Edge Mountains that is not dominated by an existing Dwarfhold is Mad Dog Pass. It seems that Barak Varr wants to change that. Many have tried to make something useful of the sprawling, anarchic lands known as the Border Princes over the years, and one of the few times it was managed was almost two thousand years ago, when Emperor Sigismund the Conquerer established the province of Lichtenberg. With Dwarven support, perhaps you can follow in his footsteps. [-] Nagarythe For delivering a Druchii that had been working with Clan Moulder to the Nagarythian Ulthuan Ambassador, you were given a token that will allow you to live and fight alongside them for ninety-nine days. There's no time limit on it except for your lifespan, all you have to do is arrive in Lothern and present the token. You did just complete quite an adventure, but perhaps that whetted your appetite enough for another. [-] Research Sabbatical You can't deny that your research projects have been piling up, and it might be nice to take some time off to concentrate on getting through those. But it would mean no immediate challenges to keep you engaged, no employer resources to draw on, and no payroll to keep the Wizards you've gotten used to working with around and focused. This vote is for which possibilities Mathilde will investigate. No commitment is being made here, the results of this vote will be the roles Mathilde looks further into, so vote for whatever ones you are interested in. Some of the possibilities are marked [-]. This signifies there's not really anything to investigate, but they're still listed here for reference purposes. You can still vote for them if you really want to and if someone votes for them by accident, it's not a problem. Don't take the results of this vote as an ironclad indication of what the thread's interested in - being curious enough to want to find out more is not the same as being interested enough to dedicate the next swathe of the quest to it. -There will be a three hour moratorium. If there's another position or project you want Mathilde to consider, feel free to suggest it. - I say again, this is not the vote for selecting Mathilde's next assignment. This is for what she's interested enough in to find out more about. - There's no set cut-off points for what will win. I'll decide based on what the final vote looks like. Simply vote for what you like the sound of and want to know more about. -The job offers were originally posted here; the announcement from Karaz-a-Karak was originally posted here. - Mathilde missed the Karak Vlag meeting with Thorgrim because I tried to write it a bunch of times and it wasn't working. Mathilde won't miss out on any accolades because of this, they've just been delayed a little. - The decision for how/whether to spend Mathilde's boons and such will be made after the next assignment is locked in.

Post-Expedition Interlude, Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results Tally 397 votes total (a new record for DL) [264] The Waystone Project [190] Bodyguard and Tutor to Prince Mandred [166] Markgraf of Eastern Stirland [157] Border Princess of the Howling River [144] Governor-General of Swamp Town [131] Loremaster-at-Large of Karak Eight Peaks [131] Spymaster of Wissenland [118] Ranaldian High Priest of Kislev [110] Ambassador-at-Large to the Karaz Ankor [49] Count of Sylvania By the time your gyrocopter takes off from the wooded plateau atop Karak Norn, you've settled on a list of opportunities you'll look into further. Notable amongst these is Barak Varr's plans for the Border Princes for the simple reason that you'll be passing through there on the way back to Karak Eight Peaks, and you'll be able to pop in for a chat on the subject while there - if not with the King himself on such short notice, then at least with someone who'll be able to answer your questions. --- As you'd expected, King Byrrnoth isn't available at zero notice, but you do end up in front of Barak Varr's Varrakatuli, which translates to something like the 'Master of Oceanic Cartography'. Every ship that plies the waves takes soundings with lead lines and triangulates its position based on the coastlines, but Dwarven ships do so with exacting precision and every measurement eventually flows back into the office of the Varrakatuli to be distilled into charts. It's said they're of such accuracy that they can be used to navigate in heavy fog by depth soundings alone. Elamina Skarrenbryn of Clan Gunnarsson spreads the map out on the table, weighing down the corners with intricately-carved stone depictions of various sea-beasts. The range of recorded depths of what seems like every foot of the Howling River is marked off in intricate detail, and in stark contrast the towns and villages of the area are pencilled lightly in so they can be removed without having to redraw the entire map. "There are seven major rivers in the Border Princes," she says, "excluding Wrecker's Run, as both banks of it are considered Tilean by most. Each of these rivers has a Dwarfhold somewhere in the headwaters." She points at the map, going west to east. "Karak Izor, Karak Hirn, Karak Gantuk, Karak Angazhar, Karaz-a-Karak, and Karak Eight Peaks via Ulrikadrin. The only exception remaining is the Howling River, as the Varfund outposts were abandoned after the Silver Road Wars, and the Clans that once guarded it moved to the Grey Mountains." "And now the security of these rivers is more important than ever," you say, nodding. "Yes, and for a few different reasons. Most prominent being Karak Eight Peaks, of course - it is growing more self-sufficient, but that simply means that instead of importing staples it's beginning to generate more traditional and more valuable commerce, and barely a year goes by without a lot of gold or silver flowing north and some new shipment of weaponry going south. Karak Azul is not buying quite as much now as it did during those first few years, but it's still an old and wealthy Hold that wishes to trade with the world now that it can. And, of course, the Canal project demands a great deal of supplies, and once it's completed the rivers will only grow busier as trade begins to flow up and down the Skull River. Despite the rapid expansion of the Slotchokri, trade will outstrip our ability to defend it for years, possibly decades to come." You run your eyes up and down the Howling River. It's a neat story, but if piracy was their only concern there were much easier solutions. Even your untrained eyes can recognize a half-dozen places a boom chain could be strung across the river. "And the Pass itself? The last pass through the World's Edge Mountains not controlled by the Karaz Ankor, isn't it?" She nods reluctantly. "With the Marienburg situation and the Canal project consuming so much attention, most have so far overlooked that the Karaz Ankor is on the brink of being able to exert complete control over all overland trade with the East." You nod thoughtfully. "But an aligned human polity on the flatlands... well, that might boost trade since you wouldn't have to worry about the locals robbing the caravans, but you've got a grander ambition. What are Barak Varr's plans for Mad Dog Pass?" She hesitates. "We plan to have plans for Mad Dog Pass." You're surprised at that - for them not to have a course planned out already must mean they're truly scrambling. "Most of our resources are tied up with the Canal project for now. But whatever those plans end up being, the current powers in the area would be a great hindrance, and a friendly power would be a great help. And most of all, we want to have someone in place to prevent some other power from realizing that Mad Dog Pass is the only still unclaimed route through the World's Edge Mountains, and moving to claim it for themselves." That makes sense. None of the Old World's major powers would be daft enough to try to seize a Dwarfhold, but Mad Dog Pass was never home to proper Dwarfholds, only outposts for them to project power between Karaz-a-Karak and Karak Eight Peaks. That makes it up for grabs - and with the Karaz Ankor's population already stretched thin by the reclamation of Karak Eight Peaks, the Dwarves aren't in a good position to make that grab. "Okay, that makes sense." You tap the map and lean closer to try to read the pencil marks. "Tell me about these princes." "There are two major enough for us to know of, operating out of the two primary population centers. To the south, a loose collection of bandits and pirates operating out of Mirstadt, and to the north, a Tilean mercenary band that has taken Zenres as their base. Since they don't seem to clash we suspect they have some sort of accord, and there's certainly an element of symbiosis - without mercenaries nobody would feel safe enough to travel through the area and the bandits would have nobody to raid, but without bandits there'd be no reason for caravans to hire the mercenaries." "Do we know what mercenary company it is?" She shrugs. "Not one of the ones we regularly work with. All we know for sure is they use spears." Since she'd already said Tilean, that doesn't narrow it down much. At least you can rule out Braganza's Besiegers. "What do you know about the terrain in the area?" "Mostly flat, growing hilly as you approach the mountains. The river itself is fresh and wholesome, though too fast for fishing on any scale. The soil is thin but there are still those that manage to coax crops out of it, and the grasses are sufficient to graze herds on if you can protect them. There's minable quantities of iron ores in the foothills, and every now and then gold flecks are found in the Howling River, though we've never managed to find the source. There's supposedly ruins of some sort in the area, but they say the same of everywhere in the region." "And greenskins?" "Bloody Spear Night Goblins in the mountains, Black Spider Forest Goblins in the Forest of Gloom to the north, Iron Claw Orcs in the plains to the south. But the lands around the Howling River seem to be too far from any of their population centers for them to be more than a nuisance." A nuisance by Dwarven standards could be considered quite threatening by others. "What support would King Byrrnoth be willing to provide to a theoretical Umgi of proven trustworthiness who might be carving a principality out of the area?" "Generous monetary and logistic support to establish it, and after that 'most favoured nation' treatment for imports and exports. King Byrrnoth does not want to be seen as directly intervening to prevent too much attention turning this way, but we can organize arrangements with suitably discreet and trustworthy mercenary companies. He is also willing to establish a treaty granting sanctuary rights to all citizens of a theoretical friendly principality." That last point comes as a surprise to you. When a Waaagh or some more esoteric threat sweeps into the Border Princes, the population flees westwards to the valleys of the Vaults, where Karak Izor grants them shelter in the valleys that surround the Dwarfhold. Barak Varr has never extended the same protection to the inhabitants of the Border Princes, possibly due to a lack of sheltered valleys to keep refugees a safe distance away from the Hold itself. Shelter being available at Barak Varr would make a lasting nation a lot more possible than if the nearest sanctuary was at Karak Izor. "That answers the questions I had. Thank you." She nods. "Of course. Fair travels, Loremaster." --- You built the foundations of the plan for the Waystone project during the gyrocopter trip, but working off half-remembered skimming is grossly insufficient. Once you're properly settled back in, including letting Belegar know you'll have a formal report ready the next morning and letting Panoramia know that you've returned intact and giving her ample opportunity to confirm that for herself, you settle into your library, mildly handicapped by Wolf's continued attempts to climb into your lap. You dig through your library for books on an eclectic range of subjects as you begin to put together a rough outline of the Waystone project, should you decide to embark upon it. This isn't something that could be covered by an interview, as the person who would be conducting the project is you, as you try to bring together the disparate scraps of knowledge possessed by man, Elf, and Dwarf. The first piece of the puzzle: the Eonir. Most Imperial accounts describe them as fae woodland spirits of which little is known for sure, but Dwarven ones go back considerably further, all the way to a research expedition sent by the Everqueen into Laurelorn during the reign of the second Phoenix King, Bel Shanaar the Explorer. In time it sprouted into the two cities of Tor Lithanel and Kor Immarmor, and at first they were simply outposts of the Kingdoms of Ulthuan. Then during the civil war when Malekith and Caledor I tore Ulthuan apart over who was the rightful third Phoenix King, the Old World colonies declared themselves Elthin-Arvan, the eleventh Kingdom of Ulthuan. After Malekith was expelled and Caledor I was slain by assassins, the newly-crowned fourth Phoenix King, Caledor II, quite firmly suppressed this attempt at independence and brought the High Council of Elthin-Arvan back under the direct control of Ulthuan, breeding quite a bit of resentment amongst the Old World Elves who chafed under the rule of an island that many of them had not seen for centuries. Then Caledor II shaved the Dwarven Ambassador and began the War of Vengeance, and the full force of the Karaz Ankor fell upon the Old World colonies. By the time Caledor II fell during the Battle of Three Towers, slain by High King Gotrek Starbreaker, the devastation of the Elthin-Arvan was almost complete. Athel Numiel was destroyed, later to be rebuilt as Pelzburg, then Dorogo, then Kislev City. Kor Vanaeth was destroyed, leaving a single standing tower that humans would build around, first as Reichsdorf, then Reikdorf, and finally Altdorf, and College rumour has it that the central tower of the Celestial College is that same tower. Athel Maraya was destroyed, though its existence is firmly rejected by the Cult of Taal who insist that their ancestors were the first to build a city within the great crater that surrounds modern Talabheim. Tor Alessi was besieged fourteen times by the Dwarves, and the final time became the final battle of the War of Vengeance, and the buildings that survived later formed the core of Castle L'Anguille in Bretonnia. Only three significant Elven population centers remained in the Old World: the port-city of Sith-Rionnasc'namishathir, the scattered settlements of Loren Faen, and Tor Lithanel of Loren Lauroi. Sith Rionnasc is easy to explain, because a river delta surrounded by swamps and supplied by sea is not the easiest nut to crack. It was later abandoned anyway after the fifth Phoenix King, Caradryel the Peacemaker, ordered all Elves to return to Ulthuan to participate in its defence against a renewed assault by Malekith and his followers. The ruins they left behind were settled by the Jutones as the capital of the Jutonsryk, and it is now known as Marienburg. The Elves of Loren Faen survived by joining with the forest itself, entering into strange pacts with the tree spirits native to the area and over time becoming known as the Asrai of Athel Loren. But Tor Lithanel survived by turning to the 'Grey Lords', the organization founded by the original research expedition and bolstered by Archmages exiled from Ulthuan for unsavoury experiments. When a Dwarven Throng destroyed Kor Immarmor and were on their way to do the same to Tor Lithanel, the leaders of the city called upon the Grey Lords, and the Throng never emerged from the forest they were marching through. As a bastion of safety in a sea of angry Dwarves it swelled with Elven refugees from across the Old World, and that immigration formed the basis for their modern society consisting of the aristocratic 'Cityborn' descendants of the pre-War settlers and the 'Forestborn' underclass that live in treetop dwellings. And presumably the Grey Lords still fit into there somewhere, enjoying the protections and privileges that their defence of Tor Lithanel bought them. What this amounts to is that the city at the heart of Laurelorn has stood for over five thousand years, and was originally founded by magical researchers. That is, to put it mildly, rather promising. Since then they've been largely isolationist, but much less violently so than the Asrai. After a rocky start with the now-extinct province of Drakwald's attempts to conquer them early in the Empire's history, they actually came to the aid of the Empire during the destruction of Drakwald by Beastmen, and then later during Mandred Skavenslayer's war against the Skaven. Over time relationships improved to the point that they actually signed a treaty allowing limited logging by Nordland in 1700. But something must have changed, and by 2168 things had soured to the extent that Laurelorn's army besieged Nordland's capital of Salzenmund until the Grand Baron of the time begged forgiveness. You're not sure if Nordland failed to learn a lesson from this, or if this emboldened Laurelorn to start reconsidering their concessions. The different books you have on the subject reach wildly different conclusions about who is to blame. The second piece of the puzzle are the Dwarves, who need no introduction. They're quite likely to be difficult as the only ones likely to have relevant information are the Runelords, who have a religious obligation to be secretive about runelore. What you're hoping is that they don't consider the Waystones as falling under their aegis, either due to the involvement of the Elves in their original creation or because their knowledge of how to create them is lost, and therefore they'd be able to be part of a joint investigation into them. You also have hopes that they might still have in storage somewhere items siezed during the War of Vengeance. Dwarves don't loot, but being very thorough about taking trophies isn't looting, nor is the seizing of reimbursements. Last, but hopefully not least, are the possible human contributions to the project. Teclis did not reveal much of the workings of the Waystones to the Colleges, but what he did reveal lays a foundation, and Teclis is not the only source of mystical secrets in the world. You know from Panoramia that the Jade Order knows more of their workings than what Teclis said, and you wouldn't be surprised if any of the others knew more than they let on, including your own. Each of them come from mystical lineages, some very ancient indeed, and though the Waystones themselves are of Elven manufacture, many are supported by Henge networks of apparently human make. Someone had to have made them, and their descendants may still exist among the Colleges or the Cults or both. And there's always the many libraries of the Old World and beyond, and the many arms you'd have to twist to get access to the most interesting. The more you think about it, the more it seems like the Waystone project is going to be less about pure research and more about getting all the extant information in one place and getting as many relevant organizations on board as possible, at least at first. There's no chance you'd be able to reverse-engineer the world-spanning masterpiece of the Elves and Dwarves at their heights from scratch - older and wiser than you have tried and failed. The same would likely apply to any given researcher from the Eonir or the Karaz Ankor. But together you might succeed where individually you would all fail. --- The next morning, you go over your many notes from the Expedition. You'd spent some of your downtime during the last leg to Praag going over what your report would be, and then that announcement from Karaz-a-Karak, or more specifically the date of said announcement, had thrown an unexpected complication in. You've got strong circumstantial evidence that Karaz-a-Karak is on some level aware of the flow of magical energy from the Karaks, which could be seen as supporting King Belegar's belief that Karaz-a-Karak is knowingly stealing that energy. Do you include that conclusion in your report to him? [ ] Yes [ ] No - There will be a one hour moratorium. - The remainder of the explored options will come over the next few updates. I've not yet decided exactly where the cut-off will end up being - I'll do at least the top five, and might extend that to top seven. - More detailed reunitings will be available in coming updates. - A lot of the Eonir lore here does come from WFRP 4e, but not all of it will be exactly as it appears there, and that doesn't mean that everything from 4e is quest canon. Looking at you, Sudenland.

Post-Expedition Interlude, Part 2 - Choosing a Future

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Yes As he was in the Karag anyway today for a meeting with Francesco Caravello, King Belegar comes to you for the post-Expedition debrief, and you set your sitting room up with the appropriate maps and with a few other reference materials that would cover tangents the discussion might head in. With a nod from him the Hammerers accept your offer of a fresh keg for them to split out on the balcony, so you and the King can talk in private of some rather sensitive topics. From the notes you had sent over to him yesterday and the circulation of gossip between the Dwarven Holds, he knows the broad strokes of what's happened, it's only the details that he needs to be brought up to date on. "First off, Karag Dum," you begin. "I'm still much lighter on details than I would like to be, but they've bound or tricked or reached an accord with the current incarnation of Cor-Dum as well as a number of its followers. The full details are in the notes I had sent over, but the main point is that Borek's reaction and comments seem to indicate that however they did it, it's a possibility that he was already aware of and felt the rest of the Karaz Ankor would disapprove of. The observations that I and the other Wizards were able to make line up with what we saw, so I don't think it's any kind of trickery or illusion - Cor-Dum really is there and so are a number of Beastmen, though he appeared to have his aura of mutation suppressed until it was unleashed while it was being attacked by some Kurgan." "So the Kurgan were opposed to the Beastmen?" Belegar asks, his brow furrowed. "It seemed more like some sort of initiation or feat of bravery than a full-blown attack, there were many more horsemen watching than were trying to press the attack. They broke off as soon as one of them was mutated by exposure to Cor-Dum, which they seemed pleased with." "So it can't really be taken as indication that they're still opposed to Chaos." "That's my interpretation," you reply with a nod. "They were also maintaining the flow of energy southwards, but I don't know if they had any way to know that it had been hijacked to keep Karak Vlag trapped in the Aethyr, so that can't really be taken as proof one way or the other, either." Belegar considers that. "There's been communication flowing back and forth with gyrocopter messengers among the Kings of the Karaz Ankor, and the growing consensus seems to be that they've either completely fallen or they've turned to methods so radical that their fall is merely a matter of time. Do you have any insight that might contradict this?" You consider it, and shake your head. "Then so be it. That they seem to have no desire to explain themselves strikes me as the strongest indication that they're no longer to be trusted. Either whatever they've done is unforgivable, or they're so far gone that they no longer care what the rest of the Karaz Ankor thinks of them. It might be best to write them off and let them fade from history. They can do no more damage from where they are than the rest of the Chaos Wastes do already." You nod. "Especially with High Pass once more in friendly hands." You recount your discovery of the defences behind the magic keeping it sealed in the Warp, and the events that followed. "Fallen Slayers," he says heavily. "I never would have thought it possible, but I suppose what takes place in the Aethyr has no obligation to possibility. Who knows what sort of torments and trickery the Dark Gods would be capable of in the heart of their own realms." "I don't know how many survived-" "According to word from Karaz-a-Karak, two thirds, give or take," Belegar interrupts. "Twenty thousand." You take a moment to process that, then smile. "I'm glad so many did. That supports my suspicion that they were keeping the pressure high and casualties low to 'harvest' as many of the Dwarves as they can, whether their intention was to turn them into shock troops or just for their own amusement. If all they wanted was to wipe out the Karak, it would have been trivial for them to do so once it had been pulled into their realm." Belegar nods. "I shudder to think what ten thousand fallen Slayers would have done to Dwarven morale if they had come as a surprise during the next Great War. Our fallen kin in the east have already taught us that it's not impossible, but we've had plenty of time to grow used to them. Being suddenly confronted with an entirely new twisting of who we are could have been devastating." "There might still be thousands in the service of the Chaos Gods. Hopefully once they've adapted to their return, Karak Vlag should be able to give us some idea how many extant fallen there might be, and how many of their missing numbers died in the Karak's defence." "With the element of surprise gone, they're largely defanged," Belegar says confidently. "Their appearance on a battlefield now will only serve to spur us to greater heights." You consider the best way to segue into the next matter. "Do you know when Karaz-a-Karak learned how many of the survivors there were?" "At least a month ago. Thorgrim supposedly went there himself to coax them out from behind their defences." "And the conclave's announcement was dated shortly after that." "Ancestors forbid he acknowledges the good done by an Umgi," he says with a frown. "Much better to announce some drivel about Dwarven souls in Umgi bodies." Not quite how you'd word it, but it matches your own suspicions about the announcement. "From my understanding of Dwarves, that's not an announcement that would have come quickly." "Likely not. He must have called them in the moment he heard Karak Vlag had returned. A gyrocopter from High Pass, I assumed." You shake your head. "We had originally planned to have a gyrocopter with the Expedition, but we ended up using that deck space for Asarnil and Deathfang. We sent a Knight back to have a letter sent through the post from Praag." He frowns, and bends over the table to peer at the map, measuring distances with his fingers. "Kislev's horses are supposed to be exceptional," he says suspiciously, "but not quite that exceptional." "And that only would have got the message halfway," you confirm. "From there it would have been the Empire's Roadwardens." "So Thorgrim knew before he got the message?" "The timetable doesn't make sense otherwise." He considers that, and his frown deepens. "The flow of stolen energy resuming?" "I checked before we left High Pass, and it had resumed. So that seems to be the most likely explanation." "If true, that would prove that he knows of it. It's not some forgotten Golden Age relic still turning in the darkness." "Additionally, Borek knew of that flow of energy, and seemed surprised that I did." You double check your notes. "'Did Ulthuan tell your Order, or did King Belegar inherit secrets', is what he asked." "He was speaking Khazalid?" You nod. "Inherit secrets..." You've already gone through the thought process that Belegar is, though he might be able to extract something new from it. He speaks Khazalid natively and has done for many times your age, after all. Kalangromthit thindrongazgalak - no connotations of subterfuge as might be present in a Reikspiel translation. It was hidden in the sense that a vault might be hidden, as the proper protection for something valuable. "He believed that's why the High King did not contribute more to the Expedition, as he would have concluded that both northern Karaks had fallen due to the cutting off of their energy flow." He considers that. "From what I've been told by Dwarves that lived through it, the Karaz Ankor's ability to project power was all but crippled by the losses during the Great War. That's why Thorgrim was able to get the Engineers Guild to accept the crash-development of the Everpeak Aircorps, because it was that or nothing for decades. But it's true that he contributed more to the Karak Eight Peaks Expedition than to the Karag Dum one - that was mostly Zhufbar and Karak Kadrin." "'Karag Dum remembers much that others have forgotten, even when some might prefer we didn't. Even when we might prefer we didn't.' In hindsight, I think that last bit was a reference to whatever he feared Karag Dum had resorted to in his absence, which turned out to be correct." "'Some might prefer we didn't'," Belegar echoes. Umdawal sarbrynak binmhornak. That he used 'umdawal' for the 'some' might indicate that they're Dwarves, but it might not - Khazalid doesn't really have a race-neutral collective noun, so 'daw' is often defaulted to even when it isn't technically correct. So it could be taken as a general reference to secrets that the Marauder Tribes might prefer be forgotten, like the engineering, metalwork, and Runecraft that they had used to strike them down for generations. "Blast him for speaking in riddles." You nod firmly. You'd thought similar many times over the past few weeks. "Still. Karag Dum knew about it. If it was entirely to Karaz-a-Karak's benefit, they could have used that to pressure Karaz-a-Karak into supporting them - they'd called for aid a number of times in the lead-up to the Great War." "Thorek once spoke of a rift in the Runesmiths Guild between Karag Dum and the rest of them, as they'd insisted the true threat was north while everyone else was concerned with Ulthuan's movements in Bretonnia." "How bad did it get?" You remember Thorek's promise to tear the Guild asunder if his suspicions proved correct. "Bad," you say bleakly. "Would Karag Dum have been willing to resort to blackmail?" "They resorted to Cor-Dum as a bodyguard. I think they very much would have preferred blackmail, if it was an option." "And yet Borek ran around the Karaz Ankor for eighteen decades and never got more than accommodation and half an ear from Thorgrim." Belegar frowns as he processes that. "So either Karag Dum benefited or was complicit in some way..." "Or there's more to it than Karaz-a-Karak benefitting at the expense of the other Dwarfholds," you finish. Belegar scowls as he considers it further. "I'll have to give this matter more thought," he finally concedes. "The other matter I wanted to discuss-" He sighs. "Did you pull some other bizarre miracle on your way back?" You recall your visit to Kraka Ravnvake. "Not for lack of trying. No, this is a more in general sort of thing. I'm wondering what the future duties of Loremaster Weber would be." He nods. "The Karak is a lot more secure and orderly than it was when the Council was formed, and the same can't be said for the entire Karaz Ankor. The position is yours for as long as you want it and I'd be more than happy to keep you in reserve for when the next disaster comes knocking on our gates, but if you want to go further afield there's all sorts of ways you could be useful by building goodwill amongst the other Karaks. There was a time when every Karak lived as Karak Azul once did, where other Karaks were some theoretical thing that you heard from a few times a decade, but in this age of gyrocopters we're much more a united people, and that's on the verge of becoming more so with the canals. I want Karak Eight Peaks to retake its place at the forefront of the Karaz Ankor, and you could be a big part of that." "Do you have anything specific in mind?" you ask curiously. "I'm sure Karak Vlag could use assistance in making sense of the world they've returned to." He thinks for a moment more. "Zhufbar has a nest of Fire Dragons in one of their upper halls that has resisted every conventional attempt to evict them. Karak Norn always has strange and mystical troubles of one sort or another. Barak Varr has some sort of plan for Sartosa, which was an outpost of theirs long ago, but in modern times has proven able to resist any conventional assault - and there's also talk about something in the Border Princes to stamp out the pirate problems, you might be able to help with whatever that turns out to be. Karaz-a-Karak might be meaning to take a poke at Mount Silverspear - when I met with the Grey Mountains Clans they let slip that they're apparently also in talks with Karaz-a-Karak. If that's the case, they'd probably need something novel to avoid it going the same way as the Silver Road Wars. The current Emperor is asking for Dwarven assistance in securing under-Ubersreik... and undoubtedly there's plenty more that I'd hear word of once the Karaz Ankor realizes that you'd be available to help out." You nod thoughtfully. "That does sound interesting. I'll give it some thought over the next few months. Speaking of, what did you want me doing now that I'm back?" He smiles. "On top of recovering Karak Vlag and ending the uncertainty around Karag Dum? You were mining the seam from both ends in the lead-up to the Expedition. If you're absolutely desperate for something to keep your hands busy then the Lhune Depths could use poking around in, but don't feel obliged if you need to spend some time recovering. As much as you do your best to prove otherwise, I know humans aren't quite as sturdy as Dwarves." --- Pfaffbach's central keep isn't anywhere near the size of Eagle Castle, but its furnishings are much more luxurious than its modern size would lead one to expect. You suppose it's only natural, as this was once the holiday home of the current Empress in her previous guise. You're not sure if Roswita has grown used to them as the deserved trappings of a Grand Countess or is overlooking them entirely in favour of seeing this as the most central point to oversee the final Sylvanian holdouts. "I've been hearing that the siege is on the verge of ending for years now," you say as you slip into the room. "So have I," she says distractedly, staring broodingly down at a map. "But each year they get measurably weaker, and I can't justify putting my own impatience over needless Stirlandian deaths. I'm currently thinking I might use their soon-to-be-vacated titles to bring in more assistance. Siegfriedhof seems to thrive under the Black Guard, after all. Maybe another Order could follow their example." "Or you might lure in a Lord Magister," you say lightly. "Or that. I was wondering how long it would take you to get that letter. How was the Chaos Wastes?" "Plenty of chaos, but I wouldn't call the trip a waste." "So I hear. Do you really have the soul of a Dwarf?" You shrug. "That's what the Dwarven Conclave says. I don't really know enough about souls to say one way or the other with any confidence." She considers that, then nods. "It's out of my area of expertise too. I might have more to work with if it was out terrorizing the countryside. So you're here to talk about a title?" "I'm open to the possibility. Of Markgräfin, specifically." "Right." She taps the map forcefully. "Settling the matter of Sylvania is why I took the title of Grand Countess, but the oath I swore when I became it was to Stirland, not Sylvania, and I'm neglecting that oath with every season spent here. One way to resolve that is..." She frowns, considering her words. "Despite my misgivings when we first met, you've proven beyond any reasonable doubt that you're worthy of absolute trust. If you became Markgräfin of Sylvania, I could turn my full attention to Stirland without concerns." "And what would that entail, exactly?" "You would operate out of the County of Drakenhof, which would include Regrakhof and Teufelheim-" "Teufelheim is part of Drakenhof?" She nods. "On paper everything south of the South Stir is part of the County, even if it hasn't been enforced for Gods know how long. I'd make it clear to whoever become the Barons and Counts that they're to follow your lead and if there's any that I'm even a little unsure of I'll leave you with signed arrest orders for them, just in case. Your main priority is rooting out the remaining Vampires and Necromancers, and I'm sure there'd be plenty. We'll be levying taxes right from the start because it'll give us justification for digging through financials, but they'd be nominal and you'll have broad powers to waive them wherever necessary to secure cooperation. I don't care if Stirland doesn't see a penny from Sylvania for the next century, I just want to make sure it doesn't see a Vampire from it." You nod. "Have the locals been causing trouble so far?" "No, but that's with the entire Army of Stirland marching around the place. There's going to be true believer Vampire Cultists out there, whether or not there's any Vampires left to pull their strings. Those in power lived very comfortably in Sylvania when they were able to pay their taxes in other people's blood, and they won't give that up without a fight, and it's going to be the sort of fight fought by Witch Hunters and Grey Wizards, not the sort fought by the Army of Stirland." "Ah. Yes. Speaking of which..." She hesitates. "My preference would be the Holy Order of the Templars of Sigmar, but I'd understand if you'd rather bring in another organization to assist with that. The Longshanks have expressed an interest, as have Zhufbar's Order of the Stone Wall, which you'd probably get along with. There's already the Black Guard and the Dreamwalkers here, so I don't think the Fellowship would be a good fit. Priory of the Spear, maybe? Helhunten's? I hear the current Andanti is fairly skilled, or the Knights of Everlasting Light... it'd be entirely in your hands." "What of the matter of religion?" She leans back in her chair and sighs. "There's never been any sort of success trying to ram Sigmar down the throat of the Sylvanians, though I've been hearing from plenty who are eager to make another attempt. So, Rhya maybe? Verena? Myrmidia? Kasmir has some ideas involving old local Gods, and truth be told I don't care who they pray to as long as it's not a Vampire or a forbidden God - I'm sure there'll be plenty rushing to fill any vacuum." "That's a lot of latitude," you note. "Sylvania's not going to be brought to heel by someone shackled by micromanagement. You'd have full power to do whatever it takes to make sure that when one of the von Carsteins wakes back up, Sylvania doesn't immediately revert to their control." "And the duration?" "As long as it takes, as decided by yourself. Even if you become another Elspeth von Draken, if you feel the job's not done, then you can be delivering reports to my great grandchildren." "That's a lot of trust." She runs a hand over her face. "If I'd given it to you earlier, I'd already be done here. I like to think that I don't make the same mistakes twice." --- The citizens of Altdorf take pride in cultivating an air of indifference to Wizards doing Wizard things, so it's something of a surprise when your arrival in Nuln gets a similar lack of reaction. It takes you a moment to remember that Nuln has been home to a much more formidable figure for generations, and your entrance can't come close to comparing to that of a Carmine Dragon. Nuln is a city of castles. There's the hilltop Palace that once used to be the home of the Emperor, of course, but Nuln's Cathedral of Sigmar was where the worship of Sigmar was born and is built as an expression of martial might, rather than more traditional piety. Nuln is the capital of Myrmidia's worship within the Empire, and the Temple of Myrmidia is the size of a city block and as fortified as one would expect of the Goddess of War. The College of Engineering, little-known would-be rival to the Imperial Gunnery School, is a demonstration of the art it promises to teach its students, and the Imperial Gunnery School is much more sprawling but also much more bristling with every kind of artillery imaginable. And around the entire city are twenty-foot walls patrolled by the 'Blue Heron' mercenary band, who were originally Tilean but have been on retainer in Nuln for so long that it would take quite some searching to find a Tilean accent among them. You wonder how much defence it all would prove against attack from below. You need wait only a minute before you're shown into the dining hall of Nuln's Palace, where Grand Count Konstantin von Liebwitz has half the table filled with food and the other with paperwork. "Pull up a chair," he says as you approach. "Grab a drumstick if you've a mind to. You're here about the Spymaster job?" "Yes, your grace." "Kazrik raves about you, and from how you played the rats against each other under Eight Peaks, I can understand why. We tried something similar here, and, well," he waves a hand missing three fingers at you. "Got off lightly, too. And from what I understand, they're not the sort to forgive and forget." "That's one way to put it," you agree. "Now, I understand that you Grey Wizards aren't allowed to play politics, and if you take the job I won't be pointing you anywhere outside of Wissenland's borders, it'd be entirely about the rats." He frowns and considers. "Maybe Cults and Beastmen and that sort of thing too if they pop up while you're here, but you get what I mean. Enemies of the Empire." He drains his tankard and then puts it down and taps it, then looks up and frowns. "Right, I sent them out. Rats are a secret, after all. What's that about? Nobody can give me a straight answer." "They call it the 'Conspiracy of Silence'. The theory is if they think we don't know about them, then they'll feel safe enough to fight amongst themselves rather than uniting against humanity." "Does it work?" You shrug. "Seems to. As far as I know, we haven't lost an Emperor to them since Mandred Skavenslayer." "I always thought he was a story for children, chasing the rats through the street with his hammer. Anyway, apparently we've got Clan Skab under us, whatever that means." You're glad you checked your books before setting out. "The nine most powerful Skaven Clans have a seat on their ruling Council. Clan Skab is one of them. They produce an inordinate amount of Stormvermin, the black-furred warrior caste, and train them to a higher standard than other Clans, and a lot of their wealth and influence comes from selling their services as bodyguards." "So, none of the tricks with monsters and strange guns?" "They probably do have them. That'd be what they'd spend their wealth and influence acquiring." "Damn. Anyway, that's the score. You're good at killing rats, and we've got a lot of rats that need killing. You'll have all the resources of Wissenland behind you, and if you're like the Dark Lady and want to build a creepy tower, you can have the Iron Isle - it's the size of a city block but the Dwarves get annoyed if we try to do anything with it, but they like you, right?" "Why do they care?" "Used to be part of some old fortress of theirs, they say." "Kazad Kro?" He shrugs. "Maybe? I thought they were just screwing with us. Dwarves build in mountains, after all." "Things were different, once." From your recent readings on the War of Vengeance, you know that Kazad Kro was the wealthiest of the Dwarven cities built in the Reik basin. The so-called 'Hill Dwarves' of the lowlands took the brunt of Elven attacks before the war swung in favour of the Dwarves, and most of them either returned to the mountains or started new lives amongst the human tribes of the Belthani that lived in the forests. In time the ancestors of the Empire arrived and conquered or assimilated the Belthani, and those Dwarves became the first of the Imperial Dwarves, and some of their descendants probably call Nuln home once more. No wonder they'd be touchy about the home of their fallen glory. "This is why Wissenland needs you. Put an enemy in front of me and I'll fight them. Put a politician in front of me and I'll yell at them. But secret underground rat bases? Ancient Dwarven history? I need someone who can sort that out, and when I asked people who know about this sort of thing, your name kept coming up. I'll pay well, I'll give you whatever support you need, and if you want to get up to creepy Wizard stuff in your off hours, Nuln is used to that sort of thing." --- The Laurel's Rest is one of the most expensive and exclusive hostels in Altdorf, and one would expect that even a Lord Magister would have to marshal some resources to finagle their way in. If the ladies-in-waiting who accompany the Empress everywhere are harbouring any sort of grudge that you'd somehow managed to slip effortlessly into the position of the Empress' confidante, they might have expected that this is where you'd get your comeuppance. If so, they shall have to live with disappointment, as the Greatsword bodyguard are used to you, the doorman is trivial to slip by, and when your presence is noticed, it's by the Halfling kitchen overseers who take it in turns to shake you by the hand and bombard you with questions about goings-on in Karak Eight Peaks, where they apparently have kin. When you manage to extricate yourself, you slip into a chair across from Heidi and conceal a smirk as the hangers-on are dismissed to the other side of the room. "He has been insufferable," is the first thing she says to you. "You're a bad influence on Him. He never fought other Gods until you entered the picture." "This time was his idea," you say, smiling. "He wanted to make nice with Kislev." "Do you know what's up with that? He keeps being smugly mysterious about it all." "Something to do with him getting the Ancient Widow's siblings killed, apparently." She frowns. "Siblings? I mean, husband would make sense, because I assume she had to have one once. But I didn't really see her as the sibling type." "The Ice Witches seem to think that Ursun and Dazh and Tor are Her brothers," you say with a shrug. She considers that, then waves a hand dismissively. "Someone else's problem. Maybe your problem, actually. Is that why you're here?" "No, I was curious about the 'bodyguard' thing." "And you're not talking to the Chamberlain?" You give her a flat look, and she smiles. "Yes, it's my idea. For now he's a bit young to be tutored in your sort of thing, but nobody's too young to be assassinated. I won't waste you on day-to-day bodyguarding, but there's a few occasions a year that are too public for my liking that I'd like you there for, and I want you to sort out his day-to-day bodyguards - recruit, vet, and equip. We've got Greatswords, but they're a blunt instrument. From what I've heard, you saw for yourself how easily they can be bypassed when you were a mere Journeywoman." You nod thoughtfully. "And the rest of the time?" "Politics, my dear. I went and looked up those Articles of yours, and as long as I get my darling Luitpold to make it an order, you wouldn't be restricted by the Grey Order's rules. He comes second, they come fourth." You mentally review Article 1 and nod. 'Laws and ideals of their Order' comes after 'he who is rightfully elected Emperor of Sigmar’s Holy Empire'. "What did you have in mind, specifically?" "Luitpold isn't a young man, and Emperor's a job where many never have the chance to grow old. If something happens to him, Gods forbid, then it needs to be Mandred that's next. Electors don't like child Emperors, and I want to be able to count on their support should the worst happen. If there was a vote tomorrow, it'd almost certainly be Grand Duke Feuerbach of Talabecland. Failing that, Hertwig or van Hal." You take a moment to process that. "You think Roswita could be Empress?" "Of course. She's all but conquered Sylvania, she's cozy with the Cult of Sigmar, and she still has a marriage that could seal the right alliance. Great compromise candidate. Point is, it will take work to get things sorted out so that Mandred can get the votes instead, and there's no better or more trustworthy instrument for those sorts of games than your very own self." "What sort of games do you have in mind?" you ask cautiously. "Nothing drastic. Just the right conversations with the right people, and maybe the right favours to secure the right allies. Everyone has outstanding bugbears that need slaying, they always do. Middenland and Nordland have each other, Wissenland has the rats, Stirland has Sylvania, Ostermark has Mordheim, you get the picture. Hopefully it will all be wasted effort and Luitpold will live to see Mandred grow up to be a dashing young man, but if it isn't, then I - and our mutual friend - would be very much in your debt." You recall something Heideck once said to you: 'Many die in debt to Ranald, but very few die with Ranald in debt to them.' In your experience, Ranald tends to pay his debts quite extravagantly. Being the one that saved his long-term gamble on a future Emperor would be a very advantageous position to be in. "Interesting," you say. "I've got some other possibilities to follow up on-" She snorts. "Swamp Town?" You frown at her until she elaborates. "I hear that the worst part of being the Chancellor of the Imperial Treasury is finding some poor bastard to trick into taking the job, and even if they succeed they've got to find a new one in a few years after the last dies of lizards. Everyone that reaches Lord Magister gets that offer, as do half the graduates of Diesdorf and Bergo." She considers it. "Maybe you'd have a better chance than most, but honestly, it's a hovel trapped between jungle and an ocean, just waiting for the lizards from one side or the pirates from the other to wipe it out. And then a new shipful of bright-eyed colonists arrive to do it all again." "I'll keep that in mind," you say dryly. But you're here in Altdorf, so you might as well hear the Chancellor out. --- An oft-repeated joke by the more tedious sort of politician is that the Reiksmarshal is the Imperial Fist, but the Chancellor is the Imperial Fisc. This doesn't bring you any useful insight, but it's difficult to put the pun from your mind as you enter the offices of the Chancellor. An example of the power of access, Chancellor Friedrich von Schlafebild is from an old but destitute family that expended the last of its influence on securing him the position of Kammerjunker in a last-ditch gamble that has paid handsome dividends. "Lady Magister," he says as you are shown into his office. "How may I be of service?" "Your invitation garnered my curiosity," you say with a thin smile. "My-" puzzlement flashes across his face, then realization seems to strike with a wince. "Er. Yes. I suppose it- yes. Governor-General of the New World territories. Or Governess-General, I suppose." He shuffles the papers in front of him. "What was it you wanted to know?" "What troubles does Swamp Town face that would require my calibre of oversight?" "It's a very lucrative colony," he says almost defensively, "even discounting the trade in gold and jade. There are many herbs and spices only known to grow there that are in great demand in the Old World, and the utility of having a friendly harbour in the New World cannot be overstated. But the challenges are significant. Port Reaver and Skeggi, of course, as well as the pirates of the Vampire Coast. And the local inhabitants, lizards larger than men wielding spears and clubs that are still formidable despite being made of stone. Communicating with them seems to be extremely difficult, while offending them seems extremely easy. The garrison is understaffed and there's next to no static defences." He seems to perk up. "All that said, it seems to be a very attractive destination to the more adventurous sort of Wizard." "How so?" "Strange magics, strange creatures, strange plants, strange cities. The Elves seem to believe that whoever built those cities are older than even they, though I suppose they must have fallen to those lizards. If you're interested in it as a College-endorsed study, you'd have a very free hand to investigate the secrets of the New World. We'd also be able to offer you a crewed Wolfship, both to transport you there and to protect the harbour against raiders. Any prizes it seizes would be split between yourself and the treasury, as there's no Admiral of the New World to claim a share." "Any friendly outposts in the area?" "Santa Magritta and Nuevo Luccini nearby, as well as the ruins of Cadavo and Dalmark Town. There's rumours Bretonnia is interested in founding a colony as well, and there's an outpost of the Sea Elves nearby up the coast called Arnheim. Patrols from there regularly do their best to suppress piracy in the region." You consider that. It's pretty clear that it's an unwanted position, but that does mean you'll be able to barter for all sorts of concessions if you intend to take it. That far from the Empire you'd have free rein to run Swamp Town as you see fit, to investigate the mysteries of the New World, to claim a share of some extremely lucrative trade goods, and to essentially operate as a privateer against hostile naval forces in the area. Perhaps not the best career move, but it would absolutely be an adventure. "Thank you for satisfying my curiousity," you say. "I'll let you know if I decide the offer appeals to me." "Thank you for your consideration, Lady Magister," he says with a nervous smile. --- Once more you journey from Altdorf to Karak Eight Peaks with your mind on your future, but this time it's much better equipped with knowledge and ready to make a permanent decision. A lot of doors have opened to you with your newly-acquired promotion, but tragically you can only go through one. Select the opportunity or opportunities that most appeal to you. The one with the most votes will be the course Mathilde embarks upon. [ ] Loremaster Sinecure [ ] Loremaster-at-Large of Karak Eight Peaks [ ] The Waystone Project [ ] Markgraf of Eastern Stirland [ ] Count of Sylvania [ ] Spymaster of Wissenland [ ] Ambassador-at-Large to the Karaz Ankor [ ] Bodyguard and Tutor to Prince Mandred [ ] Governor-General of Swamp Town [ ] Ranaldian High Priest of Kislev [ ] Border Princess of the Howling River [ ] Nagarythe [ ] Research Sabbatical - Due to the amount of impact the vote will have on the future of the quest, there will be a twenty-four hour moratorium so everyone has a chance to engage in discussion, whatever their time zone or daily schedule happens to be. - There are no wrong answers here. Mathilde has earned the freedom to choose her own path in life, and it's entirely valid for her to pick something interesting over something responsible. Other competent people exist in the world, and will take the jobs that Mathilde doesn't. - Do not choose Research Sabbatical if there's just one or two things you want to finish off. There will be time to wrap things up before Mathilde moves on to her next position. Also keep in mind that while finishing off your research queue might be the responsible thing to do, it also has the potential to be achingly dull, and not all the same opportunities will be available once she's done. - I've seen some people talking up the Elfcation as it would be 'short'. That might be the case in in-universe time elapsed, but the Karag Dum Expedition was just as 'short' and look how much IRL time that took us. Don't vote for it just to get it 'out of the way'. - Mathilde has several logistical options available to her that will allow her to maintain her home and friends in Karak Eight Peaks while working elsewhere, unless that elsewhere is Swamp Town. - The next vote will decide on expenditures of Boons and Great Deeds, so they can be selected while knowing what Mathilde's next position will be. - Yes, Mathilde could select an opportunity that she did not investigate. Perhaps she feels lucky. - If you have further questions about any of the opportunities Mathilde investigates, ask and I'll answer, and I might edit the response into the above. - The exact details of how a position will work will be negotiated with whoever oversees it once a decision is made, and the thread will be able to vote on what concessions are most desired.

Planning the Waystone Project, Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] The Waystone Project Though you've so far managed to keep them from being too divided, you are a woman of many loyalties: to the Grey Order, to the Empire, to Stirland, to Karak Eight Peaks, and to Ranald. At this crossroads in your life, you were pulled in very different directions by many of them. To further support your adoptive home of Karak Eight Peaks by continuing as Loremaster and burnishing the good name of King Belegar among the Karaz Ankor; to finish the job you began seventeen years ago and bring Sylvania properly under control of Stirland and the Empire; to further the machinations of your God by ensuring his imperial gambit comes to fruition with the future ascension of Emperor Mandred II to the throne. But there's one path that has the potential to serve all those you feel loyal to, and indeed all of the Civilized Realms: the Waystone Project. Though you realize your idle daydreams of being able to fully replicate the masterworks of Ulthuan and the Karaz Ankor at their respective heights is unlikely, a better understanding of the Waystones would allow them to be better protected and might allow for bolstering them in some way. They and the Great Vortex are what make life possible on this world, as otherwise the magic constantly pouring in from the poles would accumulate indefinitely and allow Daemons to freely walk the world once more, and the forces of Chaos are very aware of this and often seek to corrupt or destroy them. Before his departure, Teclis charged the Colleges to protect the Waystones of the Old World at all costs, a duty that is all too easy to neglect when one is forced to choose between protecting the lives of innocents and protecting oversized rocks in overgrown forests. All well and good, but much easier said than done. The reason you have any hope at all of succeeding where so many have failed is that you have the opportunity to bring together many sources of information, with a strong foundation of the Eonir, the Karaz Ankor, and the Colleges. But that comes with one major question: though you're counting on the cooperation of all three, under whose aegis will the actual project be? To make this choice, you've brought yourself once more to Altdorf to meet with a living legend of the Grey College: Provost Kurtis Krammovitch, possibly the most suborned man in the history of espionage. His life story is extremely classified, but also common knowledge amongst the Grey Order - such is often the case amongst the greatest of Grey Wizards. He was born to parents who were members of the Hedgefolk, an organization dedicated to a form of magic known as Hedgecraft, involving potions, talismans, and a form of magic centered around The Hedge, the conceptual border between wilderness and civilization, and between the material and the spiritual. Not to be confused with 'Hedge Magic', which is a catch-all for any form of non-Teclisean, non-Dark magic. Not quite an Order, not quite a Cult, but a powerful and ancient organization nonetheless. It's said that they date back to man's first arrival in the Reik basin, and that Sigmar was assisted by the Hedgewise during His mortal days. But with power and respect comes enemies, as the Sigmarites resent any suggestion that their God had magical assistance, the Taalites brook no competition for the conceptual territory of the wilderness, and the Ulricans oppose them because Middenlander Hedgefolk worship Ranald, whom many Ulricans despise. By the late 2200s they were almost on their last legs, and when Teclis formed the Colleges he may have sealed the fate of the Hedgefolk, as in a single stroke he poached some of their most powerful and knowledgeable magic-users as founders of the Grey Order and created a new entity that was charged with hunting the Hedgefolk as unauthorized magic-users. All this set the stage for Kurtis' formative tragedy, as when he was barely more than a baby his parents were burned as witches, some say by a Bright Wizard. He was raised by his uncle, also a member of the Hedgefolk, and developed the gift of magic at the shockingly tender age of eight. At the age of nineteen, he was a master at Hedgecraft and had pretensions of being a master of espionage, and attempted to infiltrate the Grey Order by pretending to be a newly-developed talent where a Grey Wizard could see him, and allowed himself to be brought to Altdorf to be taught as a Grey Wizard. Somewhere along the way he was either found out or developed actual loyalty to the Grey Order - the stories vary - and was flipped to being the Grey Order's spy on the Hedgefolk, as Article 13 requires the Grey Order to do. There are many parts of the world where the Colleges have no sway but the Hedgefolk are greatly respected, and thanks to Kurtis' influence many budding magical talents who proved unsuited to Hedgecraft were funnelled to the Colleges, where previously they would have been left to their own devices, and such stories rarely end well. But after one of these recruits came to a nasty end at the hands of the Magisters Vigilant - deservedly or otherwise, as once again different versions of the story exist - Kurtis changed allegiances once more, and became the agent of the Hedgefolk inside the Grey Order. In these years the Hedgefolk got their hands on many secrets and spells that the Colleges would prefer they not have. (Or not, as some versions of the story posit that spreading Teclisean teachings amongst the Hedgefolk would be in line with College doctrine. Was this a ploy by the Grey Order, to feed Teclisean teachings to the Hedgefolk in the hopes that one day they might be absorbed entirely into the Grey Order? Was Kurtis an unwilling dupe whose 'betrayal' was orchestrated by another, or did he merely pretend to be suborned in cooperation with the Grey Order's plot?) The next change in allegiance came shortly after Kurtis' promotion to Lord Magister, as disaster struck the Hedgefolk in a way that highlighted the disadvantages of such a splintered and varied organization. The Ostland Hedgefolk were almost entirely wiped out in a skirmish with a necromancer in the Forest of Shadows, and the few survivors refused (and, as far as you know, still refuse) any assistance in restoring their numbers as the 'foreign' Hedgefolk were not dedicated to their patron Goddess Halétha, which all but guarantees that the Hedgefolk will go extinct in Ostland within a generation or two. It's said he went to the newly-promoted Algard and confessed his actions expecting to be burned or Pacified, but instead he was promoted to Provost, enshrining his twin loyalties in his job description. It is hoped that one day the Colleges of Magic will have enough manpower and influence to cover the entirety of the Empire from the largest city to the smallest and most remote hamlet, but until that day the Hedgefolk were a lesser evil in a very long list of some very evil evils, so it was in the interest of the Empire and the Colleges that the Hedgefolk benefit from a blind eye and a backchannel. The argument being that Article 15's exhortation to oppose 'destructive and anti-Imperial machinations, practices, peoples, and creatures' does describe itself as the 'prime concern and purpose of the Colleges, their Orders and the Magisters belonging to them', and thus assisting the Hedgefolk in poaching magic-users in remote areas that might otherwise be recruited by practitioners of Forbidden Lores is in accordance with the Articles, even if in a vacuum it could be considered to breach Article 13. Of course, many would not see it that way, which is why that is Lord Magister Krammovitch's unofficial responsibility. His official one as Provost is to maintain the Grey Order's official relations with organizations both inside and outside the Empire, and it's to that end you've sought him out today. He more than anyone will be aware of the possibilities and pitfalls that your Waystone Project might encounter as it tries to make the transition from an idea existing entirely in your own head to an actual formal organization. You meet him within the Tempelgarten, a tranquil and charming park taking up a significant amount of space in one of Altdorf's wealthiest districts that nonetheless manages to fend off any attempts to build over it thanks to the combined efforts of the Taalites and Rhyans, the Jade College, and a particularly touchy resident spirit. Lord Magister Kurtis is sitting on a lakeside bench and subjecting the ducks to careful scrutiny, and you take the opportunity to subject him to the same. Many elder Wizards are able to maintain an appearance that you once heard described as 'old enough that you should respect me, young enough that I can still thump you over the head if you don't', and Kurtis slots firmly into the elder end of that bracket, with grey hair and deep lines on his leathery face. "Lady Magister," he says without turning as you approach. "Lord Magister," you reply. "Ducks behaving themselves?" "I've got a colleague in the Amber Brotherhood that keeps them in line." You're not sure if he's joking or not, so you simply nod as you take a seat next to him. "So. Waystones, is it?" You nod. "The Eonir reached out through the Cult of Ulric, they're interested in working with me and the Dwarves of Karak Eight Peaks on the matter." "Algard nearly had kittens over that. Not a lot of good reasons for the Cult of Ulric to single out a specific Grey Wizard and ask for a meet. We came up with a lot of guesses and none of them came close to the mark in the end." "That whole business took a lot of people by surprise, from what I've heard." "In hindsight, it shouldn't have. Nordland's been ratcheting up the pressure for centuries, whether they intended to or not. Where they see prime shipbuilding timber, the Eonir sees a residential district. Something was going to give eventually. But that's a headache for the Emperor to sort out. You want to know what official framing to give your project." "I suppose the easiest solution would be to just have it be a joint project between-" "No," he interrupts. "Definitely not. You inherit the baggage and enemies of all of them and don't garner enough gratitude from each individually to make up for it." You nod. "What are my options, then?" "Most obviously, you keep it in-house. A project of a Lord Magister of the Grey Order. That's the easiest and will mean it doesn't get as much attention, for good or ill - anyone that holds opinions about us will already hold those opinions about you for being one of us. It'll mean you'll be under Algard's jurisdiction and would make for easy relations with the other Colleges. It does mean you'll be tied to Imperial politics if that's an issue. Or if you use some of the influence you've been accumulating to found an institute or branch of some sort, it'd put you directly under Dragomas instead of Algard, but it would mean that you're starting from zero with the other Colleges. Both of these would mean that you'd be operating under the laws of the Empire, including the Articles, so you won't be able to employ foreign magic-users - it would bring them under Imperial authority, which would oblige you to recruit them into an Order, report them to the Witch Hunters, or destroy them." "But I could still work with them, right? I've seen foreign magic-users at College events." He sighs. "That's a can of worms. Legally, Damsels and Ice Witches are considered clergy under Imperial law, rather than magic-users. Properly accredited Arabyan and Tilean magic-users are overlooked by the Templars for diplomatic reasons, rather than legal ones. Same with the Ulthuan diplomats when they've been from Saphery. I doubt you have to worry about anyone trying to claim that Runesmiths should be recognized as magic-users, but technically every magic-using Eonir in Laurelorn is in violation of the Empire's laws. Anyone daft enough to try to enforce it has never emerged from Laurelorn, but it could be an ugly mess if you go that route and end up getting the wrong sort of attention." He gives a significant glance to the bulk of the Cathedral of Sigmar, visible over the trees. "If I did, how would that turn out?" "Indefinite legal limbo as it turns into one more reason for the Sigmarites and Ulricans to yell at each other, probably. So you won't end up burned over it, but it would be a headache to deal with. Though that does remind me - you could also have it under Middenland authority, they're eager to build goodwill with their new 'converts' so they'd jump at the chance. That'd mean you're under the aegis of the Graf and the Ar-Ulric, rather than Dragomas, and does mean that Middenland and the Cult of Ulric will be on your side. But, again, the Sigmarites would be likely to be a headache." "For the sake of argument, what are my options outside Imperial law?" "Firstly, Karak Eight Peaks, of course - much the same as you are already. You'd be under Dwarven law, which I assume you already know the pros and cons of. This would leave you free to bring in any magic-users recognized by them - Imperial Wizards, Ice Witches, Damsels, Tileans, Tempelwijk... not sure about Arabyan ones, you'd have to check. The Eonir ones might be a problem, though. War of the Ancients and all that." "I've looked into that, at least legally the Eonir are free from that baggage. In the lead-up to the War they were on the brink of open rebellion against Ulthuan's authority, and after the fifth Phoenix King withdrew his armies from the Old World, the Eonir declared independence." He nods. "Much the same as the Asrai, then. I've been meaning to read up on all of that, but there's always something that needs doing and at least so far nobody's dragged the Colleges into that whole mess. Being under Dwarven authority won't bring you any enemies you shouldn't have already, except perhaps Marienburg. It would mean you should be able to bludgeon the Cult of Sigmar with their 'aid Dwarf-folk' scripture to get them to cooperate, which would be a rare advantage for a magical research project to have. And the other side of the coin, under Eonir authority. I can't really tell you much of how that would operate - they're not exactly open about their society - but it would put you under their law and authority. But it would mean you'd be able to approach Marienburg without any of the baggage of current politics, and it might mean you'd be able to make overtures to Ulthuan - Finubar has been building bridges with the Asrai and Eonir ever since the Asur returned to the Old World." You nod, taking mental notes. "Those are my options?" "The ones that seem relevant to me. You could approach any province or any nation, I suppose." He shrugs and smiles. "You could always go to the Border Princes. Wouldn't be the first research project to do so, not even the first this decade. But it does mean the Witch Hunters would start sniffing around, and from what I gather the neighbours there are often unfriendly, even when they aren't green." You smile. "I've heard the same. Thank you for your insight." "It was my duty to provide it. Let me know if you need any further help, whether it be making introductions or hashing out the details. Algard's very interested in this project of yours, and after your successes so far, he's willing to give you quite a lot of leeway to make it happen." You leave the park with a smile on your face from that last tidbit, and begin to collate your mental notes, adding on to the possibilities that Kurtis touched on with a few of your own, ranging from the obvious to the outright fanciful. Roswita seemed like she'd be happy to have you close at hand, so Stirland is one possibility. You got along well with Ljiljana and Ranald is up to something up north, so Kislev might be another - it might be nice for the Fire Spire to rule Praag's skyline once more. And while you're spitballing, your good name amongst the Dwarves could get you in the door at Tobaro in Tilea. And you've heard that Karak Norn has been working well with Carcassonne lately, so they might be a possibility too, and might open the door to working with the Damsels. And with all this talk of Marienburg... well, there's one way you could bypass the current political tension. Fully compiled, the list looks something like: Grey Order Jurisdiction: The Empire Superiors: Emperor Luitpold, Supreme Patriarch Dragomas, Magister Patriarch Algard Natural Allies: Colleges of Magic, Reikland, Hedgewise? Relevent Opposers: Marienburg Research Institute Jurisdiction: The Empire Superiors: Emperor Luitpold, Supreme Patriarch Dragomas Natural Allies: Reikland Relevant Opposers: Marienburg Karak Eight Peaks Jurisdiction: Karaz Ankor Superiors: High King Thorgrim Grudgebearer, King Belegar Ironhammer Natural Allies: Dwarven Kingdoms, Cult of Sigmar Relevant Opposers: Marienburg Laurelorn Jurisdiction: The Eonir Superiors: Queen Marrisith, Vicereine Cadaeth? Natural Allies: Middenland, Cult of Ulric, Eonir, Ulthuan? Relevant Opposers: Cult of Sigmar, Nordland Middenland Jurisdiction: The Empire Superiors: Emperor Luitpold, Graf Boris X Todbringer, Ar-Ulric Carl Valgeir Natural Allies: Middenland, Cult of Ulric, Eonir Relevant Opposers: Marienburg, Cult of Sigmar, Nordland Stirland Jurisdiction: The Empire Superiors: Emperor Luitpold, Grand Countess Roswita Van Hal Natural Allies: Stirland, Zhufbar Relevant Opposers: None Marienburg Jurisdiction: Marienburg Superiors: The Directorate Natural Allies: Marienburg, Baron Henryk's College of Navigation and Sea Magicks, Great Library of Verena, Ulthuan? Relevant Opposers: None? Praag Jurisdiction: Kislev Superiors: Tzar Vladimir Bokha, Z'ra of Praag Natural Allies: Kislev, Ice Witches, Karak Vlag Relevant Opposers: None Carcassonne Jurisdiction: Bretonnia Superiors: King Phillippe V, Duke Huebald, Morgiana le Fay? Natural Allies: Carcassonne, Damsels?, Asrai? Relevant Opposers: None Tobaro Jurisdiction: Tobaro Superiors: Prince Angelo de Vela Natural Allies: Tobaro, Estalia Relevant Opposers: Tilean City-States Border Princes Jurisdiction: None Superiors: None Natural Allies: Barak Varr Relevant Opposers: Witch Hunters, Greenskins, other Border Princes You won't make a decision here and now, of course. For most of them you'd have to do some research and probably meet a few key figures and discuss how a theoretical agreement might work. Now is the time to start carving down the list of possibilities to a few solid possibilities that you'll investigate further - and if they all turn out to be duds, there's always doing it as part of the Grey Order to fall back on. Vote for as many possibilities as appeal to you. Mathilde will seek further details of the winning four and the final decision will be made amongst those four plus 'Grey Order', which is the 'default' position and has no further details to seek. Anything that does not make the final four cut-off will not be a possibility for the final vote. [ ] Research Institute [ ] Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Laurelorn [ ] Middenland [ ] Stirland [ ] Marienburg [ ] Praag [ ] Carcassone [ ] Tobaro [ ] Border Princes - There will be a three hour moratorium. - If you have an idea for another host - that is, somewhere that would bring an advantage that nowhere already present has, not 'I want to see if Boney will add Kleinkleckersdorf to the list' - please let me know. - Stirland does not mean being Markgraf, Praag does not mean being High Priestess, and Border Princes does not mean being Barak Varr's nation-builder. It would be happening on the side and getting involved in it would be an option, but someone else would be in charge of it. - Research Institute would not necessarily require Mathilde to expend a Great Deed or a Boon - she has the resources to make it happen with money and favour, though doing so would be expensive. If that option wins, Mathilde would explore the possible expenditures to make it happen. - Don't just consider who will be the most friendly landlord. Authority over the project is a big card you can only place once, and it can open doors that would otherwise remain closed. - Yes, Carcassonne is misspelled in the voting options. It wasn't brought to my attention until voting had already begun. The correct spelling will be used in the future.

Planning the Waystone Project, Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results Tally [*] Karak Eight Peaks [*] Laurelorn [*] Carcassone [*] Praag "Right," King Belegar says as you approach him in Karag Lhune's council chamber, where he's locked in battle with teetering stacks of books, scrolls, and letters in his attempts to find ways to lure Clans to Karak Eight Peaks. "You wanted to talk about setting up the Waystone project here?" You nod. "You'll have my backing wherever you end up doing this, of course, but all the resources and influence of the Karak are concentrated here. You're already familiar with the advantages of the Karak - decent wealth and influence, access to Dwarven resources and expertise, Gyrocarriages, and the like. The complicated part is the Runesmiths. Operating out of Karak Eight Peaks would mean you'll have easy access to Kragg and Thorek if you can convince them to get involved, as well as making it easier to recruit any other Runesmiths you think might be able to contribute. The Cult of Thungni is very leery about outsiders getting their hands on their secrets, and being under Dwarven authority would make them more comfortable with the situation and might help sway any that are unsure. "Of course, the reason they'd be more comfortable is that the Cult of Thungni has a lot of law, precedent, and tradition backing them up when it comes to keeping their secrets. They're not going to get anywhere trying to claim the Waystones themselves as secrets of Runesmithing because they were created in conjunction with the Elves, but they might stick their nose in if they think you're getting too close to what they consider theirs. It might be easier to perform your investigation far from their reach with an open-minded Runesmith than to do it right under their nose - I trust you to keep any secrets you stumble across to yourself, but the Cult of Thungni may not." You nod as you absorb this. "Whose jurisdiction would I technically be under in that regard? Karak Eight Peaks doesn't have a Runesmiths Guild." "Not for lack of trying on my part. If there's something that needs to become official, then the Ironbrows of Karak Azul would argue that it should fall to them, while the Thungnissons of Karaz-a-Karak would undoubtedly do the same. The Redbeards of Barak Varr might end up a compromise candidate. But whoever it is, I assume it wouldn't help to have a suspicious Runesmith looking over your shoulder and glaring at the Elves." "Probably not," you admit. "The other complicating factor would be Waystones themselves. I'd ask that you not try to experiment with the Karags, and I don't know where the next nearest ones would be, whether you might be able to find some in the Badlands or the Border Princes or might have to travel all the way to the Empire. You'd have access to the Gyrocarriages for that, of course, but that seems like it would still present an inconvenience." "It may, depending on what it would actually look like once we get to the in-person study and experimentation." You frown as you consider it further. Do greenskins habitually interfere with the Waystones? Would Strygos have? What about the many, many different holders of the Border Princes over the years? It might actually come down to having to go all the way to the southern Empire for the nearest working Waystone. "We're certainly not short of places you could set up," Belegar continues. "You could expand further down into Karag Nar, or if you need somewhere away from bystanders, Kvinn-Wyr or Karag Zilfin are mostly empty. Or the Lhune Depths, or the Silver Tower, or... well, it might be quicker to list the areas that aren't available. You get the idea." "What about the matter of politics? If I'm under your authority, then technically I'm also under that of the High King." "And if the Karak-Waystones are being used to benefit Karaz-a-Karak alone, then he could use that authority to try to interfere with attempts to inspect the Waystones. That's true, but if he does do so it would confirm my suspicion and give me an excellent reason to broach the topic with the other Kings. While the letter of the law gives the High King a great deal of power, most of it hasn't been exercised since the shattering of the Underway. Four millennia of tradition carry a lot of weight." You nod while you resist the urge to frown. While that confirmation might be very useful to King Belegar, it could also grind the project to a halt as it gets bogged down within a larger conflict within the Karaz Ankor. You've got greater ambitions for it than being a diplomatic tripwire. "Out of curiosity, where are the other candidates? Altdorf and Laurelorn, I assume?" "Those two, plus Carcassonne and Praag." "I've been hearing good things of Carcassonne of late from Karak Norn and Karak Izor. I'd been hoping that manlings would take note of the Dalaz Kron business after the reclamation, and wondering if word of it spread that far afield, or if they've got some other reason to align with the Grey Mountain Dwarves. As for Praag... well, few places would welcome what you hope to provide more than they, I'm sure." --- That Laurelorn is far from the worst forest on the continent to walk into unannounced and unescorted says more about the continent than it does about Laurelorn. So you have Lord Magister Krammovitch send a message to his counterpart in the Gold Order, who sends a message to the Wizards and Alchemists Guild in Middenheim, who send a message to the Graf's diplomat, who presumably sends a message to someone of the Eonir. The reply you get has you travelling north to Middenheim to collect a letter of transit, then further north to Nordland's capital of Salzenmund. Built at the confluence of the headwaters of the Salz in the Silver Hills, Salzenmund is known as a bustling and prosperous city built upon carpentry and silversmithing. But that was before the Eonir began to enforce their territorial claims and now Salzenmund abuts the border with a foreign power, and in stark contrast to its reputation the city you find is quiet, tense, and full of soldiers, and the western wall is bristling with cannon. The phrase 'Wizard business' and a stern look gets the gate raised for you, and it slams shut behind you as you cross the bridge across the Salz, into Laurelorn proper. The road is sturdy and well-made but no longer maintained, and questing roots and bold saplings have begun to lever apart the stones. To each side young trees fill areas that had once been felled clear, and overhead the canopy seems to deliberately stretch out to fill as much of the sky as it can, leaving only a thin sliver of daylight above. Despite its darkness the forest is filled with life and the air with birdsong, and you catch many glimpses of flitting birds and darting rodents. But despite all that you catch barely a glimpse of ambient magic, and it takes close examination to see a shimmer of Ghyran afterglow in the trees. From experience you know that woods like this are usually thick with magic, but it seems the Laurelorn is an exception. It's not immediately obvious when you reach Oldenlitz, as only a drop in the quality of the road and a thinning of the canopy overhead are immediately obvious. Closer examination finds a great deal of rubble half-buried in the leaf litter and flagstones shattered so that a sapling can rise defiantly through what was once a stone floor. And the saplings themselves prove of interest, as you can feel a faint tug upon the pool of Ulgu within you as you approach, and a wisp of magical energy you release is drawn into the wood and sinks downwards and out of sight. "Lornalim ithil," says a familiar voice, and you refuse to jump. "Vicereine Cadaeth," you say as you straighten up. "You're looking very different than when we last met." She smiles as she approaches, brushing imaginary dirt off her outfit of leather and scale, with what looks like bark standing in for steel. "I was an envoy seeking to charm, where I am now a mother standing vigil over her children." She runs a fond hand over the leaves of the nearest sapling as she passes. "Lornalim ithil... I thought the Silver Wood was west of the Demst?" "The Verdan Ithil was once more than a few well-guarded glades. You could once find groves of the two varieties of lornalim throughout the entirety of Laurelorn and beyond, before the men of Nordland discovered their names were quite literal. They learned that if they see veins of silver or gold in the trees, they will find the same if they dig down." You watch as a second wisp of Ulgu is greedily drunk by the tree. "They're natural Waystones." "Yes, for a certain definition of 'natural'. Tributaries to the leyline-streams. But quite dependent on the metals they take their name from, and given a choice between material wealth and the continued existence of life on this world, your kind has a distressing tendency to choose wealth." You think again of Salzenmund's twin industries of silversmithing and carpentry and wince. "Ah," you say. "Our long resistance against Drakwald sapped both our and their strength, until they fell to Beastmen and we nearly with them. So when Nordland began to encroach, we measured what lornalim losses we could sustain without our forests becoming thick with stagnant magic and swarming with Beastmen, and for a time we achieved peace with the Nordlanders. But every new generation and each new Grand Baron wanted more, and when more was not given, they took anyway. We were faced with a slow extinction by Beastman predation, or a fast extinction by a new war. Until we encountered an army of Middenland while fighting the slow extinction, and found a third way forward. One that required only a few villages to die." She kneels down and runs a finger along a barely-visible vein of silver along a sapling's trunk. "If we had waited just a few more years, we would have felt the reactivation of Karak Eight Peaks ripple through the leylines and known that there may be a fourth way, a way not so steeped in blood. History seems to delight in making fools of us all." "This is why you wanted to meet me here? To make a point about the history between Empire and Eonir?" "Partly." She gives a sudden smile, almost managing to dispel the mood she's crafted. "And because curiosity is a powerful motivator. Though we will contribute no matter where it is that you will pool the efforts of Elf and Dwarf, we will not show you the wonders of Tor Lithanel unless it plays host to the work in question." "What wonders would those be?" you can't help but ask. "The towers and jewels of Tor Lithanel have captured the soul of many an artist, but I suspect most relevant to you would be the Library of Mournings, twice the age of your Teclis' White Tower. It contains scrolls that predate the Elven race, and scrolls written in the hands of Caledor, Astarielle, Maruviel, and Yvraine. Access to such a library would be of great benefit to the project, don't you think?" You take a breath. "It would," you say with incredible understatement, trying not to show how tempted you are. "So you would allow the project to be located within Tor Lithanel? Including all its associates?" "Dwarves and all. They never managed to reach Tor Lithanel in the turmoil of their War of Vengeance, and with the extinction of House Elywn at the Battle of the Schadensumpf, we have no more major houses from Kor Immarmor. So the High Council is now quite unanimous in letting bygones be bygones. We'll also be a lot freer to contribute our expertise to a local project - we have mages that will travel to contribute, but the Grey Lords prefer not to leave their forests, as do some of the more esoteric beings that contribute to our society." She gives an artful little smile and cocks a hip. "Myself included, if you've grown fond of my company." "I'll keep that in mind," you say simply. Though to your mundane sight she's simply standing there talking, you've watched the bulk of her soul flow from tree to tree like a nurturing mother bird, and you're quite sure you have only a fraction of her full attention. Part of you finds that intriguing, but another part is reminded that you're still not sure if you could identify her species with any confidence. "Please do. We've no intention of being the mirror to our cousins of Ulthuan, who always seek to control and only ever grant the meagrest of morsels. We want to build a lasting partnership, and a lasting peace, with the institutions of the Empire, so we can live in peace in our forest. Considering the beings that would be all too eager to fill the void if we passed from this world, isn't that in everyone's best interest?" She's certainly easier on the eyes than the Beastmen. You promise her that you'll have an answer for her soon before parting ways once more. You've got two possible hosts left to check, and a lot of hours airborne ahead of you.

Planning the Waystone Project, Part 3

Carcassonne is a Bretonnian state with an unusual reputation. For one, its position abutting the greenskin-infested Irrana Mountains and the rough, hilly terrain means its society is heavily militarized, but that does not seem to have infected its spirit and turned the people hard and joyless. Instead they take pride in being the bulwark for their more tranquil northern neighbours, and enjoy a close relationship with the neighbouring and famously beautiful duchy of Brionne. Secondly is a reputation that takes you some time to finagle out of Soizic: that they are quite relentlessly practical, and quite adept at finding ways around chivalry's more troublesome requirements without outright breaching them. This is best embodied in the traditions of Carcassone's shepherds. Chivalry states that peasants cannot be trusted to fight independently, but nobody can deny that shepherds need to be able to protect their flock from predators, and there's no harm in giving the peasants the training and equipment to do so effectively. As such the history of the duchy is littered with examples of shepherds banding together to fend off Orcish warbands without Knightly instruction. A step further than this is their use of mercenaries, which is of course very unchivalrous. But chivalry has nothing to say on the topic of hiring foreigners as shepherds, or on happening to lose a bag of gold while hiring them, or on having large bands of hired shepherds guard a single sheep that just happens to be in the path of a Waaagh. This is enough to get you open to the possibility of working with them, especially when combined with their recent good relations with Karak Norn and Karak Izor. Apart from a few minor Holds in the northern Grey Mountains, Bretonnia doesn't really border any Dwarfholds, but you suppose this would mean they maintain their view of Dwarves as distant legendary weaponsmiths instead of having to live with the day-to-day of touchy neighbours that still have it written down somewhere that three thousand years ago your ancestors sold them mouldy grain. So you're hopeful that the promise of even better relations with the Dwarves and the runic weapons that might come with that could be bartered for good terms with the Bretonnians. A message is sent through the Empire's diplomatic apparatus, and the eventual response has you travelling further west than you ever have previously, your gyrocopter from Karak Norn cautiously skirting Athel Loren and following the rivers until you finally reach the Duchy's unimaginatively-named capital of Castle Carcassonne. It's a shockingly large castle that takes up the entirety of a large island in the River Songez, with a shockingly small town clustered along the river bank. Near the center of the castle a single slender tower of pure white rises from the grey stone: the Tower of the Enchantress, one of the homes of the Fay Enchantress, the seemingly immortal manifestation of the Lady's will. Her word is paramount in Bretonnia, taking precedence over the authority of any Duke or King, and at her decree armies have ridden and Kings have been banished. To the stares of a gathering crowd you touch down in the jousting lists inside the walls, and you badger onlookers until you find one that speaks Reikspiel and send them off to let the Duke know that his appointment has arrived. Before long you're led into the heart of the castle through drab and utilitarian rooms lined with trophies and weapons until you reach the cabinet of Duke Huebald d'Carcassonne, a small, wiry, and dour-looking young man in a simple tabard flanked by a tall, plump, and pretty young woman in a red and blue dress. Both seem to be studiously ignoring you, which you begin to frown at until a steward sidles up to you. "What is the preferred address for madam?" he asks in a stage whisper. "Lady Magister Weber will be fine," you reply. "Lady Magister Weber," Duke Huebald says in greeting, only now seeming to notice you. "I am Duke Huebald d'Carcassonne of Carcassonne, and this is my wife, Duchess Schermilde, who will translate for me," he says in heavily accented but still intelligible Bretonnian. The Bretonni came into the Reik basin with the tribes that eventually gave rise to the Empire, and their language has not yet drifted so far as to be unintelligible to you - at least, not among the upper classes. The accent and variations become stronger as you go further down in social class, with the peasantry completely omitting the past tense from their speech and using future tense in its place for reasons you cannot begin to fathom. "A pleasure," Duchess Schermilde says with a curtsy, making no attempt to translate. "Likewise," you reply. The Duke gestures, and the steward and the man who led you here depart from the room. "You have a plan," he says leadingly. "The Grey College of the Empire, the Eonir of Laurelorn, and the Dwarves of Karak Eight Peaks seek to enter into a research project together to investigate the Waystones. There's debate as to where the research should be performed, and some feel it would avoid problems if it is located outside all three. So we look to our allies in the west." "We've been reading up on these Eonir," Schermilde says. "Fascinating people. Dangerous, of course, but only when provoked." "Bretonnia does not need monuments to banish evils. But there are many innocents we cannot protect, and Dwarves are good friends to have. We are willing to help." "Morgiana is too, our upstairs neighbour. She's a busy woman, but she says she's willing to give you a nudge or two in the right direction, and to have one of her helpers join your number." You raise your eyebrows at that. "A generous offer." Duke Huebald frowns, and exchanges a look with his wife, who nods. "We shall speak unrelatedly of other matters that we are pressed with, but nonetheless able to overcome with thanks to the Lady, so we need no mystical assistance with," she says. "To demonstrate the truth of our chivalrous nature, and so how worthy partners we would be." "Iron Orcs," the Duke says. "Like Black Orcs, but with the armour set into their skin, bearing runes of the Dark Gods. They come from the mountains in greater numbers every year." You grimace at that. Though the greenskins almost always stay true to their native Gods of Gork and Mork, that 'almost' covers more than enough nasty examples to give any ruler cause for concern, and motivation to seek esoteric answers - even if their societal rules prevent them from saying so outright. "You'll find few places as secure as Castle Carcassonne," Schermilde says, "and we do have some of these stones your letter described in the area, I visited one myself to confirm. And don't worry about supplies - by river we are joined to Quenelles and Brionne, and from Brionne by sea to the world. Though little is made here, anything can be brought here. Morgiana certainly imports plenty of equipment for her experiments." You nod. The Bretonnian navy does not consider itself bound by the Lady's prohibition against gunpowder, and as such their Galleons possess a formidable cannon broadside that is more than able to secure the Bretonnian coastline. "There is the question of status. I understand that Bretonnia has different ideas to the Empire about who can hold power..." "Most know better than to gainsay any magic-wielding women," Schermilde says with a smile. "And besides, you are a Knight of your Realm. Anyone that would not respect either of those is a cur that deserves whatever punishment you deem fitting." The Duke nods firmly. "Oh, and there is another thing. Morgiana said, what was it... 'your friend can visit with you as long as he makes no plans to stay'. Something about a colleague of yours, I suppose?" "I understand what she means," you say with a nod. You'd heard that Ranald is outright proscribed in Bretonnia, but you didn't have any plans to broadcast your faith of Him so didn't think it would cause problems. But it is nice to have that outright confirmed. "Thank you for meeting with me. I'll let you know as soon as I can where the project will be based out of. Even if it's not in Bretonnia, if it bears fruit we'll do our best to spread the benefits as widely as possible." "Good intentions have a way of fading with distance," Schermilde replies, her smile a little strained. "Do think it over." --- Getting in touch with Kislev seemed like it would be surprisingly easy: Kazrik spoke to Karak Kadrin who spoke directly to Kislev, since they've been working closely with them to try to reintegrate the newly-returned Karak Vlag. But after enough time had elapsed for you to get miffed, you sent word directly to the Ice Witches through Lord Magister Krammovitch's unofficial channels to see what was going on, and only then did you get a response through the official Dwarven ones. Slightly mollified, you make your way through the Gyrocarriage relay up the mountains towards Kislev City and your appointment in the Bokha Palace. At your arrival, a steward comes running to greet you and guide you through the long and winding path through the crumbling marble of the ancient palace. The layout is greatly confusing, partly because of the countless times it has been rebuilt and expanded over the years but mostly because the Ice Witches are always quite insistent on marrying into the Tzar's family, and every few generations this produces a throwback to the Khan-Queen that raises a new wing to the palace from ice that inevitably melts after her death. Impractical, perhaps, but it's the sort of thing that definitely leaves an impression. You're finally led into what you're told is the West Hall, an oak-panelled room with an enormous roaring fire dominating one wall and the others dotted with innumerable candles, battle flags, shields, and weapons. In the center of the room a very large young man with a very impressive moustache is sparring with a member of the Kreml Guard, saber clashing against axe as the guard is pushed back by an onslaught of blows that begin to wind down as the combatants notice your entry. "Dobry. Do widzenia, Kovnik," the young man says, before turning to you. "Atamanka Ved'ma Weber, yha?" The steward nods, and withdraws from the room along with the Kreml Guard at a jerk of the man's head. "Tsarevich Boris Bokha. My father left this matter to me, as it does not involve killing or eating. My friends who are your friends say it is important, and they would know. You have rocks that push back the Dewastacja?" "Yes. When they work properly, they form channels that would allow it to flow away to where it will not bother anybody." "Where is that place that it flows to?" he asks, his eyes narrowing. "Ulthuan. They have a magical vortex there that dumps it back into where it came from." He laughs. "Better answer than I expect. The sea-elves are annoying, but they know what they are doing. They still tell stories of Yrtle's final battle." Boris grabs a pair of chairs and drags them over to the fire with a grinding of wood on wood. "Sit. Talk. Tell me of this." You take a seat and marshal your thoughts. "Long ago, when magic first came to the world, there was so much of it that Daemons could walk freely. The Elves created the Great Vortex to drain most of it away, and built Waystones throughout the Old World and beyond to channel magic towards the Vortex." Boris nods. "Yha, there is one below the dungeons, glows white during blizzards. Always wondered what it was for." "But that was many years ago. They built them with the help of the Dwarves, who later became their enemy. Now nobody knows how to build them, and Cultists and Necromancers and Vampires seek to deactivate or destroy them, so there are always less. But there are Elves who are not of Ulthuan called the Eonir, and they are willing to work with the Dwarves of Karak Eight Peaks to try to understand them once more. So we can reactivate the ones that are dormant, and protect those that remain. Maybe even to build new ones." "And now everyone wants to be in charge, yha?" "Something like that." "And everyone comes running with promises. Well, here is Kislev's promise. You say there might be ways to push back Dewastacja? Restore Praag? Push back Troll Country? I say: to make this happen, all of Kislev will move mountains. You need gold? Kislev has gold. You need Ice Witch? They want make friends with me after father ignores them, they want me to take Ice Witch wife, I can make them cooperate. The Hag Witches? The kossars know they are mine, you can have Hag Witches. Ursun knows me, His priests will cooperate. If Elves in Erengrad want to stay in Erengrad, they must help. There is nothing I would not make happen if it means more Kislev and less Za. Do you understand?" You nod. "Good. I have gone to the returned Dwarves, spoken to them of you. You tore them from the grip of the Za after all had given up on them. After they had given up on them. Do the same for Kislev, and there would be no reward too great." --- You try to put your reeling thoughts back in order as you make your way back out of the palace. Rather a forceful personality on the Tsarevich, and he seems to have gotten a perhaps oversized idea of what the project might accomplish. You put a hand to your neck and feel the cord that Ranald's Coin dangles from, and sigh. The worst part is, you'd gotten exactly what you'd hoped for: full credit for the rescue of a Dwarfhold. You'd just hadn't really expected how dramatic that rescue ended up being, and now people have a great deal of expectations for you that you may not be able to live up to. But whatever trouble those expectations might bring you at some nebulous point in the future, right now they're opening doors. Laurelorn is waving a truly ancient library under your nose, Carcassonne will give full cooperation and a free hand as well as the input of the Fay Enchantress and her hand-picked representative, and Kislev will do just about anything in the hopes that it could lead to an encore of Karak Vlag, including browbeating their local magical traditions and possibly even the Elves into cooperation. Are these temptations worth the weight of expectations and the added complication of having to operate under their authority? Or would it be best to remain in the familiar territory of the Colleges or the Karak, under superiors with a much clearer view of the possibilities, who you're already practiced in managing? You're not entirely sure, and you may never be entirely sure, but you have to make the decision anyway. Who will Mathilde found the Waystone Project under the authority of? [ ] The Grey College [ ] Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Laurelorn [ ] Carcassonne [ ] Kislev - There will be a 24-hour moratorium. - The winner of this vote will not only determine the setting of the next arc of the quest, it will also determine my new forum avatar. - Wherever it is set, Mathilde will be able to maintain her home and relationships in Karak Eight Peaks. Gyrocarriages are wonderful things. - I won't do a 'canonical' list of benefits and detriments for each option, because it would be based on Mathilde's best guesses but would be treated as WoQM. I encourage the thread to build one (or several) of its own; if any complete misunderstandings take hold I'll step in to dispel them.